<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="yja-11-march-1857.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-03-11">March
                        11, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-03-11">March
                        11, 1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare
                    Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region>/><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-04-07">April 7, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="YW">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter"><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_035.jpg"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>E. C. Oxford Geo.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-03-11">March 11th 1857</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My Dearest Mollie</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>You received my <hi rend="underline">note</hi> a few days since, I suppose,
                    acquainting you, that I should be necessarily detained
                    <unclear>or</unclear>delayed in answering your last letter. I reckon too, you
                    begin to feel or think that my <hi rend="underline">week's grace</hi>is now
                    about expired, well, Dearest, it is out <sic>to night</sic> I believe, and yet I
                    can hardly claim <hi rend="underline">just a few minutes</hi> of <add
                        place="supralinear">
                        <hi rend="underline">as</hi>
                    </add>my own, even though I desire to devote them to thee alone- but I will
                    venture <hi rend="underline">any how</hi>to write you a few lines, for as you
                    said of me <hi rend="underline">I know you deserve</hi>them, and I can not, I
                        <hi rend="underline">will</hi> not withhold any longer, that which I know
                    and feel <add place="supralinear">so</add>justly belongs to <hi rend="underline"
                        >thee</hi>.<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_036.jpg"/>But, Dearest, in the first place, I have many apologies to
                    make, and I think they are due to yourself and just to me. My remarks in
                    reference to the anxiety and suspense (well, well Mollie I've broke my gold pen
                    right here) which I felt, were perhaps rather strong, and expressed in language,
                    as I too truly apprehended, which was of so dubious and equivocal meaning as to
                    convey to your heart rather unpleasant sensations. Believe me, Dearest, it was
                    an unintentional as well as an unguarded stroke, --for I could never trifle thus
                    with your tenderest feelings,-- inflicted in the moment of intense emotion and
                    the excitement of that earnest affection which the poor limping <hi
                        rend="underline">ambiguous</hi>language of that hour <hi rend="underline">so
                        far</hi>failed to express to you.</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>It was not, My Dearest, in the spirit of censure that I wrote them; I chide not
                        <hi rend="underline">your</hi>delays, for yours are always good excuses,
                    (though you say you have none) and I accept them. I did not then write them, to
                    reprove your delay, by no means; nor did I censure the past to amend the future,
                    and yet, Dearest Mollie, those sentiments are <add place="supralinear"
                        >were</add>the true utterances of my heart. Yes, Mollie, of that heart,
                    whose every pulse claims to be a throb responsive to thine; They were
                    utterances, voices, echos, as it were, from the very soul of affection, and how
                    sorry indeed was I to learn that they had pained thy heart-- but why should I
                    write so much about <hi rend="underline">this</hi>, were it <hi rend="underline"
                        >a crime</hi>, then it might need some extenuation, a flagrant offense, then
                    might I waste time to palliate it,<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_037.jpg"/> but as it is neither, (<del
                        rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="strikethrough" unit="words" extent="1"/></del>) but what I regard, as the <add
                        rend="supralinear">most</add> indubitable evidence and unmistakeable
                    manifestation on either side.-- (The <sic>strongh</sic> expressions and rather,
                    as some might think, extravagant picture of anxiety on the one and the pained
                    heart and moistened eye of affection on the other)-- of that true and vital
                    union of hearts which (<hi rend="underline">I trust</hi>) we have enjoyed for so
                    many years, and which I trust we shall in years to come enjoy <add
                        rend="supralinear">still</add>more <hi rend="underline">intimately</hi> and
                        <hi rend="underline">inseparably</hi>.-- <del><gap reason="strikethrough" unit="words" extent="2"/></del> I shall now
                    hasten on, knowing that you will not love me less for having told you how glad I
                    am <hi rend="underline">to be</hi>with you and when I cannot <hi
                        rend="underline">be</hi>with you, how I rejoice <hi rend="underline">to
                        hear</hi>from you- and when either fails, how torturous and painful the
                    interval <pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_038.jpg"/>that <unclear>we</unclear> are separated, that holds our hearts
                    from <del rend="strikethrough">the</del><add place="supralinear">sweet</add>
                    communion. Pardon me, Dearest, for writing so much about that, I could not say
                    less.</p>
                <p>I have just now arrived at the <hi rend="underline">threshold</hi> of my letter--
                    and doubtless you think I ought to have been there before now-- and I find that I
                    am scarcely able to enter; I am <sic>litterally</sic>, Dearest, nearly worn out; duty!
                    duty!! study! study!! clamors at my heels all day long, and at night fatigued
                    and weary I sit down to write with brain addled, thoughts confused, and scarcely
                    strength or energy enough to originate a thought or conceive an idea, and so it
                    is to night, as you perceive from what has preceded, and no hope for
                    the better.</p><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_039.jpg"/>
                <p>But, Dearest, I promised <del rend="strikethrough">you</del> that I had a few
                    items for you, reserved especially for this communication, in addition to which
                    I thought I would also add some little fragments of news (or "reflected
                    fragments" as Mrs. Cross calls them) as news is such <hi rend="underline">a
                        rare</hi> thing with me, and still <hi rend="underline">rarer</hi> in our
                    communications.</p>
                <p>In company with Prof. Williams I had the privilege on last Saturday week of
                    visiting Madison, by the way, quite a noted place for its colleges, schools and
                    general intelligence, for the high toned moral character and dignified
                    sentiments and deportment of its citizens. As we were there for solicitation
                    and our only business was to establish a Lodge of Knights of Jericho, (at the
                    head of which<pb/>we found the <hi rend="underline">Pastor</hi><add
                        place="supralinear"/><hi rend="underline"
                    ><unclear>D'nl</unclear>Kelsey</hi>of the Church surrounded by a noble and
                    zealous corpse of the oldest and most valiant citizens of the place, all of the
                    same fold, (Methodists I mean) we had some more attention paid us than had it
                    been a visit on any other occasion-- (but by the by, Prof W. was once Prof.
                    there in the Meth. Col.) and therefore I was well accommodated and provided
                    for.-- Pardon my awful (--)ses.<add place="inline">parentheses</add>
                In the evening I went around to the College buildings and made my circuit embrace
                    the principal boarding houses. I saw many <hi rend="underline">beautiful
                        faces</hi>, notwithstanding the compliment quite the contrary which I heard
                    a <hi rend="underline">Yound American</hi><unclear>pay</unclear>them.--
                I could hardly realize the place or the thought that I was passing<pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_040.jpg"/>through
                        <add place="supralinear">the</add>streets of Madison, hemmed in on all sides
                    by so many bright eyes and happy, smiling faces as met my askant glance from
                        <add place="supralinear">to</add>the window of their study. I fancied myself
                    more than once in LaGrange, but as quickly from there I found myself at Macon,
                    but no <hi rend="underline">Dearest One's</hi> glance, or smile or eye, kindled this heart or yey, for I
                    knew, My <hi rend="underline">Only Beloved</hi>, was not one of <hi
                        rend="underline">them</hi>, but that she was far away, and that made me sad.
                    So pensively I passed from their midst, but as I was wending along betwixt a
                    "smile and a tear", half glad and half sad, about, I knew not what, lo! I came
                    to the <hi rend="underline">grave yard</hi>-- the fittest place for me then--
                    and entering, soon<pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_041.jpg" n="9th"/>I stood the living above the dead--as if in obedience to
                    the poetic injunction--<quote><l>"Ye living men come view the ground</l><l>Where you
                    must shortly lie,"</l></quote>
I had appeared there. It was a solemn place, the pantings
                    of the multitude died away before they reached it, no thoroughfare with its
                    jumbling of carriages and rattling wheels and tides of (active) life, broke upon
                    the stillness of the scene, nor invaded the rights of the sleepers; no unki<add
                        rend="supralinear">n</add>d foot or careless <add rend="supralinear"
                        >eye</add> wandered amid the habitations of the lonely dead or traced the
                    brief epitaph at once their history and eulogisms. It was a solemn place, I
                    repeat again, but I love solitude and solemn things and therefore I loved that
                    place<pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_042.jpg"/>and indulging (the) a meditative mood I found it good to be there.
                    "Solitude" says our great <hi rend="underline">Revivalist</hi>, "makes the head
                    clearer and heart better." So I hope it was with me that evening. I wandered
                    amid the tombs, read inscriptions, meditated, thought of the past, the present
                    and the future, thanked God that while below me lay "the countless dead" above
                    me was (<hi rend="underline">the</hi> heaven", rejoiced that though soon I
                    should be as they, that I had a hope that I should be with Christ. Learned many
                    impressive lessons from <hi rend="undeline">its</hi> pages, resolved to live
                    better, more devoted to God, nearest to heaven and in Christ. I forgot to  
                    mention that at a little distance northward runs the R. Road where the<pb/><sic>the</sic>cars
                    as they pass over the lofty embankment seemed <add rend="supralinear">as</add>
                    if intent, to point the weary traveller to his last and final home; yes, it
                    struck me very forcibly Dearest, to see the cars sweeping by there freighted
                    with immortal destinies, and I immediately thought of the passage-- which runs
                    somehow thus--"<unclear>That</unclear>day will come when he that runs shall
                    read," and thought I, this must surely be an instance of its fulfillment-- for
                    who, that looked upon that place, did not read his own destiny and his (final)
                    inscription, thus--<quote>"<hi rend="underline">'Tis the birthright of
                        mankind<lb/>to die."</hi></quote>
                Many <add rend="supralinear">more</add>interesting reflections and thoughts were
                    suggested there, but I have not time now to speak of them, I fear I am wearing
                    your patience any how.</p>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_043.jpg"/>
                <p>Suffice <add rend="supralinear">it</add>then to say in conclusion for the <add
                        rend="supralinear">
                        <hi rend="underline">to</hi>
                    </add>night, that I left the <hi rend="underline">grave yard></hi> better in
                    heart and in head than when I entered its portals, and hastened back to town, it
                    being then late in the evening, took supper and immediately entered upon the
                    discharge of our business-- the instituting of a K-J-Lodge; we concluded about
                    10AM and took the 11AM train back to Oxford reaching here about 1PM, had a fine
                    night's rest &amp;c and arose early and prepared for the duties and
                    exercises of the sabbath, a brief account of which I will give you tomorrow
                    night if nothing prevents more than I now know of to the contrary.</p><closer>So
                        until then, I commit thee <add rend="supralinear">to</add>My Dear Savior,
                        and bid <hi rend="underline">you</hi><add rend="supralinear">thee</add>an
                        affectionate <hi rend="underline">Good
                        Bye</hi>.--<signed>Young</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
