<TEI xml:id="yja-31-march-1857.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-03-31">March
                        31, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen </sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie, <date when="1857-03-31">March 31,
                        1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book
                    Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="thyun">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->
                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>
                    <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement/>
                            <region/>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
			<item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-03-25">March 25, 2009</date>
                <name>Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_010.jpg"/>

           <div type="letter">

<head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, March 31, 1857]</head>

                <note resp="#yja" place="inline">N. B.<p>I will have to send this contrary to your
                        request.-- So you must pardon it and write back on Saturday or just as soon
                        as you can.-- I'll be patient.--Young</p></note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>E. C. Oxford Geo.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-03-31">March 31st 1857</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My Dearest Mollie--</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I would gladly avail myself of any opportunity that presents itself of writing to
                    you even though it be but a few lines at a time-- therefore as I have a few
                    leisure moments now, I trust that to spend them in sweet communion with <hi
                        rend="underline">my Dearest Mollie</hi>, will not be altogether unacceptable
                    to thee.-- I have not time to enter into a full and comprehensive answer to your
                    letter so full of affection and confidence <hi rend="underline">in him
                    who </hi>hopes at no <hi rend="underline">very distant</hi> day to share with <hi
                        rend="underline">thee the</hi>/burdens and crosses of life of which you
                    spoke 

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_011.jpg"/> 

                    in such simple and pathetic
                    language.-- <hi rend="underline">Mollie</hi>, I have read your letter over and
                    over again; it is sad, yet that sadness is sweet when I see it united with such
                    tenderness of spirit such abasement of self-- it is a strain of sadness such as
                    is calculated to work profitableness to the soul; it is a sadness such as the
                    wise man contemplates when he said it is better to go to the house of mourning
                    than to the place of mirth.-- Yes, Mollie, it did, though, unanticipated by you,
                    give me more pleasure than pain. And how can that be, does not My Dear One ask?
                    Well, Mollie, I'll tell you how it is.-- I have had the same experiences myself,
                    I had to suffer mortification, disappointment and anguish from the very same
                    causes. I had to be abased, humbled and taught my own weakness, and 

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_011.jpg"/>

                    depravity, my utter helplessness and insufficiency of myself to accomplish any
                    good, just as you have stated in reference to yourself, your own heart; now
                    Dearest, in all these things our experience does not diverge at all, but
                    mutually coincide throughout.--</p><p>You have now arrived at a most important
                    crisis, <del rend="strikethrough">where</del>in the history of your religious
                    experience where you can just begin to see the glory of being a <hi
                        rend="underline">thorough devoted, entirely converted Christian</hi>, you
                    are now my <hi rend="underline">precious Mollie </hi>occupying a high stand point
                    from which God permits you to look <del rend="strikethrough">below</del><add
                        place="supralinear">down</add>upon the <hi rend="underline">world as it
                        is</hi>--upon <hi rend="underline">your heart as it is</hi>, now Dearest
                    that is a <hi rend="underline">precious</hi>privilege and one which you should
                    value very highly because now that you have seen the deceitfulness, the corrupt
                    blindness 

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_012.jpg"/>

                    of your heart, you can turn
                    away more successfully from its suggestions and dictates and flee to the Closet
                    for Communion with God, with him who knoweth the secret intents and purposes of
                    your heart.-- I might say a great deal on this interesting and fruitful subject
                    but it is all needless, but suffice it to say- My Dearest, that you are <del
                        rend="strikethrough">now</del><hi rend="underline">almost</hi>right, if not
                        <hi rend="underline">quite right</hi>, and I
                    believe Dearest from your experience that you have shared some
                    of the fulness of the promised blessings of God-- that you have had great
                    encouragement to be vigilant and vigorous still in the struggle; the fiercest of
                    the conflict perhaps is over now, for the powers of darkness are beginning to
                    yield and fall back when the horrid deceit and crimes of the soul 

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_013.jpg"/>

                    when the <add place="supralinear"
                    >its</add>secret faults and weaknesses are beginning to show themselves you have
                    overcome the greatest and strongest of <add place="supralinear">his</add>powers-
                    that is-<del rend="strikethrough">the</del>to see yourself as you are, that is
                    what Satan would have us blind to always, and as long as he can have that he
                    knows the case is a sure one, but thanks to God, <hi rend="underline">My
                        Mollie</hi>, that the secret path, like that around Thermopylae of old has
                    been found out by you, and that you have been enabled to defeat the purposes of
                    your great arch-enemy by getting <del rend="strikethrough">a proper</del>so to
                        speak,<hi rend="underline">into</hi>yourself and beholding for yourself the
                    hidden works which he was carrying on there.-- Raise the shout now, My Dearest
                    for the Victory is surely yours, you will Triumph, though the devil with
                        
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_014.jpg"/>

                    all his legions oppose you, you may
                    expect a desperate encounter- you perhaps have had one, <del
                        rend="strikethrough">for</del>Leonidas and his brave companions did not give
                    back when they stood in that narrow pass, you recollect, but met the enemy and
                    fell on the field-- so these daring presumptuous sins these legions <del
                        rend="strikethrough">from</del> commissioned from below to torment and worry
                    your soul will bravely contest it with you till the very last moment, but just
                    as sure <del rend="strikethrough">as the</del>as the Spartans fell at
                    Thermopylae will they fall before the armed power of God; trust <hi
                        rend="underline">in God</hi> then my dearest, My Beloved;-- I can rejoice
                    over the account you gave me of your experience because I think all will <hi
                        rend="underline">soon</hi>be right, God grant it may be.</p>

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_014.jpg"/>

                <p>Sad account! why Mollie you could have told me nothing <hi rend="underline">(that
                        seems)</hi> so auspicious as that; that is the sure sign of your progress.--
                    Oh! be encouraged; I am <hi rend="underline">almost</hi>led to say that you have
                    obtained that for which you seek.-- Another one of my friends has been enabled
                    to obtain and rejoice in <del rend="strikethrough">the</del><hi rend="underline"
                        >perfect assurance</hi> of acceptance,- of perfect Love, and we have
                    frequently talked it over; (it occured since I wrote you last,) and I find that
                    our experiences very much resemble and both greatly, particularly as to doubts
                    and fears, coincide with yours.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Thank God</hi>, any how My Dearest, yes I do <hi
                        rend="underline">right now</hi>, that you have been brought this far in his
                    knowledge and

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_015.jpb"/>

                    <sic>and</sic> in the light
                    of his countenance.--</p>
                <p>You lack nothing at all My Dearest now, according to your experience, that I
                    know, that keeps you from that perfect Love. I believe you have obtained it. I
                    will venture to say so <hi rend="underline">any how</hi>- for how is it that you
                    were not so blessed before when you asked? You said then that you could not
                    believe God would give it to you right <hi rend="underline">then</hi>.-- Well
                    now, how was it when you said you <hi rend="underline">would</hi> believe, did
                    not the blessing come, did you not feel happy, did you not rejoice? Oh! My
                    Dearest, that was the obstacle all the while, and that <hi rend="underline"
                        >surely</hi> was the blessing which you received as soon as it was removed-
                        <sic>wasn't</sic> Dearest? Yes, Glory be to God-- don't you say so too from
                    your very heart-- Mollie?</p>

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_016.jpg"/>

                    <p>But you
                    feared, and indeed you said, that you could not believe you had received such a
                    blessing, judging from your life the next day-- now Mollie I don't think there
                    was anything in <hi rend="underline">that</hi> which could authorize you to
                    disbelieve it; I don't doubt but that you felt some bitter regrets and that your
                    conscience smote you some for having neglected what you purposed doing-- but my
                    Dearest, I cannot see that that was a particular violation of any (very
                    impervious) <hi rend="underline">duty</hi> or that the neglect of once or twice
                    reading the Scriptures under such circumstances should cause you to doubt your
                    acceptance, to doubt what the Lord had done for you-- no My Beloved I don't
                    think that can be any evidence at all 

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_017.jpg"/>

                    that you were not blessed with a full salvation.--</p><p>Your resolutions were
                    firm and your intentions were bright towards God, then let not your heart be
                    discouraged for says Thomas A. Kempis, "it is <hi rend="underline">no
                        illusion</hi> that thou art sometimes wrapt in an ecstacy but presently
                    returnest to the accustomed weaknesses of thy heart", by no means, but it was
                    not even weakness in thy heart nor the absence of a better purpose that caused
                    you to neglect that which you so much regretted, no but rather the pressure of
                    circumstances.-- Oh! My Beloved, arise and rejoice in the Lord, burst the
                    fetters of darkness and give glory to the Lord, God of our Salvation.-- My
                    Beloved I cannot write 

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_017.jpg"/> 

                    any more now on these very interesting themes, nor
                    have I time to notice all your letter, but I do believe-- and I must say press
                    on-- that you are <hi rend="underline">almost</hi>home, My Dearest Mollie. I
                    never fail to remember you, and the Lord <hi rend="underline">will</hi> answer
                    your petitions, and I can't help but believe, it is his work that's now being
                    accomplished in your experience-- don't then get discouraged but when you sin go
                    to God and confess it and he will pardon and accept you for Christ's sake.-- You
                    know how I <sic>done</sic><add place="supralinear">had to do</add>, what
                    expedient I had to resort to when I was convicted and awaken'd to a sense of my
                    duty in reference to this blessing. I tried my rellious, wicked, <hi
                        rend="underline">deceitful heart</hi> till I could not trust it in

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_018.jpg"/> 

                    a single instance so I took my little (vade
                    mecum) <del rend="strikethrough">
                        <unclear>[illegible word]</unclear>
                    </del> commonplace book and set down every sin, every thing which I thought or
                    felt to be in my way, and that is <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the way I would
                    overcome myself.-- I would always forget <add place="supralinear">neglect</add>
                    and excuse myself, because I had forgotten exactly what I promised I would do.--
                    Perhaps some such expedient as that might aid you a great deal in carrying out
                    your purposes-- a <hi rend="underline">minute</hi> enumerations of your
                        <sic>principle</sic> obstacles and difficulties set down in a book where you
                    could refer to them every day would keep your memory alive and retention of all
                    these things which otherwise you might forget and neglect.</p>

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_019.jpg"/>

                    <p><date>Apr. 1st</date>I have a very
                    few minutes this morning, My Dearest, of leisure but <hi rend="underline">the
                        short time</hi>I will spend with <hi rend="underline">you</hi>.-- I had
                    another conversation yesterday evening with my friend who has so lately
                    professed and does now enjoy the blessing of Perfect Love, of Entire
                    Sanctification.-- Oh! Mollie he is a noble fellow, such as this world presents
                    but seldom and there are but few such in <hi rend="underline">this College</hi>
                    I assure you if <hi rend="underline">any at all</hi>. He is one of the Senior
                    Class, is already licensed to exhort and intend preaching and joining the
                    Conference next winter.-- I love to be with him. I enjoy myself so much now in
                    his company-- he and myself are all that have made any professions as 

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_020.jpg"/>

                    as to this last attainment, and I assure you,
                    My Dearest, that a tie has in that been matured which binds and attaches us much
                    more strongly than ever before-- if then it is so with him, Mollie, how (will)
                        <add place="supralinear">
                        <hi rend="underline">is</hi>
                    </add>it (be) with us, how dear<del rend="strikethrough">ly</del> do you suppose
                    thou art to me now?</p><p>Why Mollie, God bless you, I feel the more and more I
                love God and the nearer and nearer I get to his throne, the better I love you, the
                better I can appreciate the <hi rend="underline">gift</hi> which God has chosen for
                me-- yes the better I can appreciate and the more I feel the inestimable value of
                    <hi rend="underline">her</hi> whom I feel the Lord has chosen for my companion
                and partner through life.-- Isn't it so with you Dearest? Isn't it true
                    Mollie?--Yes--</p>

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_020.jpg"/>

                   <p>Well, Dearest, you spoke sometime <add place="supralinear"
                        >since</add>of Miss Nellie Dozier being such a sweet girl, will you now
                    please give me a <hi rend="underline">particular</hi>account of <hi
                        rend="underline">her</hi>; I want to know how she stands in College-- what
                    her reputation and name among the faculty and students-- what her temper and
                    disposition-- whether she is cheerful in spirit and happy or given to melancholy
                    and seclusion-- what are <sic>he</sic> religious feelings and standing-- what
                    does she anticipate as to a future life-- does she speak of a desire to live and
                    labor in the vineyard of her Lord or what? Please now Dearest answer me all
                    these questions for I am <hi rend="underline">particularly</hi> interested and I
                    know you are the very one to apply to for such information. I will tell you
                        
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_021.jpg"/>

                    sometime why I ask you all these
                    things-- but I can't wait, I'll tell you now.-- This <hi rend="underline"
                        >good</hi> friend of mine has somewhat of an interest <sic>
                        <hi rend="underline">her</hi>
                    </sic> and he was speaking to me of his--, in Macon and <hi rend="underline"
                        >that</hi><add place="supralinear">she</add>is the <hi rend="underline"
                        >one</hi>, so I want you to tell me sure, Dearest; I love her too Mollie
                    because <hi rend="underline">you</hi>recommend her as such a sweet girl, and
                    because her <hi rend="underline">lover</hi>, if I can be allowed so to speak, is
                    such a <hi rend="underline">good fellow</hi>himself and such a particular friend
                    of mine.</p><p>You must not, Dearest, hint anything of this to her at all but be
                    perfectly private about it.-- Write me just such an account of her as you would
                    be willing. <hi rend="underline">She</hi>should see <hi rend="underline">if
                        you'll let me show it to him</hi>.</p>

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_022.jpg"/>

                    <p>I have not time to write you the news, in fact, I have none to write.-- I
                    wrote to Mellie again the other day. I spent last Saturday in Atlanta, first up
                    at the Trout home where <hi rend="underline">we</hi>staid, and Oh! so many
                    pleasant recollections as came to me there. I loved to look at the stairways and
                    passages along which we passed together. I felt like I was getting most to My
                    Mollie again but ah she was far away-- I've got a <hi rend="underline"
                        >pretty</hi>for you Mollie, do you want it? Or don't you like <hi
                        rend="underline">"pretties</hi>?</p><p>Well I am out now don't you think--
                    if I've got down to such insignificance as that.-- So I'll quit off.--

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_023.jpg"/>

                    But I must say again press on, press on My
                    Beloved One.</p><p>Yes "press forward, the <hi rend="underline">prize</hi>is<hi
                        rend="underline">in view</hi>. And a <hi rend="underline">crown</hi>of<hi
                        rend="underline">bright glory is waiting for you"</hi>.--</p><p>Mollie, I do
                    have some very happy times indeed, but I have to deplore my exceeding
                    sinfulness, my proneness to go astray and it keeps me very <hi rend="underline"
                        >low</hi> very humble in God's presence, though not half as much as it
                    ought.--</p><p>Pray for me, My Sweet One, that the Lord may uphold me and
                    strengthen me for all the conflicts of life.-- I thought I was about to <hi
                        rend="underline">close</hi>, but here comes another thought which I do not
                    desire to keep back from the <hi rend="underline">only one</hi>who can share my
                    heart, its affections, its

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_023.jpg"/>

                    thoughts and hopes.</p><p>I have been exercised a
                    great deal here of late and solicited by several in reference to beginning the
                    work of the Ministry <hi rend="underline">now</hi>. I want to do just what <hi
                        rend="underline">God would have me do.</hi> I have given myself entirely
                    into his hands and in reference to this important matter &#x0026; calling. I
                    have submitted it to him as to whether I should be <sic>liciensed</sic> and
                    begin <hi rend="underline">now</hi>or wait till some other time after or about
                    the close of my College course.-- What do you think about it, My Dearest Mary? I
                    confide all my heart to thee and you shall be my counselor, in everything, I
                    don't intend to keep anything back from such a Dear One, and I never expect to
                    begin anything of any very great or serious importance without 

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_024.jpg"/>

                     first consulting with <hi rend="underline"
                        >thee</hi>and getting thy advice.-- Now please write your thoughts in
                    referencence to this and send me your opinion.-- Be sure to pray for me My
                    Dearest, much and often and particularly in reference to this duty.--</p><p>The
                    Lord's will and not mine be done.-- Amen.</p><p>Mollie I feel like praising God
                    and serving him <hi rend="underline">too</hi>this morning.--</p><p>Read the <hi
                        rend="underline">Riches of Grace</hi>, Mollie in connection with your
                    present experience and struggles for entire sanctification and holiness. My
                    friend is reading it now in connection with his as I suggested and he has
                    already been greatly blessed and confirmed in his experience-- try to think of
                    nothing else nor talk of little else until you feel entirely free and have
                        
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_025.jpg"/>

                    that deep abiding peace which always
                    follows that great change, which introduces the soul into the ocean of God's
                    love.-- Let not your mind be distracted and confused by too many things at a
                    time, but let it be exercised much on that subject.-- And if I were you Mollie
                    and could get a convenient opportunity I would talk with some good old Christian
                    who professes such a state-- but if you will read the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Riches of Grace</hi> which is nothing else but a number of experiences--
                    and pray much you will be sure to get all the counsel you need. I think, it
                    would be best to read it as private as you can, so that your soul and mind can
                        be

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_026.jpg"/>

                    fully exercised, so that when you
                    feel like praying you can just drop down before God and plead for what you
                    need.-- Do that Mollie, please don't neglect it and I think it will make all
                    right sure enough.--</p>
                    <salute>May God bless you <hi rend="underline">every day</hi> and give you soon the
                        blessed assurance that your consecration is accepted and that your name is
                        registered with the sanctified and pure of earth and the Redeemed and happy
                        in heaven, is the humble and fervent prayer of your Devoted and Loving</salute>
			<closer>
                    <signed>Young J. Allen</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="envelope">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_008.jpg"/>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1857-03-31">March 31st '57</date>
                </dateline>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <address><persName>Miss Mollie Houston</persName><lb/><addrLine>W. F. College</addrLine><lb/><addrLine>Macon</addrLine><lb/><addrLine>Georgia</addrLine></address>
                </p>
                <p>Care of<lb/>Prest. Smith</p>

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF2_009.jpg"/>

            </div>
        </back>
    </text>


</TEI>
