<TEI xml:id="yja-1856-11-17.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1856-10-10">November 17, 1856</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
              <choice>
                <sic>A.Y.J.W.Allen</sic>
                  <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
              </choice>
            </name>
	</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston <date when="1856-11-17">Nov. 17 1856</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                
           
             <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date> 
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
		    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item> 
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-05-07">May 7, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="sat">Sue Trowbridge</name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
 <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_057.jpg"/>
            <div type="letter">

         <head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, November 17, 1856]</head>      

                <opener><dateline><name type="place">Emory College, Oxford Geo.</name><date when="1856-11-17"> Nov.17th 1856</date></dateline><lb/>
                    <salute>My dearest Mollie.<lb/></salute></opener>
                <p>Yours of the 14th inst. mail was received on yester eve with a welcome of kindness and pleasure which belongs to the greeting of thy letters alone. It arrived Saturday morning but I was absent on a visit <hi rend="underline">down to Starrsville</hi>.  I had an excellent time, Mollie, with my old friends there; spent some pleasant hours in the company of some charming ladies, <hi rend="underline">last</hi> summer graduates of the <unclear>SM??</unclear>  <hi rend="underline">one</hi> of whom seemed disposed to avail herself of <hi rend="underline">Leap Year</hi> privileges, but met with <hi rend="underline">no</hi> encouragement, or rather <hi rend="underline">success</hi> in so <hi rend="underline">attempting</hi>.</p> 
                <p>But, my Dearest One, I have something more happy, more glorious, more soul-rejoicing to tell you, than that I had a pleasant visit to Starrsville and a pleasurable time among my friends there- and you too are intimately connected with and interested in it.</p>

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_058.jpg"/>

                <p>You spoke of never being satisfied until you shall have attained and realized the maximum of Christian enjoyment here, the blessing of <hi rend="underline">Perfect Love</hi>, of Entire Sanctification and you appealed to me if I had <hi rend="underline">it</hi> not to seek it with thee, or if it were mine to aid you all I could in securing it.  I thank the Lord that you ever made such an <hi rend="underline">appeal</hi> to me, it aroused my "sluggish soul," my "drowsy powers" unabated, and I promised that <hi rend="underline">with thee</hi> I <hi rend="underline">would</hi> seek it for I <hi rend="underline">had it not then</hi>.  I thenceforth, My Dearest, began to yield myself more unhesitatingly, more unreservedly into the hands of the Lord than ever before.  I soon found <hi rend="underline">5</hi> more who were anxiously striving for Holiness of heart, purity of life, the <hi rend="underline">"rest of faith"</hi> the "groaning to be set free" from all <hi rend="underline">inbred sin</hi>, all <hi rend="underline">carnality</hi> of mind, from <hi rend="underline">everything</hi>, in a word, that was offensive in the sight of God.  I shall not enter into details now, as it is so near the close of the term and I will soon be permitted to see you "face to face" and

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_058.jpg"/>

 tell you what glorious things have been done for me wherof "I am exceedingly glad" yea <hi rend="underline">happy</hi>- but I will simply tell you that the Lord has done for me far greater things than could my heart ever conceive.  I tell you Mollie, I misinformed you before, as to Sanctification being necessarily a <hi rend="underline">gradual</hi> work, nay I've found out better since, it comes like justification, just as soon as we are ready to receive it, just as soon as we have consecrated <hi rend="underline">all</hi>,<hi rend="underline">all</hi> to God, then the blessing is there.  Oh! <hi rend="underline">my Dearest Mary</hi>, I feel to day like a new creature in Christ; I've given up all my indulgencies, matters not how seemingly innocent and inoffensive before Heaven, all evil propensities, all besetting sins, which before rendered my religious life so in uniform, so insconstant, which kept me always sinning and repenting- and now I am the Lord's; I feel that God <hi rend="underline">does</hi> accept the poor offering and claim me as his own; blessed be God for such an assurance.  My peace has been abundant ever since last

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_059.jpg"/>

                Nov 16 '56

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_060.jpg"/>

                Monday night, my love and joy full and overflowing often during that time.  Yes Mollie; would that I could do more for Christ, for His Cause, for the wretched of the Earth, for sinful man:- Oh!  Mollie, join with me in praising and giving glory, <hi rend="underline">eternal</hi> glory to God for what He has done for Your poor unworthy <hi rend="underline">One</hi>-  Pardon me for being so disconnected, so scattering in my remarks above, I have not time to write to a careful arrangement and order of sentence nor Sentiment- but I trust you understand that another great change has been wrought for me since last I wrote to thee.  I will leave this now to resume it again when I meet you; then will my joy be to tell you of the wonders of God's love as revealed and realized by unworthy me.</p>
                <p>I have no news atall, Mollie, to give you, I received a letter from Matt, last week, <hi rend="underline">only</hi> the second one at that.  I suppose you <del rend="strikethrough">hav</del> will have seen her perhaps before you get this.

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_061.jpg"/>

            She said she started up there the other day but found you were absent and stopped in Grantville, and stated that she would pay you a visit <hi rend="underline">this</hi> week.</p>
                <p> I have <hi rend="underline">much,</hi> <hi rend="underline">much</hi> to tell you My dearest, though not properly under the head of news, which I will reserve for <hi rend="underline">our</hi> <hi rend="underline">meeting</hi>, which I trust will not be quite two weeks hence.  I shall come to see you just as soon as I get home; you need not expect any <hi rend="underline">note</hi>, Mollie, but you may expect <hi rend="underline">me</hi> every day till I come after I get home, which will be either on Friday night, or the next morning near two weeks hence (on Friday night week then).</p>
                <p>You must not fail to accompany me to the Conference, will you Mollie?</p>
                <p>You must write me another very long letter before I leave here, Dearest,- <hi rend="underline">I will not lose confidence in you, no, no.</hi> but now you must write me sure before I leave and just as soon as you get this too.</p>

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_061.jpg"/>

<p>Ah! <hi rend="under">work</hi> and <hi rend="under">study</hi> <hi rend="under">all the day</hi> and in the <hi rend="under">evening 'stead of</hi> play <hi rend="under">With work and study writing combine</hi> And thus you'll rapidly improve your mind- and <hi rend="under">cheer thine own loved one</hi>:  Pardon the above artless rhyme, but heed, please, its request.</p>
                <p>My Dear, like you I'm ashamed of such a letter but it is the best that I can do now, accept it then from him who is thine and only thine</p><lb/>
                <closer>Forever Young Allen</closer>
                <postscript><p>Please answer by Saturday morning if you can or at least by Monday morning. Young</p></postscript>

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_062.jpg"/>              
                
                </div></body></text>
</TEI>