<TEI xml:id="yja-1856-09-10.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1856-09-10">September 10, 1856</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
                <name type="person">
                    <choice>
                        <sic>A.Y.J.W.Allen</sic>
                        <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                    </choice>
                </name>
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston<date when="1856-09-10">August 2 1856</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>  
                </listPerson>
            
            <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
		    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
            <name xml:id="ST">Sue Trowbridge</name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    <text><body><div>
  <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_016.jpg"/> 
<head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Molly Houston, September 10, 1856]</head>
      
        <opener>
            <dateline><placeName>Emory College, Oxford Geo. </placeName> <date when="1856-09-10">Sept. 10 1856</date>
            </dateline><lb/>
            <salute>My Dear Mollie,</salute></opener>
        <p>Three weeks ago tomorrow I wrote you a short letter, and hearing of your excuse for not replying sooner, I waited two weeks, and then 
            addressed you another, since which I have now waited to within one day of another week, making out the three, and no reply has come yet.
            My Dearest One, you must pardon me if I begin to be impatient, and if I should suppose something very excusable has transpired, I can not 
            account for it, unless some of you are sick and I <hi rend="underline">do hope not,</hi> for I know you <hi rend="underline">have not forgotten me</hi>,  no, you cannot forget me.</p>
        <p>Perhaps you did not receive my letters, which might be possible, but I reckon they went through right.
            <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_017.jpg"/> 
        Now Dearest, you cannot doubt my wish to hear from you.</p>
        <p>You cannot imagine, "the pain the agony, the doubt," that has characterized this long, long and painful suspense, thrice long and doubly painful because it is <hi rend="underline">thee</hi>, and <hi rend="underline">thy</hi> delay.  I have no doubt as to your excuse for not having written, atall, and that is one of the <hi rend="underline">whys</hi>, that I am so anxious to hear from you, that I may know what has been the cause, whether anything serious or not, for I begin to fear there is- and yet if you were sick or otherwise seriously or providentially hindered from writing it seems that some of my friends surely would write me some information of it; but as yet none of <hi rend="underline">them</hi> have written, surely I must
            <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_017.jpg"/> be <hi rend="underline">forgotten</hi>.</p>
        <p>Dearest one, I know you will write before long; if not before receiving this, in answer to this.</p>  
        <p>This surely is punishment, is torture commensurate with any crimes I have done, is'nt so Mollie.</p>
        <p>I have <hi rend="underline">a heap</hi> to write you My <hi rend="underline">Dearest One</hi>, as soon as you will reply to my previous letters and cheer me up enough to write it.  Please do it then soon.</p>
        <closer><salute>Accept the unfeigned love of your ever faithful and Devoted One,</salute>
        <signed><name>Young Allen</name></signed><lb/>
<lb/>
        <dateline><name>Miss Mollie Houston</name><lb/>
        <placeName>Grantville<lb/>
        Georgia</placeName></dateline></closer>
    </div></body></text>
    
</TEI>
