<TEI xml:id="yja-buddha.1" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
>
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mrs. Pattillo, <date when="1906-10-14">October 14, 1906</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
                <name type="person">
                    <choice>
                        <sic>Young John Allen</sic>
                        <reg>Allen, Young John></reg>
                   </choice>      
                </name>
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from  Young John Allen to Mrs. Pattills <date when="1906-10-14">October 14, </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="thyun">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>T.</forename>
                        <forename>H.</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1865">
                        <placeName>
                            <country>Korea</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="wac">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Warren</forename>
                        <forename>Akin</forename>
                        <surname>Candler</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1857-08-23">
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1941-09-25">
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="tsoong">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Kia</forename>
                        <forename>Tsing</forename>
                        <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>George</forename>
                        <surname>Bell</surname>
                    </persName>
                </person>
                <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
            
            <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    <item>Missionaries--China.</item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2008-03-21">March 21, 2008</date>
            <name xml:id="TR">Tarina Rosen </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
<change when="2008-04-08" who="#RSV">
        <name xml:id="RSV">Stewart Varner</name> Added Library of
Congress Subject headings and cleaned up the text.
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body><div><pb facs="4419.jpg"/><head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Mrs. Pattillo]</head><opener>The image of Buddha is bronze-
It is 54 ft. high and there is 
a temple in its body for
 worship.<lb/>

<placeName>Shanghai, China</placeName><lb/>
<dateline>Oct  14 1906</dateline><lb/>

<salute>My dear </salute><persName> Mrs Pattillo</persName>,</opener><lb/>

     <p>Only six weeks, and lo! I am at the antipodes  - the ultima of distance from you, and a continent and an ocean are between us. What a wonder is modern transportation!</p>
    <p>I arrived on the 29th September-   Found all well-Caught up with Bp Candler at Nagasaki, Japan, and we arrived together at Shanghai<pb facs="4420.jpg"/>
I hope you have all gotten well through the summer and are now
enjoying such glorious weather as we are now having in October. Our
voyage in September, the worst month on land, was most delightful.  We
had bright calm weather all the way  - hardly a white-cap on the sea -
nor a swell. The name Pacific was written on sky and sea and was
equally appreciated on shipboard, where there   was   scarcely a
"pale" face. Our only discomfort was the overcrowding at times, as
between San Francisco and Honolulu, and from Honolulu to Yokohama,
because we had to take on the passengers from the stranded
Manchuria. We had about 60 Missionaries from Honolulu on to Japan and
China. But the crowding was in the staterooms - not on the decks or
elsewhere. The Korea is an 18.000 ton ship and fast, having done her 20 knots across the Pacific, making the run from Yokohama straight across to San Francisco in 10 days 10 hours. She and her sister-ship the S.S. Siberia hold the record as yet. I send this letter by her on return, leaving tomorrow = but her speed in ordinary is limited to 15 knots so you need not expect a record run. Hoping that you are all well and enjoying the glorious  weather, and   that I may hear from you soon.</p> <lb/><closer><salute>I remain as ever, with love to the family.</salute><lb/> <signed>Young J. Allen</signed></closer><lb/>
<postscript><p>P.S. Bp Candler expects to return by the
America Maru leaving here 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>inst - Y.J.A.</p></postscript></div></body></text>
</TEI>



