<TEI xml:id="yja-1906-02-27.001">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Tsoong Kia Tsing, <date when="1906-02-27">February 27, 1906</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic>YJA</sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen, <date when="1906-02-27">February 27, 1906</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="thyun">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>T.</forename>
                        <forename>H.</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1865">
                        <placeName>
                           <country>Korea</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945
                    </death>
                </person>
           <person xml:id="wac">
            <persName>
              <forename>Warren</forename>
              <forename>Akin</forename>
              <surname>Candler</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1857-08-23">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1941-09-25">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </death>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="tsoong">
            <persName>
              <forename>Kia</forename>
              <forename>Tsing</forename>
              <surname>Tsoong</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName>
              <forename>George</forename>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
            </persName>
          </person>
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2008-03-21">March 21, 2008</date>
                <name xml:id="JDP">Jason Puckett</name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
    <div xml:id="yja-1906-02-27.001" type="letter">
        <pb facs="4413.jpg"/>
        <head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Tsoong Kia Tsing]</head>
        <opener><dateline><placeName>On Board T.S.S. "Dakota"<lb/>
            in<lb/>
            Mid-Pacific</placeName><lb/>
<date when="1906-02-27">Feb <hi rend="underline">27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> 1906</date></dateline>

        <salute>My dear <persName ref="#tsoong">George</persName> --</salute> </opener>
 
        
        <p>Your letter of Jan 1st reached Shanghai after I had left but caught me up at Kobe, Japan.  So I brought it on with several others to be acknowledged at Sea.  We left Shanghai on the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <unclear>illegible word</unclear> and hope to reach port Seattle, Puget Sound, about 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> or 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst. and Georgia a week or ten days afterward --</p>

        <p>We crossed the 180&#176; meridian on Tuesday, 20th <unclear>illegible word</unclear>, hence had a <hi rend="underline">double Tuesday</hi> or a day of about 47 hours long -- This ship <hi rend="underline">Dakota</hi> is said to be the largest Cargo Capacity of any vessel afloat at this date -- though larger are abuilding -- It has 28.000 tons capacity --  
    <pb facs="4414.jpg"/>

It is simply immense and complete in its accommodation and comfort of its passengers -- At present we have only about 10%, but it can accommodate all told some 2000 including Steerage --  The recently appointed Imperial Chinese Commission sent abroad to Study and report on the Governments, methods of administration &#x0026; etc. of different countries, is aboard and comprises some 40 members of suite -- <persName>Prince (<del rend="strikethrough">Tsai <unclear>illegible word</unclear></del>) <hi rend="underline">TSAI TSEH</hi></persName> and two other mandarins of high degree are the heads of the Commission.  Two leading Commissioners went on ahead and have already reached Washington -- I find them very pleasant, and have been supplying them day by day with reading matter, mostly my own books and copies of my periodicals, which they</p>
        <pb facs="4415.jpg"/>

<p>2nd Sheet</p>

        <p>have read and appropriated most eagerly -- One of them said to me: I find your periodical the best paper in China for the use of information and Edification, and the most widely read and influential among the Officials -- I have had some close discussion with the Chief members on the subject of their mission which is to prepare their country for the adoption of Constitutional Govt. and one of the members who listened to my views of China's needs and how to proceed, etc., remarked there is no one understands China as you do -- I esteem this <unclear>illegible word</unclear> opportunity for influencing these leaders as one of great importance and so am trying to <unclear>improve</unclear> it, both for the Cause of Mission, and the Good of the Country -- I <unclear>illegible word</unclear> very much to <unclear>learn</unclear> China at this <unclear>juncture</unclear> in her history, but <unclear>hoping</unclear> to make up for it by contact with the leading members of this Commission.  To my gratification 
    <pb facs="4416.jpg"/>

I found among the suite two of my former pupils at Shanghai, and <unclear>number</unclear> of them who were familiar with my books and periodicals, so that intercourse with them from the prince down has been easy and pleasant and I hope profitable. --</p>

<p>I am always glad to hear from you, and I can assure you that it is with the greatest pleasure I look forward to seeing you, and thank you ever so muchfor your very kind invitation to sojourn with you for several days.  It is certainly very kind of you and I am sure I should enjoy as never before such an opportunity for high <unclear>illegible word</unclear> communion and fellowship.</p>

<p>I can understand your loneliness, for in this far away East, while I have many acquaintances, there are no old friends and the distance, silence and separation from those in the Home land is something appalling --</p>  <closer>I mail this in Seattle and will follow it immediately, and hope <unclear>as</unclear> a convenient time to be with you -- till then good bye my dear old friend -- Love to all -- <signed><persName ref="#yja">YJA</persName></signed></closer>
    
    </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>