<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="yja-1854-06-02.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1854-06-02">June 2, 1854</date>, an electronic edition</title>
        <author>
          <name type="person">
            <choice>
              <sic>A.Y.J.W. Allen</sic>
              <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907"&gt;</reg>
            </choice>
          </name>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
        <date>2008</date>
        <availability>
          <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_101">&#x0026;#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.

                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original

                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:

                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
          <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
          <name>Stewart Varner</name>
          <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie, <date when="1854-06-02">June 2, 1854</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
        <listPerson>
          <person xml:id="yja">
            <persName>
              <forename>Young</forename>
              <forename>John</forename>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836

                        <placeName><settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement><region type="state">Georgia</region><country>United States</country></placeName></birth>
            <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907

                        <placeName><settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement><country>China</country></placeName></death>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="thyun">
            <persName>
              <forename>T.</forename>
              <forename>H.</forename>
              <surname>Yun</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName>
              <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
              <surname>Yun</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1865">
              <placeName>
                <country>Korea</country>
              </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945

                    </death>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="wac">
            <persName>
              <forename>Warren</forename>
              <forename>Akin</forename>
              <surname>Candler</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1857-08-23">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1941-09-25">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </death>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="tsoong">
            <persName>
              <forename>Kia</forename>
              <forename>Tsing</forename>
              <surname>Tsoong</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName>
              <forename>George</forename>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
            </persName>
          </person>
        

    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
        <listPlace>
          <!-- add any list places you want to -->
          <place>
            <placeName>
              <settlement/>
              <region/>
            </placeName>
          </place>
        </listPlace>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_102">This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part

                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_103">The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.

                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_104">Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF

                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were

                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to

                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced

                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of

                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using

                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.

                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI

                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at

                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em

                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles

                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear

                in the original text.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <creation>
        <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
        <rs type="language">English</rs>
        <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
        <date>1800-1899</date>
        <!-- or 1900-1999 -->

        </creation>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list>
            <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
            <item>Emory College, Oxford, Ga.</item>
            <item>Missionaries -- China.</item>
            <item>China--Religion.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date when="2008-03-13">March 13, 2008</date><name xml:id="sej">Steve Johnson</name>

            transcribed and encoded the text.

        </change>
      <change when="2008-04-04" who="#RSV"><name xml:id="RSV">Stewart Varner</name> Added Library of

Congress Subject headings and cleaned up the text.

      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_1023">
    <body xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_1022">
      <div xml:id="yja-1854-06-02.002">
        <pb facs="4276.jpg" xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_105"/>
        <head>[Letter from Y. J. Allen to Mollie Houston]</head>
        <opener>
          <dateline><placeName>Emory &#x0026; Henry College</placeName> June 2d '54</dateline>
          <salute>Miss Mollie Houston. Dear Mollie:</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_106">Amid the flattery and encomia heaped upon the reception of my <unclear>unmeriting</unclear> letter, need <hi rend="underline">I</hi> tell <hi rend="underline">thee</hi> your letter was with warmest emotions welcomed and perused, and oft reperused, freshened <add place="margin-left">still</add> by the dews of its lovely eden bower, and all radiant and glowing with the tenderness and affection which thy fair hand has traced in lines of purity and simplicity -- Nay -- need I tell you that yester's eve (1st of June) was hallowed by the multi-perusals of its silken-like embroidered <unclear><sic>frazes</sic></unclear> -- and the image of Whose form and beauty I saw reflected there -- </p>
        <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_107">Yea Dear Mollie -- thy letter was truly a mirror in which beautifully reflected I saw the gentleness of thy mind; and truly too -- it was a <hi rend="underline">Telescope</hi> through which with my mind's eye I could wander in retrospect <del>back</del> through the misty maze of distance and days whose sacredness yet lingers as grateful fragrance fresh in memory, and which oft chase away the dull cares of a solitary hour, when unseen, unheard the pensive pulsations of  <add place="supralinear">the</add> heart's deepest emotions. <add place="margin-right">thrill</add></p>
        <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_108">Dear Mollie -- I was glad to know that bound with the fetters of Science, and depressed by thought, you were Struggling yet to ascend the rugged Steep -- where "Star eyed Science" and fame unfold their banners to every anxious aspirant, and under whose folds of magnitude and magnificence all <hi rend="underline">alike</hi> are permitted to recumb, and recur those who have in vagrancy strayed "tracing Shadows" -- beware of <choice><sic>Shdows</sic><corr>Shadows</corr></choice> Mollie. -- </p>
        <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_1010">As thou hast well ascribed thy mind is strong, thy thoughts and sentiments pure and ennobling, aside from thy beauty and surpassing <choice><sic>lovliness</sic> <corr>loveliness</corr></choice>, and Mollie -- ere long, (methinks now I can indulge the hope) I hope to recognize thy <hi rend="underline">signature</hi> <unclear reason="page torn"><sic>enroll</sic><corr>enrolled</corr></unclear> among the list of 



<pb facs="4277.jpg" xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_109"/><sic>of</sic> Fair Female Correspondents of literature, Yea -- meseems to look forward even now and behold thee, the <hi rend="underline">"Amelia"</hi> of Georgia -- May you be its fondest boast.</p>
        <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_1011">Aye Dear Mollie -- thou art gay -- <del><unclear reason="text crossed out and illegible">hero! nimium</unclear></del> <hi rend="underline">hero! nimium felix</hi> -- when thou was floating away in the fanciful <hi rend="underline">Quadrille</hi>, I would like to have seen thee robed in all thy beauty -- but from the <hi rend="underline">ball</hi> and the <hi rend="underline">dance</hi>, (pardon me,) I ever beg to be absent, there never was, there ne'er can be <hi rend="underline">there</hi> charms for me -- Smiling faces there may cheer me, flattering tongues <del>there</del> may there elate with <unclear reason="illegible"><hi rend="underline">Can-dos</hi></unclear> the charms of beauty, but alas, as Vanity it vanisheth, aside from there, and then dismantled of its feigned assimilations, the heart cold, and inhuman greeting -- Oh! Vanity of Vanities <hi rend="underline">the Ball</hi> -- <hi rend="underline">the Dance</hi> -- there can <del>but</del> be there <add place="supralinear">but</add> a little polish of Society and a little pruning and pluming of rusticity to mingle with whatever of urbanity the <hi rend="underline"><sic>cives</sic></hi> may perchance have. --Yea -- dear Mollie -- firmly and <choice><sic>Stedfast</sic><corr>Steadfast</corr></choice> am I planted against <hi rend="underline">that</hi> evil -- which I am proud to say is so fast -- (I trust) winging its everlasting flight from the Shores of our beloved land. -- for as I said above it can - do, but cultivate a little <choice><sic>erternal</sic><corr>external</corr></choice> beauty of carriage, and fanciful movements, while on the other hand -- Oh! that immortal Soul -- is neglected -- Yea instead of adorning that part which shall live forever, the <hi rend="underline">Ball, the Dance</hi> cultivate and adorn that which shall perish soon -- when death comes to "<sic>elaborat</sic> life's elixir from its clayey crucibles" -- Dear Mollie -- then Oh! then let me advise <add place="supralinear">you</add> to away, away with the Shadows of pleasure -- The <hi rend="underline">"Ball-Dance"</hi>, Oh! let them as idle tales pass by; "Remember", Dear Mollie, "thy Creator in the days of the Youth," neglect not, longer let me entreat you peace with Your Great Preserver &#x0026; Benefactor
        <pb facs="4278.jpg" xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_1014"/>
        Go, to the fount of living waters and drink there never ceasing pleasures, pleasures that the blinded world knoweth not of, but which Angels delight in Heaven to recognize; The Ball's pleasures quickly fade and die away, but the pleasures of Religion are lasting, perpetual, -- Yes -- Religion is the sure balm and cordial to the troubled heart and sovereign antidote against the fears of death -- as a friend then -- Yea as lover, let Me implore thee, to turn away from the follies and sinfulness of this vile world's pleasures and seek everlasting pleasures, and a home in heaven -- in Religion is the only where they can be found. -- there is more happiness and consolation in the enjoyment and sweet peace of Religion one hour than the world can afford in a million of ages -- Yea -- Dear Mollie, if not on my brow you saw sadness brooding, it was there, and in my heart its pangs of anguish have often been felt, and oft a bitter tear in Solitude has suffused my eye; Thou mayest not suppose because, when in they presence I was not sad I ne'er am so, nay for too often "Gilded tombs <add place="supralinear">do</add> worms enfold". -- as for me Dear Mollie I am trying to live so that when I come to meet death I can like my dying friend, a few days since, sing out with him "Religion is a fortune and heaven is a home." Yea Dear Mollie upon that Star, perhaps we are gazing at the same time, when it seems to mirror back thy beauty in its own resplendent brilliancy -- Often I remember thee with warmest emotions and tenderest affections. -- I have not time now Mollie to write you a long letter; I have one more <choice><orig>Zamination</orig><reg>Examination</reg></choice> in Latin and then I'm <hi rend="underline">done</hi>, on <hi rend="underline">Wednesday</hi> is <choice><orig>Commenz</orig><orig>Commencement</orig></choice> day and on Thursday I expect to leave for the North --</p>
        <pb facs="4279.jpg" xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_1018"/>
        <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_1019">Pardon my brief attempt and <hi rend="underline">illegible fist</hi>.  It would much gratify me to write more but methinks thou canst <hi rend="underline">Pardon</hi> me.</p>
        <p xml:id="yja-1854-06-02_1020">It is my greatest delight to receive a letter from you and I trust that immediately You will respond -- and I assure you that it will be a welcome messenger from thee fostered and prized much --</p>
        <closer>
          <salute>Pardon me -- Dear Mollie -- if in this I may have cast any insinuations upon your finer feeling, And believe me Sincere &#x2014; ad eternum</salute>
          <signed>
            <name>A.Y.J.W. Allen</name>
          </signed>
        </closer>
        <lb/>
        <postscript><p>P.S.



Tell me in Your next who is paying his <hi rend="underline">distresses</hi> to you, wait not 'till I come home -- for the Lord only knows when that may be.</p></postscript>  <signed><name>Allen</name></signed>


<postscript>
<p>And with due <add place="supralinear">de</add>ference and Much respect I subscribe myself a Hermesian <hi rend="underline">With Motto</hi><lb/>&#x03A0;&#x03BB;&#x03BF;&#x03C5;&#x03C4;&#x03C2; &#x1F41; &#x03C4;&#x03B7;&#x03C2; &#x03C8;&#x03C5;&#x03C7;&#x03B7;&#x03C2;, &#x03A0;&#x03BB;&#x03C5; &#x03BC;&#x03BF;&#x03BD;&#x03BF;&#x03C2; &#x03B5;&#x03C3;&#x03C4;&#x03B9;&#x03BD; &#x03B1;&#x03BB;&#x03B7;&#x03B8;&#x03B7;&#x03C2;  -- 
<lb/>And dear Mollie may that be your Motto as <hi rend="underline">it is that of The Hermesian Society</hi><lb/>




Allen -- <hi rend="underline">a member</hi>
</p>


<p>Yes Mollie I'll tell you all about my trip when I return and some by line if you'll respond soon so that I may receive it when I return -- an <hi rend="underline">et nunc vale</hi> = and now farewell Mollie</p></postscript>
<signed><name>Allen</name></signed>
<lb/>
<postscript><p>&#x0397;&#x03C3;&#x03C4;&#x03B9;&#x03BD; &#x03A0;&#x03BF;&#x03B8;&#x03BF;&#x03C2; &#x03C3;&#x03BF;&#x03C5;... --</p></postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
