<TEI xml:id="yja-1891-09-12.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
>
       <teiHeader>
              <fileDesc>
                     <titleStmt>
                            <title>Letter to Young John Allen from T.H. Yun, <date when="1891-09-12">September 12, 1891</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                            <author>
                                   <name type="person">
                                          <choice>
                                             <sic>T. H. Yun</sic>
                                              <reg>Yun, Ch'i-ho, 1865-1945</reg>
                                             </choice>
                                   </name>
                            </author>
                     </titleStmt>
                     <extent></extent>
                     <publicationStmt>
                            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                            <date>2008</date>
                            <availability>
                                   <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                                          Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                                          contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                                          <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                            </availability>
                     </publicationStmt>
                     <seriesStmt>
                            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                   <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                                   <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                                   <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                                   <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                            </respStmt>
                     </seriesStmt>
                     <sourceDesc>
                            <bibl>Letter from T. H. Yun to Young John Allen, <date when="1891-09-12">September 12, 1891</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                            <listPerson>
                                   <person xml:id="yja">
                                          <persName>
                                                 <forename>Young</forename>
                                                 <forename>John</forename>
                                                 <surname>Allen</surname>
                                          </persName>
                                          <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                                                 <placeName>
                                                        <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                                        <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                                        <country>United States</country>
                                                 </placeName>
                                          </birth>
                                          <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                                                 <placeName>
                                                        <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                                        <country>China</country>
                                                 </placeName>
                                          </death>
                                   </person>
                                   <person xml:id="thyun">
                                          <persName>
                                                 <forename>T.</forename>
                                                 <forename>H.</forename>
                                                 <surname>Yun</surname>
                                          </persName>
                                          <persName>
                                                 <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                                                 <surname>Yun</surname>
                                          </persName>
                                          <birth when="1865">
                                                 <placeName>
                                                        <country>Korea</country>
                                                 </placeName>
                                          </birth>
                                          <death when="1945-12-06">December 12, 1945
                                          </death>
                                   </person>
                                   <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
                            
                            <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                                   <place>
                                          <placeName>
                                                 <settlement></settlement>
                                                 <region></region>
                                          </placeName>
                                   </place>
                            </listPlace>
                     </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
              <encodingDesc>
                     <projectDesc>
                            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                                   of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
                     </projectDesc>
                     <samplingDecl>
                            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                                   Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
                     </samplingDecl>
                     <editorialDecl>
                            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                                   images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                                   captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                                   an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                                   have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                                   the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                                   the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                                   For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                                   Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                                   http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                                   dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                                   displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                                   in the original text.</p>
                     </editorialDecl>
                     <classDecl>
                            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                                   <bibl>
                                          <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                                   </bibl>
                            </taxonomy>
                     </classDecl>
              </encodingDesc>
              <profileDesc>
                     <creation>
                            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                            <rs type="language">English</rs>
                            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                            <date>1800-1899</date>  
                     </creation>
                     <textClass>
                            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                                   <list>
                                          <item>Allen, Young John,
				     1836-1907.</item>
<item>Emory College, Oxford, Ga.</item>
                                   </list>
                            </keywords>
                     </textClass>
              </profileDesc>
              <revisionDesc>
                     <change>
                            <date when="2008-03-12">March 12, 2008</date>
                            <name xml:id="AH">Alice Hickcox</name> corrected and validated the text.
                     </change>
                     <change>
                            <date when="2008-03-03"></date>
                                    <name xml:id="BC">Brian Croxall, </name>
                             transcribed and encoded the text.
                     </change>
<change when="2008-04-04" who="#RSV">
        <name xml:id="RSV">Stewart Varner</name> Added Library of
Congress Subject headings and cleaned up the text.
      </change>
              </revisionDesc>
       </teiHeader>

<text>
<body>
<div type="letter" xml:id="yja-1891-09-12">
<pb facs="4247"/>
 <head> [Letter from T. H. Yun to Young John Allen, September 12, 1891]</head>
<opener>
 <dateline><name type="place">Oxford</name> -- <date when="1891-09-12">9/12 -- 91</date>.</dateline>

<salute>Rev. Dr <name>Y. J. Allen</name>.<lb/>

My dear Doctor;</salute>
</opener>

<p>After having visited nearly 30 different towns--most of them small--in Va, Tenn, Md, and Ky, I am here. I came by Atlanta the day before yesterday; and am sorry that I could not see Mrs Allen.</p>
       
<p>My summer travels were a pleasant experience in my life. The collections after my talk on <choice>
       <orig>Corea</orig>
       <reg>Korea</reg>
</choice>

<pb facs="4248"/>
Ranged between $3.00 and $25.00. The latter sum occurred few and far between; but as the points I touched at were not far apart I could pay my traveling expenses of all sorts, and come to the College with $180.00. If I could manage to visit some towns in Ga during the session, I might be able to pay my way thro this year. Or at least I might get something to pay sundry expenses.</p>

<p> One <add place="supralinear">of the</add> pleasant features of my summer work was the interest and pleasure which many persons manifested on account of their having heard you some years

<pb facs="4249"/>
ago. Many told me that they were glad to see me from the school on whose behalf you spoke to them. A young intelligent looking man came up to me after the lecture in a church of Louisville, and said that he was glad to see and hear me <hi rend="underline">because</hi> he, after having heard your lecture years ago, had always wished to meet a man brought to Christ thro you and your comrades.</p>

<p>In Lynchburg, I had the pleasure of forming an acquaintance with <name>Miss <unclear>Fannie</unclear> Earl</name> and her brother. They spoke of you in the most enthusiastic terms.</p>

<pb facs="4250"/>

<p>The recent riots and uncertainty of affairs in China seem to have very discouraging effect on the friends of missions here. I shall be happy to learn more definitely about the "whereunto" of the disturbance so that I may be able to give needed answers to many inquiries on the subject.</p>

<closer><salute>Praying for your good health and happiness,<lb/>

I remain<lb/>

Yours very sincerely</salute><lb/>

<signed><persName ref="#thyun">T. H. Yun</persName></signed>.</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>