<TEI xml:id="yja-1861-01-06.001">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
			<title>Letter from Young John Allen to his parents, <date when="1861-01-06">January 6, 1861</date>, an electronic edition</title>
			<author>
				<name type="person">
					<choice>
						<sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
						<reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
					</choice>
				</name>
			</author>
		</titleStmt>
		<extent></extent>
		<publicationStmt>
			<publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
			<date>2008</date>
			<availability>
				<p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
					Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
					contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
					<address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
			</availability>
		</publicationStmt>
		<seriesStmt>
			<title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
			<respStmt>
				<name>Naomi Nelson</name>
				<name>Alice Hickcox</name>
				<name>Stewart Varner</name>
				<resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
			</respStmt>
		</seriesStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><!-- replace this with your letter information -->Letter from T. H. Yun to Young John Allen, <date when="1890-11-08">November 8, 1890</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
			<listPerson>
				<person xml:id="yja">
					<persName>
						<forename>Young</forename>
						<forename>John</forename>
						<surname>Allen</surname>
					</persName>
					<birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
						<placeName>
							<settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
							<region type="state">Georgia</region>
							<country>United States</country>
						</placeName>
					</birth>
					<death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
						<placeName>
							<settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
							<country>China</country>
						</placeName>
					</death>
				</person>
				<person xml:id="thyun">
					<persName>
						<forename>T</forename>
						<forename>H.</forename>
						<surname>Yun</surname>
					</persName>
					<persName>
						<forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
						<surname>Yun</surname>
					</persName>
					<birth when="1864">
						<placeName>
							<country>Korea</country>
						</placeName>
					</birth>
					<death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945
					</death>
				</person>
				<!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
			
			<listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
				<place>
					<placeName>
						<settlement></settlement>
						<region></region>
					</placeName>
				</place>
			</listPlace>
		</sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>
	<encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
			<p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
				of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<samplingDecl>
			<p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
				Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
		</samplingDecl>
		<editorialDecl>
			<p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
				images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
				captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
				an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
				have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
				the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
				the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
				For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
				Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
				http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
				dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
				displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
				in the original text.</p>
		</editorialDecl>
		<classDecl>
			<taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
				<bibl>
					<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
				</bibl>
			</taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	</encodingDesc>
	<profileDesc>
		<creation>
			<rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
			<rs type="language">English</rs>
			<rs type="geography">United States</rs>
			<date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
		</creation>
		<textClass>
			<keywords scheme="lcsh">
				<list>
					<item></item>
					<item></item>
					<item></item>
					<item></item>
					<item></item>
				</list>
			</keywords>
		</textClass>
	</profileDesc>
	<revisionDesc>
		<change>
			<date when="2008-03-03">March 3, 2008</date>
				<name xml:id="shp">Susan Pinckard </name>
			transcribed and encoded the text.
		</change>
	</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
	<div type="letter"><pb facs="4284.jpg"/>
							<head>[Letter from Young John Allen to his parents, January 6, 1861]</head>
							<opener><dateline><name type="place">Shanghai, China</name>, <date when="1861-01-06">Jan 6th 1861</date></dateline>
<salute>My Dear Pa &#x0026; Ma</salute>.</opener><lb/>

		<p>I ought to have written you a birth-day letter--  I know you will be glad to hear from me anytime, however, so I will write the sooner now as I did not then--  <hi rend="underline">I wish you all a happy New Year</hi>.</p>

		<p>We are still in Shanghai; with but little prospect of getting away soon.  In company with <name type="person">Brother Lambuth</name> a few weeks ago I visited the place where we were expected to live-- It was one year ago one of the largest, most populous and beautiful cities in all China.  It is quite as large in extent as N. York city and contained twice as many inhabitants; but it is now almost entirely destroyed, burned up, and very nearly all the people have left-- There were forty thousand soldiers there when we were there-- On our way back to Shanghai we met a very large rebel army marching directly to the city, with full intent to complete it's overthrow and

<pb facs="4285.jpeg"/>
entire destruction-- We met the army in the grand canal, which is about one hundred feet wide-- We were in a small boat and the army had boats-- We did not have much apprehensions of danger as they profess and show great respect and kindness to foreigners-- When they first perceived our boat, they began to make preparations to capture us.  <name type="person">Bro- L</name> and I were sitting on the bow of the boat watching the whole maneuver--  When they came quite near us, they soon perceived their mistake--that we were not Chinese but foreigners, whereupon they cried out to one another "<hi rend="underline">foreign devils</hi>," "<hi rend="underline">foreign brethren</hi>" had a hearty laugh and passed us without interruption--  We stopped alongside the bank for two hours hoping they would soon pass, but at the expiration of that time there seemed to be no abatement in progress or dimminution in numbers; in other words we concluded there was no end to them and went on--  We found them densely crowded and rapidly marching in a line for twenty miles--  Had we remained stationary where we first met them they could not have

<pb facs="4286.jpg"/>
passed us all that day-- The rear camps one night where the first ranks did the night before--  In other words the army about measures its full length during one day's march--  We had the pleasure, or rather I should say the necessity, of calling on board the General's boat--  He informed us that he had upwards of ten thousand boats--  We supposed not less that twelve thousand, the very least; upon these we counted from three to twenty seven men; that is, making a reasonable calculation, somewhere between sixty &#x0026; seventy thousand soldiers--  Through all this immense, amazing mass of boats and men we had to make headway for twenty miles--  Would that I had the time and ability to portray to you something of the scene--  It cannot well be exaggerated--  Glad indeed and thankful too were we when they were all passed--  We barely succeeded passing them in time to camp that day, notwithstanding we were both in motion--  You may think we travelled slowly; it is true we did--  You must however remember that <hi rend="underline">large bodies</hi> move slowly and so do small ones against such fearful
<pb facs="4287.jpg"/>

odds.  All these were bound to the great city of Hang Chow which we had just two days before left--  You can well imagine now, that it is doubtful how long before we leave here if we depend on Hang Chow for an opening. ~</p>

		<p>With the above facts before us and in view of a continuance of the same and perhaps worse circumstances in the future, it was concluded, at our last mission meeting, to be best not to bind our hearts and hopes to that one place; but now look out for an open door and a home somewhere else--  <name type="person">Bro L</name> and I therefore have under contemplation a visit to Su Chow and Nankin, both held by the rebels at this time, and will perhaps leave here week after next--15 or 17th of Jan--  We are very pleasantly situated here; could not be more so at home, but we are anxious to secure a place to work and a home amidst the peoples--</p>

		<p>There are hundreds of little things I would like to tell you had I time--things new, strange and heathen--  I have seen much that I used to read of and much
<pb facs="4288.jpg"/>

that's not in books but little to make one glad and much to make one sad.</p>

		<p>There never was a more distressing time nor a more distressed country than China at present--  My heart grows sick and tired of the scenes of desolation and ruin that I saw-- but oh! how infinitely worse than what I saw is the reality--  Hundreds and thousands, yea hundreds of thousands of people are destitute of house and home and many of them of the necessaries of life-- besides, a grievous famine now threatens the whole country and this vicinity in particular-- the rebels have devastated the country, leaving but comparatively few people where they have been to make crops and supply the markets, and a flood last fall overwhelmed the rice fields and destroyed <del rend="strikethrough">the </del>much of the main dependence of the poor Chinese.</p>

		<p>I hear a drought has cut short the crops at home-- but oh! how happy and well supplied are our people <del rend="strikethrough">at home</del> when compared with these?</p>

		<p>How could we complain if we but knew how it was <add place="supralinear">with</add> thousands and tens of thousands who suffer unpitied and die uncared for unnoticed.</p>
<pb facs="4289.jpg"/>

		<p>My dear Pa and Ma, I must now hasten to conclude this letter--  I hope you are all quite well--  I would like so much to have a letter from you.</p>

		<p>We are now very well indeed--  <name>Dollie</name> has altogether recovered--  My health never was better--  Our Little <name>Millie</name> is now quite well cheerful and happy--  While I write she is sitting by the fire trying to sew--  She has nearly all her teeth--  Can talk some English and quite as much Chinese.  This is our mid-winter now and it is sometimes very cold.  The changes are rather sudden and disagreeable here--  Remember us to all our friends especially to <name>Sister Millie</name> &#x0026; family &#x0026; <name>Uncle Carlis</name> &#x0026; family--  Tell <name>Allen</name>, <name>'Gustus</name> and <name>William</name> to write me, if only a short letter--  How are <name>Johnie</name> &#x0026; <name>Jimmie</name>
		</p>
<p>May God bless you all and finally bring us together again in our Fathers house above-- My dear Pa and Ma,  let us live for heaven-- I never expect to see you again on Earth below--but Oh!  I do hope and pray to meet you again in heaven above.</p>  <closer><salute><name>Dollie</name> and babie send much love with your's very affectionately,</salute>  <signed><name type="person" ref="#yja">Young J. Allen</name> </signed></closer>
</div>
</body></text>
</TEI>