<TEI>
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title><letter>from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston</letter>, <date when="1856-09-16">Sept. 16, 1856</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
              <choice>
                <sic><!-- First name Last name--></sic>
                  <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
              </choice>
            </name>
	</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston <date when="1890-11-08"></date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                
           
             <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-04-06">April 6, 1856</date>
                <name xml:id="">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body><div type="letter">
<opener><dateline><name type="place">Emory College, Oxford Ga</name><date when="1856-09-16">Sept 16, 1856</date></dateline>
    <salute>My Dearest One,</salute></opener>
<p>Doubtless the torturing pangs of anxiety and suspense have already begun to lay hold on your heart, from my already <hi rend="underline">too long delay</hi>; be assured, however, my procrastination proceeds from no vindictive feeling, or retributive motive, but alone from <del rend="strikethrough">cir</del>circumstances over which I could exercise no control, circumstances too, which I have faithfully endeavored to <hi rend="underline">out do</hi>, but alas, both time, strength and effort have recoiled exhausted and in vain and I am now forced to this <hi rend="underline">dernier resort</hi> as a last alternative lest you should in <hi rend="underline">over anxiety</hi> be constrained to interpret my delay as in retaliation, which by no means it could <hi rend="underline">ever be</hi>/I have been tortured, <hi rend="underline">Dearest one</hi>, for the last night or two, the<pb/> only time which I can properly claim for writing to you, as well as the best times, with a lingering, feverish dull headache, and as I before hinted, although I have attempted several times to reply to your sweet letter, I have utterly failed in consequence of what I am now suffering- the headache, confused mind &apm; disturbed feelings, caused by debilitation of physical powers and energies.  You know <del rend="strikethrough">my,</del> My Dear Mollie, I am always punctual to respond to your letters, and from what I have stated above you see that I have earnestly striven to be this time, but have been over ruled in my endeavors by the circumstances mentioned.  I know too, Dearest, it will cause you grief and sad disappointment again perhaps, to receive just such a<pb/> letter as this, which must necessarily <hi rend="underline">ex necessitate rei</hi> be so.  Dear one, <hi rend="underline">don't</hi> be disappointed, please don't let it disturb your mind.  I regret that I am compelled to write to you this way- for surely this is all<hi rend="underline"><unclear>???</unclear></hi> but I <hi rend="underline">do</hi> promise that just as soon as my feelings will admit, I will send you <hi rend="underline">a letter</hi>, for I cannot, dare not call <hi rend="underline">this</hi> one,- I am totally unfit, disqualified for the discharge of my duty; it is <hi rend="underline">cold</hi> I reckon that's this prostrating me- but I'll soon be restored again by <hi rend="underline">sleep</hi> and prudence, when you shall hear from me <hi rend="underline">gladly</hi>.</p><p>Do pardon me now My Dear One for not answering your letter, for <hi rend="underline">I cannot do it</hi>- my mind will not trace a single thought nor prompt one.<pb/> and there is much in your letter I desire to notice, ma<add place="supralinear">n</add>y suggestions made I wish to notice but cannot in my present feelings.</p><p>So I just write you this as <hi rend="underline">forerunner</hi> of what my intentions are and why I delay.</p><p>Give my love to those you love best and believe me faithfully, devotedly, ever thine own</p><lb/><signed><persName>Young Allen</persName></signed><lb/>
<postscript>Mollie, please write to me again, even before I write you a full answer; be assured it will be welcomed even next to your own beloved presence, which is sweeter, more blessed to me, than all other subcelestial considerations,<signed><persName>Young.</persName></signed></postscript><lb/><postscript>My Dearest, I<hi rend="underline">do</hi> hate to send this; How disappointed I am!  But why should I complain? Nay I will not, I yield to fate's stern decree.</postscript><lb/><salute><hi rend="underline">Farewell tonight</hi></salute>
</div></body></text>
</TEI>