<TEI xml:id="yja-28-aug-1857.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-08-28"
                        >August 28, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>A. Y. J. W. Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-08-28">August
                        28, 1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare
                    Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region>/><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
			<item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-06-29">June 29, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="ypw">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_015.jpg"/>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, August 28, 1857]</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Oxford Geo.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-08-28">Aug 28th 1857</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My Own Beloved Mollie,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I know you are beginning to expect a letter from me by this time, and I feel that
                    I ought to write you a few lines <hi rend="underline">any how</hi> though I have
                    no time and <add place="supralinear">or</add> opportunity for a full
                        <unclear>expression</unclear> of my heart.</p>
                <p>I <unclear>came</unclear> here, Dearest as you might expect; am pleasantly
                    situated; have a fine and agreeable <hi rend="underline">Chum</hi>, the same in
                    spirit, in faith and in calling. Have begun College duties, have a very
                    flattering prospect for a happy and pleasant term and as full a number of
                    students as formerly.</p><p>I tell you my Dear Mollie, I <pb
                        facs="Allen_11_FF4_016.jpg"/><sic></sic>very unfit for a Senior in College,
                    and the responsibilities with which I am now invested. I almost shrink even from
                    the performance of known antics sometimes, but yet I cannot with a peaceful
                    conscience. I had not been here half a day-<unclear>nor</unclear>before Saturday
                    night, the day I got here, I had two calls <del rend="strikethrough">from</del>
                    with requests from friends to fill two appointments immediately; I had
                        <unclear>rather</unclear> to hesitate at first but then I consented to do
                    all I could by the help of him who hath said "My grace shall
                    be sufficient for you." But Oh! my Dear Mollie, how unworthy I do feel; how
                        <unclear> reason="ink stain">illegible</unclear>, how<pb/>insignificant and incapable of doing or saying
                    the least thing or word which shall <unclear>tender</unclear> to the glory of God in
                    the Salvation of a single Soul. Oh! how deceitful, how rebellious is the heart
                    of man; how guilty and wretched even his best estate, Oh! the terror and horror
                    of <hi rend="underline">such <unclear>impulsiveness</unclear> and indiscretion</hi> as
                    sometimes get hold of the heart of man. The Lord <hi rend="underline">knows our
                        hearts</hi>; Oh! may he <hi rend="underline">reach</hi> and <hi
                        rend="underline">cleanse</hi> them, and purify and sanctify them from all
                        <hi rend="underline">past stains</hi> and guilts of sin. </p>
                <p>God Bless Thee, My Own Mollie, I want us to live entirely for God, I want<pb
                        facs="Allen_11_FF4_017.jpg"/>it to be <hi rend="underline">our meat</hi> and
                    our <hi rend="underline">drink</hi> to do the will of our Lord daily, to walk
                    humbly, discreetly and soberly before him; but Oh! how far short of such a life
                    were we living during my vacation. Were we not rather conforming to the world,
                    did we not become even worse, were we not too worldly minded, too "sensual, too
                    devilish"? My Dearest, we did not live right. I know it. I feel it, let us then
                    repent and confess our sins to him who hath said "he is faithful to forgive us
                    our sins if we confess them." Let us begin a new life, to walk more closely with
                    God. That we may always<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_018.jpg"/>have the happy and
                    healthfull influences of the <unclear>vital</unclear> power of Godliness in our
                    souls and in our lives. My dearest <hi rend="underline">Prayer, prayer,
                        prayer</hi> is what <hi rend="underline">we need</hi>; we neglect it <hi
                        rend="underline">too much we did not pray as we used to</hi>, or we would
                        <add place="supralinear">not</add> have fallen into such temptations and
                    indiscretions as we did. Let us then "awaken and arise from the dead" that we
                    may enjoy the light which Christ promises us.</p>
                <p>I would like to write much to you My Dear Love, you know. I would, but time
                    forbids this evening.</p>
                <p>I thought I would just<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_019.jpg"/>write you a few lines
                    now in order that you might hear from me on tomorrow morning, lest you might
                    become anxious about me, for I know you do once and a while think of <hi
                        rend="underline">him who is yours only.</hi></p>
                <p>I wish you Dearest to write to Miss Sallie Hudson and learn from her whether or
                    not she has received a copy of the "Guide to Holiness" for July &#x0026;
                    August, and please inform me. Don't forget it now Mollie.</p>
                <p>My Mollie Dearest, I have now no more time, and must now close, with a request
                    for an immediate response, tell me all the news, and the occurrences of the
                    past week.</p>
                <p>Did you go down to Uncle Carter's. Did Miss Tish come? how did you enjoy yourself
                    and what did Matt. say?</p>
                <p>Give my best-- to Miss Tish, I thought I should get to see her before I left, but
                    she did'nt come,-- but it is well she did not, for had she I should not have
                    reached here till Monday. So it is all for the best on my part.</p>
                <p>My love to Mellie and all of them.--</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>More committedly &#x0026; devotedly thine than ever</salute>
                    <signed>Young J. Allen</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <label>P.S.</label>
                    <p>Please do'nt let any one see <hi rend="underline">this letter</hi> for my
                        sake.</p>
                    <p><name>Young J Allen</name></p>
                </postscript>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>