<TEI xml:id="yja-18-july-1857.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">

    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-07-18">July
                        18, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-07-18">July
                        18, 1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare
                    Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region>/><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                       <item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
		       <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-06-08">June 22, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="ypw">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_009.jpg"/>
            <div type="letter">
                <head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, July 18, 1857]</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>E. C. Oxford Geo.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-07-18">July 18 1857</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My <hi rend="underline">own Dearest Mary</hi>,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I never received your letter till this morning, but Oh! how glad I was to get it,
                    you have no conception. But I can't dwell <hi rend="underline">now upon
                        emotion</hi>. I heard from Bob Freeman this morning also, and he stated that
                    you had arrived <hi rend="underline">safe</hi> "at home again." I
                        <unclear>dare</unclear> very nearly going up to Atlanta to meet you and spend
                    the night with you there and get you to come down with me if you would or if
                    not, to stay with you there as long as I could <hi rend="underline"
                    >anyhow</hi>.</p>

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_010.jpg"/>

                <p>Mollie I never wanted to <hi rend="underline">see you so much</hi> in all my life
                    before. I can't account for it unless it be because since I have had nothing to
                    employ my mind with so long. I thought of you only and constantly. Well that is
                    the truth. I've had nothing to do since Monday night-- but I
                    haste on.</p>
                <p>I've got something to do now, else I would write you a long and full letter <hi
                        rend="underline">almost</hi> as <hi rend="underline">full</hi> as <hi
                        rend="underline">my heart feels</hi>. Another Young Man and myself were
                    called on the other day to fill our Circuit rider's appointments, three in
                    number including both Saturday and Sunday. So you see 

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_010.jpg"/>

                    I have something else
                    now to engage my mind. We have to leave soon after breakfast and I am in great
                    haste to get this done before breakfast. I was up and preparing to leave when
                    your letter came to hand, so you must pardon this great haste. The bell is
                    ringing now I finish after I return to my room.--</p>
                <p>Well, Mollie I shall miss our Commencement Sermon, as I don't expect to return
                    till late sabbath evening, but it is better to be doing good than lying idle
                    <sic>is'nt</sic>, Dearest?</p>
                <p>I am glad to hear that Dear Miss Sallie is expected to be here, and for <hi
                        rend="underline">your sake </hi> too <hi rend="underline">Dearest</hi>. I
                    will 

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_012.jpg"/>

                    endeavor to do what you enjoin and
                    see that she is well cared for and attended to.</p><p>Mr.
                   <unclear>I.F.</unclear>Montgomery &#x0026; Lady are expected today.
                       Miss<unclear> Ginger</unclear>Cox too. Oh! that you come with her.</p>
                <p>Now Mollie I must stop, and I know you will pardon this badly written and short
                    letter under the circumstances.</p>
                <p>You must make haste and get through all your visiting before I get home, for I
                    want to be with you then <hi rend="underline">all the time nearly</hi>, though I
                    would not monopolise.</p>
                <p>I want to be with you as much as I can this time Dearest, for after this
                        vacation

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_013.jpg"/>

                    I don't expect to be with you
                    much till we meet on the next summer to <hi rend="underline">part no more</hi>.
                    I shall be down either on Wednesday night or the next morning.</p>
                <p>The buggy has come and I must go.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Now Dearest Beloved Mollie- Goodbye- till then.--</salute>
                    <signed>Young J. Allen</signed>
                </closer>
                   </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
