<TEI xml:id="yja-15-june-1857.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">

    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-06-15">June
                        15, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-06-15">June
                        15, 1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare
                    Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region>/><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
			<item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-06-08">June 15, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="ypw">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

 <pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_003.jpg"/>

            <div type="letter">
               <head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, June 15, 1857]</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>E. C. Oxford Geo.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-06-15">June 15th 1857</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My <hi rend="underline">own Dear One</hi>,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I should have answered your letter gladly long
                before now, but I wished when I wrote to accompany the
                letter with a Catalogue, designating the Speakers
                &#x0026;c for Commencement, and so have been delayed
                till this morning, which happens to be a very
                unfortunate hour for writing to <hi
                rend="underline">you</hi>. I shall then Dearest, be
                very brief, for time is short for writing. I have a
                great deal to do. I think we shall have mutually to
                excuse each other from long letters now; I will not
                then expect nor require long ones from you nor must
                you from me.
		<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_004.jpg"/>
		I
                shall not let you off however from writing me short
                ones, for I cannot do without hearing from you; and I
                know <sic>will</sic> not wish me too will you
                Mollie?</p>
                <p>I received a letter from Matt this morning and Oh! you have no idea how her <hi
                        rend="underline">words burned my very heart;</hi> I <hi rend="underline"
                        >could not write</hi> to her; I try to be impartial, honest, punctual and
                    faithful to my Correspondent. I haven't but few-- but there are times when <hi
                        rend="underline">I cannot write</hi>. I wanted to write her a long and
                    interesting letter, and was delayed for very want of time. My time is all
                    occupied. The scenes and antics through which I<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_004.jpg"/>had been passing I thought
                    would excuse me in the past. And now I scarcely know how to write to anyone. I
                    have a speech to write for Commencement, my College antics all to attend to,
                    besides I have got preparation to make this week for the Pulpit on next sabbath
                    and then on the next week I have a like engagement to fill. Oh! where! where! is
                    the time the boasted leisure of the student who attends or would attend to his
                    duties!-- I know you will pardon me <hi rend="underline">My own</hi> Mollie.</p>
                <p>Well now let me say a few words in reference to Commencement. Matt. says she
                    cannot come, and does not expect to come now- My Mollie<pb
                        facs="Allen_11_FF4_006.jpg"/>
                <unclear>Fairila</unclear> I don't expect will come. Now how will it be with <hi
                        rend="underline">My Dearest Mary</hi> won't <hi rend="underline">she
                        come</hi> neither? Now I did want you all to come, and <hi rend="underline"
                        >you</hi> specially Mollie, but I shall not insist if you do not feel
                    inclined to come since all the others- your friends have given out the
                    notion.</p>
                <p>I do want to <hi rend="underline">see you very much</hi>, and <hi
                        rend="underline">would be glad</hi> to meet you in Atlanta and bring you
                    down if you will come. Now Dearest, please write me fully whether or not you
                    will come and I will be sure to meet you in Atlanta if <hi rend="underline">you
                        will let me</hi>.</p>
                <p>Be assured you will be among friends here Mollie, if you come<pb
                        facs="Allen_11_FF4_007.jpg"/>and that you will be taken good care of for <hi
                        rend="underline">I will do it myself</hi>,-- great assurance isnt it. And
                    you shall have the <hi rend="underline">best</hi> attention and the <hi
                        rend="underline">best</hi> company that can be selected from the young men
                    here to attend you anywhere you may wish to go when I can not with propriety
                    attend you myself. You understand what I mean by propriety.</p>
                <p>I want you to come if you will, but if not, <hi rend="underline">it won't be
                        long, no it won't be long before I will come to see you</hi>, and <hi
                        rend="underline">be</hi> with you.</p>
                <p>Please pardon this rambling letter. Write me back immediately all about it--
                    about your Commencement, your subject for Composition, and please<pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_007.jpg"/><add
                        place="supralinear"><hi rend="underline">Have I "indulged" too
                        much</hi>?</add> send me a Catalogue.</p>
                
                    <p>My Dear Mary, I must close now, and I want to request you to pray much, and
                            <hi rend="underline">very earnestly</hi> for me that I may have strength
                        and power to do the will of God in all things boldly and courageously-- and
                        expecially on the next two sabbaths,-- I wish you particularly to remember
                        me.</p>
                    <p>Write me soon, let me ask again, and tell me, all you can in the letter
                        circumstances may favor you to write- whether in the long or short. I have
                        much I wanted to write you but I must wait now till I see My Mollie face to
                        face then will have a happy time. Oh! how thine only one
                        looks forward to that day.</p>
		<closer>
                    <salute>Yes thine alone I am</salute>
                    <signed>Young J Allen</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="envelope">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_001.jpg"/>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1857-06-15">June <add rend="supralinear">15</add> 57</date>
                </dateline>
                <lb/>
                <p>
                    <address><persName>Miss Mollie Houston</persName><lb/><addrLine>W. F. College</addrLine><lb/><addrLine>Macon, Georgia</addrLine></address>
                </p>
                <p>Care of<lb/>Prest. Smith</p>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF4_002.jpg"/>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
