<TEI>
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Dr. E.W. Lehow from Young John Allen<date when="1866-12-07">Dec. 7 1866 </date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic>Y. J. Allen</sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><date when=""> </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <persName>
                        
                    </persName>
                    
                </person>
           
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date> 
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-08-26">August 26, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="letter">
    <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-024.jpg"/>
    <opener><dateline><name type="place">Shanghai China</name><date when="1866-12-07">Dec. 7 1866</dateline><lb/>
    To<lb/>
    Dr E.W. Lehow<lb/>
    Con. Secty For. Miss Board.<lb/>
    Meth. Ep. Chr. South.<lb/>
    <salute>My dear Bro-</salute></opener>
    "I have just had an application from a Japanese officer and two foreign gentlemen, one an Englishman resident at <hi rend="underline">Hakodadi</hi> and the other an American of this place, to establish an Anglo-Japanese school for the instruction of Japanese youth (the Sons of officers and wealthy persons in Japan) in the English language and the Sciences.  The occasion of this demand is the recent removal by treaty stipulations of the restrictions forbidding the Japanese to leave their country either for purposes of pleasure or business-  Great numbers are availing of the present opportunities to visit foreign countries and there are constant arrivals here of students en route both to Europe and America-  The officer that applied to me in behalf of an English School here is also on his way to England-  He says there are great numbers who wish to avail <add place="supralinear">themselves</add> of English tuition, but desire to obtain it without having to leave home so far, and as Shanghai will afford far greater facilities for learning the language and observing both foreign customs and improvements beyond anything in Japan he hoped that I would consent to take the superintendency of such a school-  I hesitated for a long while and referred him and the other gentlemen to the schools already in operation here for the Chinese and even went with them to see their teachers
    <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-025.jpg"/>
        but the Japanese officer did not like the idea of having them associated in any wise with the Chinese, and would not consent to any terms of accommodation in them-  He said that when they left Japan they intended to doff Japanese customs, and learn not only the English language, but English manners- wear English clothes, and eat English food- i.e. they purposed to do away with former habits and customs and adopt in toto those of the foreigner-  They then pressed me strongly to undertake its management and guaranteed that both the students and a  proper support of the school should be had-  I finally consented and told them I would undertake it at least for one year-  I was quite perplexed.  I knew not what to do, and  fearing I should commit the same mistake I did with the Chinese Govt School, which I  had the pleasure of inaugurating on a similar plan, I took it for one year-  I <del rend="strikethrough">had</del> had the entire management of the Imperial School offered me for a period of three years, but foolishly would not accept it, because I was looking for the Board to send us a support and free us from all such engagements-  I held the position only six months <unclear>?</unclear> I have agreed to take this for one year-  There is certainly no no finer field for mission operation than this as I am now quite convinced, and, all both missions and others who know of it, urge me to take it.  The merchant because it will enhance his trade and the <unclear>missa?</unclear> because he sees in it a preparation for the Gospel.  Both the Englishman and the Japanese have returned to Japan for the present in hope of making speedy preparations for a number of students <unclear>???</unclear> at first to be sent over as early next year as possible.  I hope you will give me some expression of opinion on the subject when you write, for should it comport with your views, under present circumstances, I may be induced to accept it indefinitely, which I have the offer of its entire control.  I wrote you some time since about the wonderful stimulus to inquiry among the Chinese and <del rend="strikethrough">somewhat</del> <add place="supralinear">begged</add> to call 
    <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-026.jpg"/>
    your attention to the ideas of establishing a scientific school for them, not for a moment thinking that there would come demands <add place="supralinear"> upon us</add> from Japan for that same thing.
    <p>Bro Wood, left us on the <unclear>?</unclear> Dec, per Shp Antelope consigned to Olyphant &amp;co <unclear>???</unclear> His passage amounts to <hi rend="underline">four hundred gold</hi> (400) dollars payable thirty days after sight of order which I gave (as<unclear>??? of ???</unclear>) on W.T. <unclear>S??? ??? Balt???</unclear>  He has a splendid ship and his passage is very cheap for all of which we are indebted to the unceasing kindness of Messrs. Olyphant &amp; co-  They expect to arrive some time in March-- Will write you more although <unclear>?</unclear> mail-  All well- <hi rend="underline">Treasury Exhausted.</hi>
        <closer>Y. J. Allen</closer>
        <postscript><hi rend="underline">Nothing in hand for January or 1st Quarter.</hi>/postscript>
    </p>
    
</div>
</body>
</text>
    </TEI>