<TEI xml:id="yja-1866-07-19.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Dr. McFerrin <date when="1866-07-19">July 19 1866</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic><!-- First name Last name--></sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><date> </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <persName>
                        
                    </persName>
                    
                </person>
           
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date> 
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Mary Houston.</item>
		    <item>Missionaries -- China.</item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-08-20">August 20, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="sat">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="letter">
    <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-010.jpg"/>
    <opener>
        <dateline><name type="place">Shanghai China</name><date when="1866-07-19"> July 19 1866</date></dateline><lb/>
        <salute>My dear Dr. McFerrin</salute></opener>
        <p>The China Mission still lives," said the College of venerable Bishops in their recent address to the Genl. Conference, "and we recommend it to your fostering care."            
        </p>
        <p>Those thrilling words have reached us freighted with precious promise, and <add place="supralinear">in the absence of</add> pending information as to the sequel, we cherish them as "the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen."            
        </p>
        <p>The wonderful vitality of the China Mission has been no less gratifying to us, and I hope to you, than <add place="supralinear">it has been</add> surprising to many of our <del rend="strikethrough">?</del> doubting friends; and I hope the brief exhibit I am now about to make will not prove her unworthy to <hi rend="underline">still live,</hi> nor less deserving of your <hi rend="underline">fostering care.</hi>          
        </p>
    <p><del rend="strikethrough">She</del> It has been isolated long and separated from you,<del rend="strikethrough"><unclear>??</unclear>read <hi rend="underline">"it"</hi> for<hi rend="underline"> "she"</hi></del>
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-011.jpg"/>
        yet withered not; <del rend="strikethrough">been tempted,</del><add place="supralinear">suffered temptation</add> yet maintained her integrity; distressed, yet despaired not; embarrassed but your Missionaries served tables to minister to her nececissities and she was relieved; destitute, and they made <del rend="strikethrough">?</del> her friends of the mammon of unrighteousness, and wrought with their own hands that she might not be changeable to the beloved, yet more distressed, Mother Church, and at the beginning of the year (1866) eighteen hundred and sixty six, <del rend="strikethrough">she</del> it still survived to the delight of her friends and surprise of all, with her status unimpaired, her missionaries all well; her native church though small, yet vigorous; her operations enlarged, her property intact and her treasury though unreplenished for more than four years, liable for less than a thousand taels.  Is there not in all this reason for profoundest gratitude to God, whose providence hath cherished the orphanage of your infant Mission? and is there not in you, sir, and in the whole church, a heart to embrace it once more?  Or, shall an enterprise so important and so tenacious of life while left to itself, <del rend="strikethrough">?</del><add place="supralinear">and which has</add> outlived its separation and every adversity, to perish at last, if perish it must, in the hands of its friends?  God forbid.        
    </p>
    
    
</div>
</body>
</text>
    </TEI>