<TEI>
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Rev Messrs. Hall &amp; Innocent <date when="1866-11-19">Nov. 19 1866</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic><!-- First name Last name--></sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><date when=""> </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <persName>
                        
                    </persName>
                    
                </person>
           
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date> 
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-08-18">August 18, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="letter">
    <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-007.jpg"/>
    <opener><dateline><name type="place">Shanghai</name><date when="1866-11-19">Nov 19th 1866</date></dateline>
        <salute>Rev Mssrs Hall &amp; Innocent,</salute>
    </opener>
    <p>At our recent Quarterly Mission meeting, a resolution to invite the return of our native brother <hi rend="underline">Hu</hi> (Wu) <hi rend="underline">Ung Ti,</hi> who has been for some time an assistant in your mission, to be stationed at <hi rend="underline">Nankin,</hi> was unanimously adopted.      
    </p>
    <p>
        For several years we had meditated such a course but not until recently did the absolute demands of our work require it.  This step is necessitated new horrors, by the loss of two of our most promisnent and valuable native members, the extension and interest of our work, the eagerness of our members at Nankin for assistance and the prospect of a good work being begun and promoted in their midst and the pressing urgent demand
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-008.jpg"/>
        for his labors in that direction.
    </p>
    <p>
         We could not communicate with him and advise his coming however without first informing you of the facts-  Having  therefore apprized you of the facts and the imperative necessity of our action, we hope you will not only not oppose his coming, but cheerfully give him any assistance that may be required towards securing a passage to Shanghai.
    </p>
    <p>
        All the expenses of which we will defray as a matter of course-
    </p>
    <p>
        As it is too late to make such a change this winter we hope he will hold himself ready to come by the first opportunity in the ensuing spring.  Enclosed I send you a letter addressed to him on the subject, which I hope you will kindly deliver.
    </p>
    <p>
        Your successes cheer and encourage us. <del rend="strikethrough">and</del> Praying God's blessing on you personally and the work which you have so promisingly developed I am your Brother in Christ
        <signed><persname>Young J. Allen</persname></signed>
    </p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
    </TEI>