<TEI xml:id="yja-1880-04-03.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Dr. Wilson, <date when="1880-04-03"><!-- April 3, 1880 --></date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
              <choice>
                <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
              </choice>
            </name>
	</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Dr. Wilson, <date when="1880-04-03">November 8, 1890</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="thyun">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>T.</forename>
                        <forename>H.</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1865">
                        <placeName>
                           <country>Korea</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945
                    </death>
                </person>
           <person xml:id="wac">
            <persName>
              <forename>Warren</forename>
              <forename>Akin</forename>
              <surname>Candler</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1857-08-23">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1941-09-25">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </death>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="tsoong">
            <persName>
              <forename>Kia</forename>
              <forename>Tsing</forename>
              <surname>Tsoong</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName>
              <forename>George</forename>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
            </persName>
          </person>
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2011-06-16">June 16, 2011</date>
                <name xml:id="MJT">Jae Turner </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
  <body>
    <div type="letter" xml:id="yja-1880-04-03.002">
      <pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_015.jpg"/>
      <opener>
	<dateline>
	  <name type="place">Shanghai China</name>
	  <date when="1880-04-03">April 3, 1880</date></dateline>
	  <salute>My dear Dr. Wilson,</salute></opener>

<p>In a <del rend="strikethrough">previous</del> <add place="supralinear">recent</add> letter you requested me to make a note of such incidents and particulars in connection with my work as might prove of interest in connection with our purposed Bulletins of Missionary News.  Accordingly I now send you the following items:</p>

<p><hi rend="center"><hi rend="underline">100 good to the line.</hi></hi><lb/>
A recent letter from <hi rend="underline">Tai-Yuen</hi> fu, capital of Shansi in North China, contains this note =  <quote>"A gentleman just from Peking told me that the Tsung-li Yamen <add place="supralinear">(Chinese Foreign Office)</add> are preparing a commentary (Choo Kiai) on your <hi rend="underline">"China and Her Neighbors."</hi></quote>  <del rend="strikethrough"> If true the</del>  The full title of the work is as follows:
<hi rend="center">China and Her Neighbors</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="center">A Tract for the Times</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="center">Being</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="center">Designed to promote peace and encourage</hi><lb/>
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_016.jpg"/>
progress, by setting forth the motions and objects of Foreigners in coming to China, and the Spirit and Manner in which the demands of the situation should be met by the Imperial God, etc. etc etc.
<hi rend="center">With Maps</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="center">and</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="center">An Appendix,</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="center">Containing important Foreign and Native official Documents bearing on the questions discussed.</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="center">By</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="center">Rev. Young J. Allen</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="center">Editor Man <unclear reason="illegible">Kuoh</unclear> Kung Pa <del rend="strikethrough">n</del> <add place="supralinear">u</add></hi><lb/>
(5 Thousand) etc. etc. etc.</p>

<p>The Questions discussed are as follows -- the Commercial and Political relations of China and Foreign Countries and the Missionary and Mohammedian Questions --  It is an original <add place="supralinear">work and</add> <del rend="strikethrough">so you will see it</del> was primarily designed for the officials.  An Edition of five thousand copies was struck off in 1876 and nearly the whole of them have been disposed <unclear reason="folded corner">of</unclear>.
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_018.jpg"/>
I knew it had found great favor in the eyes of the high Mandarins but it never occurred to me that such a reception would be accorded to it in the Capital.  If true it has obtained precedence of any work hitherto published by Foreigners and is destined to far exceed my utmost hopes in regard to its circulation and influence in the Empire.</p>

<p><hi rend="center">"<hi rend="underline">Rationale of Foreign Missions.</hi>"</hi><lb/>
The same correspondent in a previous letter notified me that he had taken the liberty of republishing, for special distribution among the literati of <add place="supralinear">the</add> Shansi province, my recent Greek Conference Essay, entitled "Rationale of Foreign Missions."  An Edition of 4,500 copies was speedily disposed of.  The same Essay has since been adopted by our Chinese Religions Tract Society and will soon be issued in sufficient numbers to meet the demand.</p>
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_019.jpg"/>
<p><hi rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Corea</hi></hi><lb/>
A recent letter from the Agent of the Scotch Bible Society in Peking says that my paper, the Chinese Globe Magazine, and the work first mentioned above, China and Her Neighbors, have proven very acceptable to the <hi rend="underline">Coreans</hi> who have quick exhausted his supply.  More copies have been forwarded and it is hoped that that last of the hermit nations of the Earth will profit betimes by the lessons she is now purchasing so cheaply.  What an engine is the press!  Our books are preceding us into all this vast country and even going beyond into such places as <hi rend="underline">Corea</hi> where never foot of Protestant Missionary has trod.</p>

<p><hi rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Sandwich Islands</hi></hi><lb/>
By last U.S. Mail I had a letter from a <del>native</del> <add place="supralinear">Chinese</add> Pastor in the Sandwich Islands.  He is a regular <del>reader</del> subscriber to my paper and now writes wishing to contribute $50. to our newly organized <del>Reli</del> Chinese
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_021.jpg"/>
Religious Tract Society and thereby secure a Life Membership.  The Angel <unclear reason="illegible">having</unclear> the glorious Gospel for the nations is now <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" extent="1"/> all abroad.  The signs of the times are full of triumph and glory to the cause of the blessed Redeemer.</p>

<p><hi rend="center"><hi rend="underline">My Day School</hi></hi><lb/>
In a previous letter I mentioned that the School would probably open with <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" extent="1"/> of 20 pupils but to my utter embarrassment <add place="supralinear">as well as astonishment</add> no less than 34 insisted on coming when the school began.  That number is entirely too large for one teacher and would suffice to make two schools of the ordinary size.  But want of funds forecloses the possibility of engaging a second teacher.  So it has been arranged to utilize the services of one of the elder boys.</p>

<p><hi rend="center"><hi rend="underline">My Sunday School</hi></hi><lb/>
It still continues large <del rend="strikethrough">and</del> 
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_022.jpg"/>
and interesting.  My chief want now is competent teachers -- which are not to be had.  There was a time when I thought it might be necessary to subsidize the teachers of Day Schools in the vicinity in order to keep up a good Sunday School but I find <del rend="strikethrough">that will not</del> no lack of pupils without.</p>

<p>Other items I reserve for a future occasion.</p>
<closer><salute>Yours faithfully</salute><signed>Young J. Allen</signed></closer>

<postscript><p>P.S.
As you may not have seen copies of the books referred to above I send specimens <del rend="strikethrough">copies</del> herewith.</p></postscript><signed>Y.J.A.</signed>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>