<TEI xml:id="yja-1880-08-08.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mellie Allen, <date when="1880-08-08">August 8, 1880</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
              <choice>
                <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
              </choice>
            </name>
	</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mellie Allen, <date when="1880-08-08">August 8, 1880</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="thyun">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>T.</forename>
                        <forename>H.</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1865">
                        <placeName>
                           <country>Korea</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945
                    </death>
                </person>
           <person xml:id="wac">
            <persName>
              <forename>Warren</forename>
              <forename>Akin</forename>
              <surname>Candler</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1857-08-23">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1941-09-25">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </death>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="tsoong">
            <persName>
              <forename>Kia</forename>
              <forename>Tsing</forename>
              <surname>Tsoong</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName>
              <forename>George</forename>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
            </persName>
          </person>
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    <item>Missionaries -- China.</item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2011-06-28">June 28, 2011</date>
                <name xml:id="MJT">Jae Turer </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
  <body>
    <div type="letter" xml:id="yja-1880-08-08.002">
      <pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_039.jpg"/>
      <opener>
	<dateline>
	  <name type="place">Shanghai</name>
	  <date when="1880-08-08">Aug 8th 1880</date></dateline>
	  <salute>My dear Mellie,</salute></opener>

<p>Your letter of Aug 6th has just come to hand.  How quickly it made the <unclear reason="illegible">route</unclear>.  I was beginning to think that you had forgoten me, and might also forget the mail.  I am very glad you have written to Mrs. McGavock.  I have enclosed your letter with mine and hope the matter will now be definitely settled.  A lady, Mrs. W.P. Pattillo wrote me by last mail and said that she had seen Dr. Wilson, our <unclear reason="illegible">Missry</unclear> Secretary, who told her that a lady had already proposed to him to become responsible for your support as a missionary.  You see therefore that a great deal of interest is attached to your action in the matter.
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_039.jpg"/>
The attempt to strictly conform to their bye-laws in the matter of engagements may cause some embarrassment to the Woman's Board, but I hardly think they will let the opportunity of engaging your services slip altogether.  You may therefor get up all the strength and health you can while away for when you come back you will find plenty to do.</p>
<p>The Church has not been so crowded with women since you left.  Many still come however and look around with a good of bewilderment for you and the organ.  Last Sunday some very respectable <unclear reason="illegible">wives</unclear> came in.  There was also a very beautiful little girl that I wished you could see.  She is going to a day school and can read I believe.  When you 
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_041.jpg"/>
return you must look her up.  There is plenty of work now open for you among the women and I think you can get access to the better classes when you come back.  You must try.  Well, we have been singing on our own account.  We got the words right, but I cannot vouch for the tune.  The people came to see and many <sic>staid</sic>.  Last night we had a very good congregation.  One young man joined us on probation.  There are now 45 names on the list.</p>
<p>I am having holiday this week.  It is very quiet and cool at home.  I enjoy the <hi rend="underline">lone</hi> part as much as you do the <hi rend="underline">absent</hi> part.  I never saw such fine weather.  It is just like May.  Has only rained once since you left.  I am glad you are enjoying yourself.  Had two letters
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_041.jpg"/>
from M&#x00E1;ma.  Sent up all your things this p.m. for Shi <hi rend="underline">Hae-an</hi> cf Rev. Mr. Greenwood.</p>
<p>Will attend to the payment of the acct. Mrs. W. gave you.</p>
<p>Hope to hear from you again soon.  Take good care of yourself and of M&#x00E1;ma.  Be a good girl.</p>
<p>Give my love to Maggie and <unclear reason="illegible">Kim</unclear> and regards to Mrs. Williamson.  Tell Maggie I should be delighted to have her pay us another Christmas visit or rather one to embrace the Christmas and N Year, in other words to have her finish out her former visit.</p>
<p>Love to Mama and all the dear babies.</p>
<closer><salute>In <unclear reason="illegible">best</unclear> -- Ever<lb/>Your Afft Papa</salute><signed>Young J. Allen</signed></closer>
    </div>
  </body>
</text>
</TEI>