<TEI xml:id="yja-1858-05-20.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Valedictory to Faculty, President and Class, <date when="1858-05-20">May 20th 1858</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic>A. Y. J. W. Allen</sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Valedictory to Faculty, President and Class<date when="1858-05-20">May 20th 1858 </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <persName>
                        
                    </persName>
                    
                </person>
           
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date> 
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-06-22">June 22, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="sat">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div>
    <pb facs= "Allen_11_ff3_006.jpg"/>
    <p>Instability and change, fearful as real, seem to be written upon universal nature, experienced in human effort, and seen and felt in the vicissitudes of life- This old scarred and chaotic earth, upon which we live, has passed through many a geological convulsion, and we have no reason to conclude that even at her present age or state she is freed from fearful apprehensions of future plutonic fires, outbursting floods, upheaving continents, or oceans settling down, such as have begun and ended many a cycle in her long past, nay, she sometimes groans and moves from beneath in awful intiation that she is not secure even now from <del rend= "strikethrough">future</del> <add place="supralinear">future</add> wreck.--</p>
    <p>Human achievements and greatness too are subject alike to the same great laws:</p>    

<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_007.jpg"/>

    <p>Antagonistic forces and influences are ever at work to modify and <del rend="strikethrough">shape</del><add place="supralinear">fix</add> the destinies of the nations.  The rude hand that shapes <add rend="supralinear">(destinies)</add>touches their glory and it withers, lays hold on their monuments and they crumble, snatches crowns and sceptres from Kings and Princes and in a few instances has even blotted out the very name of their country from the catalogue of nations- and so still the genius of that spirit outrides defeat, and is commissioned from above, exercises the functions of general Superintendent, even amid the minor affairs of men and such circumstances as now surround and sadden life's young hopes- </p>
    <p>Long and anxiously have we anticipated this day- this hour, fraught wth so much eventfulness and full of so much mmeaning 

<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_007.jpg"/>

and importance to us- impatiently we awaited it arrival, and thought we often realized that all was passed, but not so; the scenes which wre in imagination then, have become living realities now and we <hi rend="underline">can </hi>and <hi rend="underline">do, </hi>both <hi rend="underline">see </hi>and <hi rend="underline">feel them</hi>-  Yes the eventful day- the day of destiny, perhaps to some <add place="supralinear">of</add> us, has fully come, and I stand here as the humble organ of my class to give expression to what our full heart feels on this parting occasion-</p>
    <p>And to you first my beloved instructors I turn with a tearful heart and a few words- As instructors you have been <sic>dilligent</sic><corr>diligent</corr> and faithful in our behalf; when we were careless, inconsiderate and desponding, tender has been your solicitude, gentle and kind your warnings and admonitions, encouraging and consoling

<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_008.jpeg"/>

        your counsels; thou hast not only directed our erring <add place="supralinear">feet</add> into the way, but hast <hi rend="underline">gone</hi> therein and both by precept and example hath encouraged and led us on; and it is for these offices of kindness so well <hi rend="supralinear">ful</hi>filled that we to day bless thee with our farewell words- and bid thee- Still "rouse to thy work of high &#x0026; holy love;" praying as we leave you, that- "The good begun by thee may onward flow in many a branching stream and wider grow; The seed that in these few and fleeting hours Thy hands unsparing and unwearied have sown may deck thy grave with amaranthine flowers And gild thee fruits divine in heaven's immortal bowers."  Farewell <hi rend="underline">farewell</hi>    </p>
    <p>And now to you, our honored and beloved President, we turn our hearts with our eyes, bathed in unseen but <hi rend="underline"> felt tears</hi>- and before we go hence, would with gratitude

<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_009.jpg"/>

        and confession acknowledge the thousand obligations under which thou hast place us to thee- Judicious and prudent yet faithful has been your administration- parental and kind your guardianship and earnest and anxious your calls and counsels, as a minister of Christ, to us, to secure the abiding presence of <hi rend="underline">one gentle and unreproaching friend,</hi> whose voice is ever in alliance with goodness and virtue, and (is) able to smooth misfortune and reclaim from folly-  Here, you have tried to encourage us to identify ourselves with the happiness of that nature to which our immortality belongs.  Here, you have struggled to lay the foundation of an early and permanent piety <add place="supralinear">in our hearts;</add> and amid the magnificent systems of material signs in which we reside 
        
<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_010.jpg"/>

       you have placed in our hands, and recommended its <sic>dilligent</sic><corr>diligent</corr> use, the mighty key- The Holy Bible- which can unlock and interpret them all-  Here, thou hast taught us to look upon the universe which we inhabit, not as the abode only of human fares or human <del rend="strikethrough">sorrows </del>joys, but as the temple of the living God, in which praise is due, and where service is to be performed- 
    </p>
    <p>But alas! painful thought, a few brief hours more, and all these things live only in memory- <del rend="strikethrough">but</del> <add place="supralinear">Aye </add> it is so, , and it avails naught, to "lengthen these sweet, sad moments out," since the "word that hath been and must <hi rend="underline">now </hi>be, the sound that makes us linger" must be spoken,
    </p>
    <p>Then Farewell Beloved President- 

<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_010.jpg"/>

Now turns my soul to you, my dearly beloved Class-mates, as it hath ne'er done before; and as it may be the last time forever, my thoughts stagger, <del rend="strikethrough">and </del>words fail to express and my lips to utter what "<hi rend="underline">the heart feels</hi> most."-  "This is our last fond meeting, our last farewell;- the world is wide and we must dwell apart."  But before my spirit gives thee now its last fond greeting, let us once more retrospect to-gether a few of the scenes,  where memory loves to dwell, and over which she will in years to come "fondly brood with wiser care"-  Many of us have taken sweet counsel and held holy communion together, in private walks and secret meditations- sweet associations cluster about recitation room and study hall- but oh! how

<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_011.jpg"/>

            <hi rend="underline"> more sweet</hi> and <hi rend="underline">hallowed the remembrances</hi> that come up from the <hi rend="underline">prayer</hi> and <hi rend="underline"> class</hi>room-  But these, all these must be left now, and the word of instruction, prayer and praise fall upon other ears- 
    </p>
    <p>But before we part (and) <add place="supralinear">to</add> return to our homes and the friends of our youth, permit me as your affectionate friend and classmate to <hi rend="underline">assure</hi> you- "Diverse though our paths in life may be, Each is <hi rend="underline">sent </hi>some <hi rend="underline">mission </hi> to fulfill; And fellow-workers still we may be, If we seek to do our Master's will."        
    </p>
    <p>The convictions of duty, the calls of heaven and the claims of humanity- (now) <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="underline"> all</hi></add> urge <hi rend="supralinear">us</hi> to tear away the tendrils of our affections from these green retreats, walks and halls and each other
        
<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_012.jpg"/>

        upon which we have so long leaned as "the olive and the vine," and go forth as voyagers upon life's uncertain sea-  But before we go, Dear Classmates, before we enter our barks for life- let's tear loose "hope's anchor from the sands of time" and fasten <add place="supralinear">it</add> (to) in eternal moorings within the vail of providence, where it shall never rust nor its cables fail-  Then let falsehood, malice or envy rage-  Misfortunes, afflictions and trials come- the world in furious hate ply her <del rend="strikethrough">powers</del><add place="supralinear">energies </add>and spring temptation's powers and threaten to prostrate us- nay, let ocean forget her bed, the winds their  hills to toss and drown our tiny sail- yet, moored on the <hi rend="underline">Rock of Ages</hi>, the Soul's great Sea shall be calm and her skies be clear- and "with joys unmeasured as

<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_013.jpg"/>

        as Eternity, <lb/>
        We'll ply on seas of glass our golden oars And pluck immortal fruits along the shore,"<lb/>
        And soon beyond the clouds, beyond the stars, beyond this mortal vision, shall we <del rend="strikethrough">come</del> <add place="supralinear">meet</add> again in immortal triumph; and crowned with everlasting honors strike <del rend="strikethrough">??the</del> up earth's rapturous chorus on heaven's harps and sing once again, <lb/>
        "Oh! the hope, the glorious hope,<lb/>
        The hope through Jesus given,<lb/>
        The hope when days and years are past <add place="supralinear">past</add><lb/>
        We all shall meet again in heaven
    </p>
        <p>Or thus if you like<lb/>
            Oh! tis the hope, the glorious hope<lb/>
            The hope through Jesus given<lb/>
            The hope <del rend="strikethrough">when</del> <add place="supralinear">now</add> days and years are past<lb/>
            That's brought us all safe home to heaven."            
        </p>
    <p>Now farewell Dear Classmates till that blissful hope be realized and we all meet again in endless reunion in happy heaven-- Mollie Houston</p>

<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_013.jpg"/>
     
        <p>Now My <hi rend="underline">Dearest, My precious Mollie,</hi> I have fulfilled your request- and though very hastily and by <hi rend="underline">guess</hi>, I sincerely hope it will not <hi rend="underline">disappoint</hi> you.
        </p>
        <p>My <hi rend="underline">Dear One, you know</hi> I have <hi rend="underline">yet</hi>
            to learn <hi rend="underline">how</hi> to <hi rend="underline">refuse you</hi>, if I know it ever- no, no.  I <hi rend="underline">never will</hi>; if <hi rend="underline">you</hi> ask anything of your own; shall I say, Dear Young, <hi rend="underline">he will never turn you away</hi>- Isn't so My Dear?-            
        </p>
        <p>Mollie permit me to write you just a few lines to fill out this sheet- I am now out of College and free for the first time in my life from such sedentary restraints-  I left Oxford on the 3d <del rend="strikethrough">of </del>inst.-visited the Gen-Conference in Nashville and remained 6 days, a pretty regular attendant upon <del rend="strikethrough">their</del> <add place="supralinear">its</add> sittings.  Our case as you already know is before the Board and Bps for their decision and direction- their meeting however will not be held until toward the close of the Conference- and therefore we will not be able to know their decision nor our
        
<pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_014.jpg"/>

            destiny until after the Conf is approved, perhaps- <add place="supralinear">Will you please Mollie write me a few lines and send them in Mellies' letter, and let me know your mind on those subjects I mentioned, particularly the <hi rend="underline">last one</hi> Write me how you like this Valedict- &amp;c- please send me a Catalogue with your class criticised &amp;c-  I shall visit your commencement if nothing prevents- <hi rend="underline">Dio Volentus</hi> and shall expect you to accompany me to mine-  Mellie &amp; Ranse are coming to spend the day with me to day.  Coming to cheer a <hi rend="underline">lonely bachelor</hi>, Oh!  I wish my Dear Mollie was here to enjoy their visit and stay with me- her own Young-  Be patient dear one- the time will soon com when <hi rend="underline">you shall return home- My heart, my house, my arms are waiting to receive you now-</hi></add></p>
        <p>You still <hi rend="underline">feel willing</hi> to go <hi rend="underline">anywhere</hi>, so you <hi rend="underline">My Mollie</hi>; even willing to stay at home and labor here in our own Country, in our own state or to go far away in "heathen lands to dwell" if the Lord wills it, do you My <hi rend="underline">precious One</hi>?  Bless the Lord I <hi rend="underline">believe thou art willing</hi>-
        </p>
        <p>My Mollie, I never wanted to see you <hi rend="underline">so bad</hi> in all my life before- and I must here, <del rend="strikethrough">make </del>in justice to my <hi rend="underline">own pure love for you</hi> and the confidence you repose in my sincerity, tell you that it is <hi rend="underline">my desire and wish</hi>, and I do hope it will be <hi rend="underline">yours also</hi>, to consummate our engagement just as soon as we can- and in view of this, I have been looking forward to the opportunity which I think will be afforded to have it done in Oxford on Thursday morning after my Graduation- just one week, it will be, after yours-  Now, Mollie, I am serious in this request, and hope you will regard it as an expression coming from the very bottom of my soul's affections- which are all intertwined with thine own-  Please, don't refuse me; (<hi rend="underline">this time)</hi>- My Mollie, I would say much more on this subject, even if I had to get another sheet, but I fear, as I feel so <hi rend="underline">simple</hi> and <hi rend="underline">earnest and <add place="supralinear">even </add> childish</hi>, in my great love for you, that you might be disposed to smile at me, and <hi rend="underline">then</hi> turn me away- <hi rend="underline">but I do hope My Mollie will not.</hi>            
        </p>
<p><add place="topmargin">Will you please Mollie write me a few lines and send them in Mellies' letter, and let me know your mind on those subjects I mentioned, partiularly the <hi rend="underline">last one</hi> Write me how you like this Valedict- &amp;c- please send me a Catalogue with your class criticised &amp;c-  I shall visit your commencement if nothing prevents- <hi rend="underline">Deo Volentus</hi> and shall expect you to accompany me to mine--  Mellie &amp; <unclear>Kanso</unclear> are coming to spend the day with me to day.  Coming to cheer a <hi rend="underline">lonely bachelor</hi>, Oh!  I wish my Dear Mollie was here to enjoy their visit and stay with me-- her own Young--  Be patient dear one-- the time will soon com when <hi rend="underline">you shall return home-- My heart, my house, my arms are waiting to receive you now--</hi></add></p>
    <closer><salute>Mollie I am <hi rend="underline">Your own devoted Young forever</hi>-</salute></closer>
    
    
</div>
</body>
    <back>
        <div type="envelope">
            <pb facs="Allen_11_ff3_015.jpg"/>
            <dateline>
                <placeName>Macon Georgia</placeName>
                <lb/>
                <date when="1857-05-22">May 22 '57</date></dateline>
            <p><address>
                <persName>Miss Mollie Houston</persName>
                <lb/>
                <addrLine>W. F. College</addrLine>
                <addrLine>Macon</addrLine>
                <lb/>
                <addrLine>Georgia</addrLine>
                <lb/>
                <addrLine>Care of</addrLine>
                <lb/>
                <addrLine>Prest. Smith</addrLine>
            </address></p>
        </div>
    </back>
</text>
    </TEI>