<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to his church Board, <date when="1868-12-09"
                        >December 9, 1868</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to his church Board, <date when="1868-12-09"
                        >December 9, 1868</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and
                    Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region>/><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-08-21">August 21, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_027.jpg"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Shanghai, China,</placeName>
                        <date when="1868-12-09">Dec. 9, 1868.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Missionaries are constantly arriving from England and America. Scarcely a month
                    passes that does not chronicle an addition to our forces. The interior is
                    gradually becoming occupied, and the aspects of our general work all along the
                    coast line are brightening. Toleration is everywhere proclaimed, and the country
                    is now decidedly open and inviting. Mobs, violence and persecution, sometimes,
                    however -- as recently as Yangchow and Formosa -- are still experienced, but
                    their effect rather stimulates than abates the progress of our work.</p>
                <p>We are anxious to see <hi rend="underline">our</hi> stations multiplied, and had
                    hopes that early reinforcements would enable us to move abreast with other
                    missions, but recent letters from the Secretary of the Board and Brother
                    Smithson quite disappoint our expectations in that respect, and in the mean time
                    our only native preacher has sickened and died, leaving us almost helpless and
                    hopeless.</p>
                <p>By the mail just in, we are in receipt of a small remittance from the Treasurer,
                    which has been appropriated to paying off the balance of our debt, which is now
                    reduced to a minimum. But he gives us but little encouragement for the future.
                        <hi rend="underline">What are we to do</hi>? For ourselves we have resolved
                    the question: <hi rend="underline">We will never abandon the China mission</hi>.
                    You can't starve us out. The siege has lasted seven years, and though it last as
                    many more we will not surrender. But perhaps you -- I mean the church -- are too
                    well satisfied of that already; hence do not concern yourself about it.</p>
                <p>Under the circumstances I am not able to preach much, but am doing the next thing
                    to it -- teaching and printing. From nine<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_029.jpg"/>
                    till twelve o'clock I am engaged in the Anglo-Chinese school, which consists of
                    fory young men, who are looking forward to appointments as the future ministers
                    and consuls to Western nations. They are of the higher and better class of
                    Chinese society, and I have so far succeeded in gaining their confidence that I
                    have no hesitation in pronouncing the school under my control and influence. I
                    shall not give it up again voluntarily. Every other afternoon, from one o'clock
                    till five P.M., is devoted exclusively to the tri-weekly newspaper, of which I
                    am editor. It is a secular paper, chiefly occuupied with the news, foreign and
                    domestic, scientific instruction, etc., and advertisements. It has numerous
                    readers, and through it I hope to instruct a large number in the knowledge of
                    the truth, and thus, by removing the basis of many of their superstitions,
                    prepare them for the truth as it is in Jesus. They all know the edtor as a <hi
                        rend="underline">Kiau Sz</hi>. The balance of my time is employed editing
                    the Native Church Intelligencer, our only church organ, of which I am also
                    proprietor. It has met with wonderful success, and has been most highly
                    commended by our oldest and foremost missionaries. The native churches are
                    delighted with it, and the native preachers heartily support it. It is taken by
                    all the missions, without exception, and circulates at all the ports and in the
                    interior, wherever there is a native preacher. You see, therefore, that I am
                    fully employed, and perhaps as usefully employed, and as successfully as is
                    possible.</p>
                <p>As a teacher and editor, I have access to all classes, and that constantly. If
                    the Board wishes me to release the school and papers<pb/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff8_031.jpg"/> I will do so, provided they will enable me,
                    without distraction, to do something better. But until then I shall never
                    voluntarily surrender my present position before this people, thirsting for
                    knowledge and dying without salvation. Under the circumstances I need to
                    apologize for brevity and haste.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>Y. J. Allen</signed>
                </closer>
                <p/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
