<TEI xml:id="yja-undated.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Dr Lehon, <date when="1868">1868?</date>, an
                    electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Dr Lehon, <date when="1868">1868?</date>;
                    Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory
                    University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-08-21">August 21, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="ypw">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">  <head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Dr Lehon]</head>
                
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF8_009.jpg"/>  <lb/>

                <opener>
                    <salute>My dear Dr. Lehon,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>Your letter of June 18th from <unclear>N. Binh</unclear> is at hand. Thanks for your
                    kind expression to us personally, and the assurance of your increasing interest
                    in the China Mission.</p>
                <p>We are happy to be brought once more face to face with you and the Board, under
                    new and more promising circumstances, and gladly avail<unclear>of</unclear> the
                    present opportunity to renew a correspondence which has <add place="supralinear"
                        >been</add> so long violently suspended.</p>
                <p>We were from Oct. 1861 till March 1866 without communication or remittance from
                    you, the war having interrupted the <unclear>one</unclear> and so impoverished our
                    people, that we did not expect <del rend="strikethrough"><gap unit="word" extent="1"/></del> the <unclear>other</unclear>. No
                    alternative or means was left us therefore during that long interval to meet our
                    wants and promote the welfare of your <unclear>mission</unclear> other than a judicious use
                    of the <unclear>mission</unclear> property and personal effort.</p>
                <p>In 1862-4-5 I sent home <add place="supralinear">duplicate</add> reports, <del
                        rend="strikethrough">duplicated</del> of each year respectively, showing the
                    condition and prospects of the <unclear>mission</unclear> at the date of each
                    communication. In July of this year I forward a full statement of the mission
                    finances to Dr. McFerrin which I presume will have reached you
                        <unclear>ere</unclear> this comes to hand, and will therefore
                    
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF8_010.jpg"/>

                    <add place="supralinear">obviate</add> the
                    necessity for introducing particulars into this letter. From that statement you
                    will be able to ascertain how far we succeeded in accomplishing our object <del
                        rend="strikethrough">and preserving the mission alive, comparatively free
                        from debt</del> the preservation of the mission free from debt, intact in
                    property and efficient in labors. Suffice it therefore to say here that when Bro.
                    Cunningham left <del rend="strikethrough">here</del> for America he placed the
                    management of the mission's finances in my hands; <del rend="strikethrough">the
                        mission</del> The Mission was in debt at that time to the amt of 1 thousand
                    taels and he left with me upwards of six hundred taels in treasury. That was <add
                        place="supralinear">Oct</add> 1861. In Jan 1866 <del rend="strikethrough"
                        >nearly five</del><add place="supralinear">more than four</add> years later
                    the mission was in debt <del rend="strikethrough">only</del> for an amt. less
                    than 1 <unclear>thou</unclear> taels with an empty treasury. <del
                        rend="strikethrough">thus</del> <del rend="strikethrough">establishing</del>  a result accomplished, without
                    either sacrifice or mortgage of <unclear>mission</unclear> property or serious interruption of
                    our labors by personal effort. Our difficulties and embarrassments have been
                    complicated and preplexing, the existence of the mission was periled, <del
                        rend="strikethrough">anxiety</del> <unclear>interest</unclear> solicitude to keep
                    the <del rend="strikethrough">mission</del><add place="supralinear">it</add>
                    untrammelled till the close of the war and the ren<add place="supralinear"
                        >ew</add>al of commerce &#x0026; remittances from home could come to our
                    relief, absorbed all our thoughts and shaped all our efforts. <del
                        rend="strikethrough">Should you and the Board</del> We hope therefore that
                    the result

<pb facs="Allen_11_FF8_010.jpg"/>

                    accomplished and the present situation of the Mission <add place="supralinear">which not all it could be desired</add> will be as
                    gratifying to yourself and the Board as it is to us who have struggled so hard
                    to outlive our adversities.</p>
                <p>Having premised thus much as to the past I will now proceed to answer your
                    questions as far as I may <del rend="strikethrough">in</del>
                    <unclear>seriation</unclear>.</p>
                <p>1st The Mission property consists of three premises, known respectively as the
                    Cunningham house, at present occupied by Bro. Lambuth. The old
                    Lambuth house, at present occupied by the French <unclear><foreign xml:lang="la">Milice</foreign></unclear> as a
                    police station and the new Mission premises occupied by
                    myself and Bro Wood, which was built with part of the proceeds of the sale of
                    the place known as the Dr Jenkins' house. Besides the mission has a small place
                    purchases of Lien <unclear>Sien Sang</unclear> our native preacher, and
                    occupied exclusively by Chinese. In addition to the above there are two small
                    chapels, one situated near the center of Shanghai City and one outside the city
                    on the new Mission premises, where it was moved in 1862 in
                    consequence of the French making new roads and <unclear>shutting</unclear> it
                    in where it formerly stood on the Cunningham lot.</p>
                <p>There is also a preaching place fitted up at <unclear>Nan Tsiang</unclear> about
                    16 miles from Shanghai and one in <unclear>Ka'ding</unclear>, both of which are
                    owned by the mission <del rend="strikethrough">and</del>. They were purchased however
                    
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF8_011.jpg"/>

                    not by mission funds, but with means
                    contributed to me for that purpose by some generous persons in the community.
                    All these places, with <add place="supralinear">the exception of the preaching
                        place in <unclear>Kading</unclear></add> are now in good repair and comfortable. Their value
                    however at this is merely nominal- indeed I doubt if they could be sold at any
                    price- not because they are not desirable or valuable, but the demand for them
                    has abated- speculations in land &#x0026; houses has ceased and the war in
                    America which concentrated many foreigners here and brought large trade and the
                    Rebellion here having been put down allow the return of the great influx of
                    Chinese population has depressed the market and driven all such things out-
                    hence the best valuation I can now set upon them is the appraisement value made
                    by the French <unclear><foreign xml:lang="la">Milice</foreign></unclear> with a view to taxation. All our premises are
                    in the French Concession, which amount in the aggregate is about 15 thousand
                    taels or 20 thousand Mexican dollars more or less. The church property will
                    perhaps amount to two perhaps 3 thousand taels. They are all small and make
                    rather an insignificant show compared to other Mission Churches.</p>
                <p>2d As to the membership of the <unclear>Native</unclear> Church--<lb/>It was
                    stated by Bro Cunningham at the <unclear>Genl.</unclear> Conference I believe
                    that the number of native members was <hi rend="underline">thirty</hi>, I do not
                    wish to contradict that statement</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
