<TEI xml:id="yja-1866-07-20.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Statement of mission finances compiled by Young John Allen <date ></date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA 30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><date> </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <persName>
                        
                    </persName>
                    
                </person>
           
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date> 
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
		    <item>Missionaries -- China.</item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-08-25">August 25, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="sat">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="letter">
    <pb facs="Allen_11_FF7_017.jpg"/>
    <p>Enclosed I send you a full statement of the Mission finances, including <del rend="strikethrough">all</del> all monies <add place="supralinear">borrowed</add> for which the mission is liable-  Exclusive of the Bible and Tract funds which Bro Cunningham transferred to the <unclear>Girl</unclear>, Miss account in July 1861 before leaving for America, the amount of outstanding Mission debt at the beginning of 1866 amounted to only 983 taels, <del rend="strikethrough">but as</del> the Mission treasury <add place="supralinear"><unclear>however</unclear></add> at that time <del rend="strikethrough"><unclear>was</unclear></del> <add place="supralinear">was</add> exhausted, we had to borrow of the Mercantile Community in Shanghai<add place="supralinear">to meet amt of debt then due and supply</add><add place="supralinear">current expenses of miss.</add>hoping that in the amts, so <unclear>?</unclear> should fall due the Board might be able to make us remittances sufficient to repay them and meet the expenses of the Miss for the future-
    </p>    
    <p>Our remittance has been received <add place="supralinear">and part of the money borrowed has been returned</add> but we could not <del rend="strikethrough">use it to pay out liquidate</del> under the circumstances <add place="supralinear">to </add> <del rend="strikethrough">retire</del>
        <pb facs="Allen_11_FF7_018.jpg"/>
        <add place="supralinear">repay all</add><del rend="strikethrough">the recently made debt;</del> for in that case we should have been embarrassed as much as ever; so it has been held to meet present current expenses, and we still look for a future remittance to meet the accounts which will fall due in May 1867.  The amt, that will fall due <hi rend="underline">in May <add place="supralinear">then</add> 1867</hi> is two thousand taels, bearing interest at 8 pec. per annum-  The other amts. may continue in abeyance so far as I can see without giving rise to any grievance on the part of those to whom they are due-    
    </p>
    <p>In addition to <add place="supralinear">the</add> amt. of in <unclear>d?</unclear> which it will be necesary to meet on <add place="supralinear">the </add>first of May next, there is the current expenses of the mission for 1867 an estimate of which I herewith forward.          
    </p>
    <p>For salaries of three foreign missionaries--tls-3400 <hi rend="underline">Taels</hi><lb/>
       " Native Assistant  120<lb/>
       " Sexton's wages     36<lb/>
       " Medical service   150<lb/>
       " Teachers' wages   240<lb/>
       " Land &#x0026; municipal taxes about 32<lb/>
       " Incidental expenses 200<lb/>
        which will amount to 4178 Taels
        This may seem <del rend="strikethrough">like</del><add place="supralinear">to be</add> a large estimate, and indeed it is, but when we consider that Shanghai is pronounced by all the most expensive place, perhaps in all the East, and that the salary of a <hi rend="underline">missionary family</hi> resident here, amts to but little more than the allowance of an individual <add place="supralinear">about 2500</add>  
        <pb facs="Allen_11_FF7_019.jpg"/>
        clerk in the business community for the simple and single item of lodging and board alone <del rend="strikethrough">per annum, it</del> It can not be <del rend="strikethrough">considered</del> <add place="supralinear">regarded</add> an <choice><sic>exagerated</sic><corr>exaggerated</corr></choice> estimate, but<add place="supralinear"> as an amount </add>demanded by the necessities of <add place="supralinear">the</add> case to enable the missionary to maintain his efficiency in active <del rend="strikethrough">mission</del> <hi rend="underline">operations.</hi>  Accompanying this I also forward the folloing statements from your missionaries-  
    </p>
    <p>1st  A personal statement of the in debt of miss to <del rend="strikethrough">?</del> <add place="supralinear">Rev. M. <unclear>t.</unclear></add> Wood for monies which he either borrowed or realized  from personal efforts and used to relieve the mission during its great embarrassment
    </p>
    <p>
        2d A <del rend="strikethrough">similar</del> statement of similar import from <unclear>G.W. Lambeth</unclear>
    </p>
    <p>3d Also one from myself showing the amt. of personal funds used to relieve the burden of the Miss in <unclear>?</unclear><del rend="strikethrough">The amt of Taels &#x0026;c</del> Herewith I also enclose a statement of what the Mission is due me personally, for monies of my own appropriated in behalf of the Mission to relieve its embarrassment, and save it from<del rend="strikethrough"><unclear>?</unclear></del> encumbering itself <add place="supralinear">further </add>by seeking a loan in <del rend="strikethrough">the community.</del>
    </p>
    <p>This amt. of taels 827.49 I consider the Mission justly indebted to me- <add place="supralinear">It</add> <del rend="strikethrough">but expended then But</del> expended in behalf of the Mission to save it from calamity then, <add place="supralinear">But </add>I freely forgive all claim against <add place="supralinear">the Board</add> now, and though I have shared, yea doubly shared the anxieties and embarrassments of the last four years of your Mission's perilous history, and suffered the loss of a large part of my personal estate <del rend="strikethrough">?</del> <add place="supralinear">in</add> America by the war, yet I cheerfully do what I do
    
    <pb facs="Allen_11_FF7_020.jpg"/>
    and with the prospect of the China Mission being sustained in the future, <add place="supralinear">I</add> <unclear>?</unclear> consecrate myself and my all <add place="supralinear"><unclear>?</unclear></add> to God and his work, praying His most gracious blessing upon you, and the interests which you represent, and that the China Mission may have large favor in the eyes the heart and treasures of our beloved church and people at home
    </p>
    <closer><salute>Yours Affectionately</salute><lb/>
    <signed><persName>Young J. Allen</persName></signed></closer>
    <postscript><p>20th July 1866</p>
<p>and a more glorious and successful career <add place="supralinear"> of usefulness</add> in China, I now enclose in behalf of the Mission &#x0026; its <unclear>?</unclear> the <unclear>acc--? ??</unclear> &#x0026; statements, all of which is most respectfully submitted by your aff but <unclear>?, Bro in Christ</unclear></p></postscript>

</div>
</body>
</text>
    </TEI>