<TEI xml:id="yja-1866-11-19new.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>letter to Dr. Thomas from Young John Allen <date when="1866-11-19"> Nov 19 1866</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic>Young J Allen</sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><date> </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <persName>
                        
                    </persName>
                    
                </person>
           
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date> 
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-08-25">August 25, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="sat">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="letter">
    <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-021.jpg"/>
<opener>
    <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi>
    <dateline><name type="place">Shanghai China</name><date when="1866-11-09">Nov 19th 1866</date></dateline><lb/>
    <salute>My dear Dr. Thomas,</salute></opener>
        <p>In a letter to Dr. E H Myers dated August 28th 1866, I notified my intention to forward at an early date some relics and specimens of Chinese art &#x0026; Literature as a contribution to the Cabinet and Library of your College, to arrive before the Commencement in July 1867.  Having, therefore in compliance with intention finished or rather cut short my collection for want of means to salvage it at present, I now hasten to forward you an <hi rend="underline">inventory</hi> of the <hi rend="underline">box</hi> I am about to despatch for the clipper ship <hi rend="underline">"Antelope"</hi> from here to N. York.
        </p>
        <p><hi rend="underline">For the Libary</hi>            
        </p>
        <p>Chinese books, upwards of one hundred volumes, including; <lb/>       
         
        1st An immense <hi rend="underline">Chinese Dictionary</hi> with <choice><sic>deffinitions</sic><corr>definitions</corr></choice> in French and Latin by M. D Guignes and published in 1813 by order of Napoleon Bonaparte-the first ever published, and worth from fifty to one hundred dollars at present.
            <lb/>
            Note- Superceded <del rend="strikethrough"> at</del> by Morrison's and Medhurst for general use by English Students. <lb/>
            2d The Chinese Classics with translation and notes also history and biography of their times and authors- by Dr. Legge-<unclear>H--?</unclear><lb/>
            3d Chinese Classics, native edition, foreign bound with commentaries-<lb/>
            4th Agricultural <choice><sic>Enclopedia</sic><corr> Encyclopedia</corr></choice> (2 cases) A Novel<lb/>
            5th <unclear>???</unclear>- or "Dream of the Red Chamber"<lb/>
            6th A number of Rebel books obtained from the <unclear>??</unclear> (Shield King) in Nan Kin during my visit there in 1861<lb/>
            The Coroner's Handbook<lb/>
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-022.jpg"/>
            8th The Sacred Edict- foreign bound.<lb/>
            9th The <hi rend="underline">Li Ki</hi> or "Book of Rites.<lb/>
            10th Description of Shanghai and its Environs traslated from an ancient Chinese miscellany- Also various books translated into Chinese by the Missionaries<lb/>
            1st The Bible- 2 copies- one the London Miss Edition the other the Committee's ed. both in <unclear>??</unclear> or literary classic Style- also parts of the same in Mandarin and Shanghai Colloquials.<lb/>
            2d A comparison of Theology<lb/>
            3d The guide to Heaven<lb/>
            4th Introduction to the doctrines of Christianity<lb/>
            5th The two Friends<lb/>
            6th Arithmetic, Algebra, Geography &#x0026;c<lb/>
            7th Numerous other books including various hymn gooks, catechisms, prayer books, ritual &amp;c also a number of Romanized- i.e. the reading sound of Chinese characters represented by roman letters &#x0026; syllables-<lb/>
         <hi rend="underline">Also</hi><lb/>
        A Japanese Dictionary<lb/>
        One copy in a <unclear>B--?</unclear>dialect- One an Indian dialect<lb/>
        One a hymn book in a modified form of the <choice><sic>Corean</sic><corr>Korean</corr></choice> character<lb/>
        A number of pamphlets pertaining to the discussion of "terms" to be used for God in translating the Bible.
        </p>
    <p>&#x0026; &#x0026; &#x0026;</p>
    <p>For the Cabinet<lb/>
    1st relics from the Porcelain Tower obtained during my recent visit to Nan Kin in September, including-<lb/>
    One, out of the 1800 images of Buddha in bas relief that faced the entire inner surface of the Tower.<lb/>
    2d Relics from Tien <unclear>Wong?</unclear> fu or palace of the Rebel Emperor.<lb/>
        Two fragments from a petrified (?) slab or pillar in a private court of the palace<lb/>
        A fragment of a yellow (royal) tile from the papace roof-<lb/>
        <unclear>D?</unclear> from his private grotto<lb/>
        " " " marble door sill<lb/>
        A long green tile (perfect) from an Empress pavilion on the famous <hi rend="underline">King Shan</hi>- Golden Island- near <hi rend="underline">Chun Kiang fu,</hi> in the Yang tse river.<lb/>
        A common brick and tile from Shanghai<lb/>
        Some fine Specimens of <hi rend="underline">lava</hi> from a partially active <hi rend="underline">Volcano</hi> in the province of <unclear>Ye??</unclear>, in the extreme north of Japan.<lb/>
        Some pebbles from famous <hi rend="underline">Tsih-li-loong</hi> gorge or pass on the <hi rend="underline">Tsien Tang Kiang</hi>, beyond <hi rend="underline">Hang</hi> Chow in  the Chi Kiang province, China<lb/>
        Two or three pieces of carved Stone and jade one a seal such as are in common use- and one representing an ancient cash coin- <hi rend="underline">used as a charm</hi>    </p>
    <p><hi rend="underline">Sundries</hi><lb/>
        Idols-<lb/>
        <hi rend="underline">Tsai Shun</hi> - the god of wealth<lb/>
        Kwan Ying - " The goddess of Mercy" or more <hi rend="underline">the goddess of children or midwifery</hi><lb/>
        <hi rend="underline">Kwan Ti</hi> A sort of devil god or destroyer these three are universally worshipped<lb/>
        A buddhist priest reciting prayers and striking a hollow piece of wood, representing a fish's head- universal practice-<lb/>
        <hi rend="underline">Buttons</hi>- blue, red, grass and white facsimile of those worn in China-<lb/>
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-023.jpg"/>
        One official hat and button (<unclear>?</unclear>) crystal for first prize <hi rend="underline">Sophomore Declamation 1867</hi> if the Faculty approve the novel innovation on old custom-<lb/>
        Two pairs Shoes- presented by <hi rend="underline">Lieu nyang nyang</hi>, the wife of our <unclear>late?</unclear> native preacher <hi rend="underline">Lieu Tsih Sung</hi><lb/>
        One umbrella- bamboo and oil paper-<lb/>
        One Opium pipe- lamp and feeder-<lb/>
        Two other pipes- water and common with tobacco for each- also some Chinese Snuff-<lb/>
        Flint and steel with paper matches- in <unclear>?</unclear><lb/>
        The <choice><sic>Abaceus</sic><corr> Abacus</corr></choice> or counting board-<lb/>
        The gentleman's travelling case, containing chopsticks knife and toothpick- also several common chopsticks<lb/>
        One small box of <unclear>Sy??</unclear> Spirit money- consumed for the benefit of the dead<lb/>
        One <unclear>?/</unclear> of dollars<lb/>
        Two ancient coins and a string of the cash in present use-<lb/>
    </p>
    <p> <hi rend="underline">Also</hi><lb/>
        Six dozen rice or pith paper pictures-<lb/>
        Four others of a large size<lb/>
        Specimens of letters- paper- envelopes- bills- receipts &#x0026;c<lb/>
        Three Specimens of Ladies' head dresses- Scissors, thimble lock and key- comb- candles- wicks- Lamp wicks dominoes and cards-<lb/>
        The Great Plan- or Diagram of the Record <unclear>???</unclear><lb/>
        One carved bamboo cane for the Rev Dr E H Myers<lb/>
        A Specimen of finest tea in China- <hi rend="underline">Pih <unclear>l?? chu??</unclear></hi> for the <hi rend="underline">Faculty</hi>- Presented by the Provincial chancellor at Suchow-   
    </p>
    <p>I exceedingly regret that my collection and contribution is so meager and unsatisfa tory- and hope at no distant day to be able to make another of more interest and value-  What it is and as it is however I forward you, hoping that in due time, say in April next, it will reach you in good order and condition-</p>
        <closer><salute>Affect. yours-</salute><signed>Young J Allen</signed></closer>
        
  
    
        
</div>
</body>
</text>
    </TEI>