<TEI xml:id="yja-1866-08-27.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Dr. Myers, <date when="1866-08-27">August 27, 1866</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic><!-- First name Last name--></sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907></reg>
            
            </choice>
            </name>
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter to Dr. Myers<date when="1866-08-27">Aug. 27 1866 </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <persName>
                        
                    </persName>
                    
                </person>
           
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-08-14">August 14, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="sat">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="letter">
    <pb facs="Allen_11_FF7_004.jpg"/> 
    <opener><dateline><name type="place">Shanghai</name><date when="1866-08-27"> Aug. 27 1866</date></dateline><lb/>
        <salute>My dear Dr. Myers</salute></opener>
    <p>In a previous letter I promised you some particulars as to mission work in China-  Since <del rend="strikethrough">founding that</del> then we have received a communication from Dr. Lehow, the <unclear>Secty of the Board of Missions</unclear> in which he assures us of increasing interest in the China Mission <del rend="strikethrough">but says in which he</del><add place="supralinear">but</add> says "we are heavily pressed with debt and the future dark and gloomy- but I am determined <del rend="strikethrough">to spare no effort </del>under the divine blessings to spare no effort for the full support of your mission, and will as soon as possible make you another remittance."
    </p>
    <p>In view therefore of the pressing wants of this work and an earnest desire to arouse and encourage the church to meet them as far as possible, by yet greater zeal and liberality, I propose to give you some statistics as to what the <hi rend="underline">native converts</hi> themselves, are doing to helpforward the great work which has been begun in their midst.  By a reference to the statistics, forwarded you sometime since
        <pb facs="Allen_11_FF7_005.jpg"/>
        you will see that the whole number of converts to christianity belonging to the various missions here accounted in the aggregate to two thousand six hundred &#x0026; seven (2607) and their contributions to the amount of two thousand nine hundred and eighty eight (2988) dollars, for the year 1864, or more than one dollar per each member.- <del rend="underline">Divided <unclear>in full</unclear></del> Several missions did not report the amount raised by their converts, otherwise the sum might have been larger still.
    </p>
    <p>Now when it is remembered that the class of people most generally represented in our churches are many of them poor indeed, and the most, if not all of them dependent on their daily earnings for the necessaries of life, their liberality is as surprising as larger, and viewed in reference to future operations and success here, is encouraging in the the extreme- Already several churches supply their own native pastor and support him by their own contributions.        
    </p>
    <p>Sometimes the converts express a willingness to give, to aid in support of
    <pb facs="Allen_11_FF7_005.jpg"/>
 the Gospel which has brought glad tidings without money and without price to them, and help extend it to others in their midst and even beyond them, but complain that they are not able, <del rend="strikethrough">but</del> convince them however of the possibility of economizing and they readily make the effort, <del rend="strikethrough">which</del> <add place="supralinear">This statement</add> has been proven and beautifully illustrated in our own little church and as it may prove a valuable suggestion to some of our brethren and members at home, I will tell them how our poor, <add place="supralinear">may</add> should I not call them rich too, church members managed to make a liberal monthly subscription for the promotion of the Gospel, by helping to sustain a native assistant during our severe trials which separated from you and all assistance from home-  I had just been spending some time in conversation and prayer with two of our young men, one of whom we had just set to work as an assistant, and before separating the condition of this Mission at that time 1864 was mentioned, and I told them I thought it would be well <del rend="underline">to have</del><add place="supralinear">for</add> them and the members generally to take more intrerest in its support and especially in sustaining the native agency which at that 
        <pb facs="Allen_11_FF7_006.jpg"/>
        time I was very anxious should not feel the burdens that came upon us, <del rend="strikethrough"> that</del> lest it might cause faintness of heart or confusion of purpose-  They mutually expressed themselves willing  to make any contributions in their power, but were at a loss to ascertain their ability-  After hesitating a moment, I inquired if either of them smoked, which I knew before, nearly all chinamen smoke, they responded in the affirmative, whereupon, I proposed to relieve them of this embarassment in reference to assisting the miss, by suggesting that I smoked also, having contracted the habit in 1862-3 as a sort of disinfectant during the cholera season, when I was daily in contact with it, but that I would be willing to leave it off now as not necessary or indispensable, as rice or tea, and asked if they would consent to do so also; they evidently had not thought of such a modus operandi as that, yet they consented cheerfully- and we immediately proceeded to enroll our names and the several amounts each was to pay per month-  which resulted as follows- I smoked <choice><sic>segars </sic><corr>cigars</corr></choice> though not constantly hence I headed the list with two dollars.
    </p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>