<TEI>
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Dr. McFerrin <date when="1866-07-19" ></date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic><!-- First name Last name--></sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><date when=""> </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <persName>
                        
                    </persName>
                    
                </person>
           
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date> 
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-08-20">August 20, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="letter">
<pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-013.jpg"/>
    <opener>
        <dateline><name type="place">Shanghai China </name><date when="1866-07-19">July 19 1866</date></dateline><lb/><salute>My dear Dr. McFerrin,</salute>
    </opener>
    <p>"The China Mission still lives" said the College of venerable Bishops in their recent address to the Genl. Conference, "and we recommend it to your fostering care."
    </p>
    <p>These thrilling words have reached us freighted with precious promise and pending information as to the sequel, we cherish them as "the substance of  things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen," and I hope the <del rend="strikethrough">exhibit</del> brief exhibit I am now about to make will not prove her <hi rend="underline">unworthy to still live</hi> nor less deserving of your "fostering care."        
    </p>
    <p>The wonderful vitality of the China Mission has been no less gratifying to us, and I hope to you, than surprising to many
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff7-013.jpg"/>
        of our <unclear>?</unclear> friends.
    </p>
    <p>She has been isolated long and separated far from you, yet withered not; tempted yet maintained her integrity; distressed, yet despaired not; embarrassed, yet <del rend="strikethrough">?</del> missionaries served tables to minister to her necessities and she was relieved, destitute and they made to her friends of the mammon of unrighteousness and wrought with their own hands that she might not be chargeable to the beloved yet more distanced Mother Church; and at the beginning of the year 1866 she stood forth <add place="supralinear">to</add> the delight and surprise of <del rend="strikethrough">both </del>friends and foes, with her status still unimpaired, her missionaries all well, her native church though small yet vigorous, her operations enlarged, her property intact, and her treasury though unreplenished for more than four years, liable for less than a thousand taels.  Is there not in all this reason for profoundest gratitude to God who hath cherished the orphanage of your infant mission; and is there not in you, sir and in all the church a heart to embrace it once more; or shall an enerprise so tenacious of life<add place="supralinear"> when left to itself</add> have outlived its separation and every adversity <del rend="strikethrough">only</del> to perish at last if perish it must in the hands of its friends-  God forbid.
        
    </p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
    </TEI>