<TEI xml:id="Montreal.1" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Mary H. Allen to Mellie, <date when="1911-05-18">May 18, 1911</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
             
            <name type="person"><choice>
            <sic>Mary H. Allen</sic>
            <reg>Allen, Mary H.</reg>
            
            </choice></name>
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><!-- replace this with your letter information -->Letter from Mary H. Allen to Mollie, <date when="1911-05-18">May 18, 1911</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="thyun">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>T.</forename>
                        <forename>H.</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1865">
                        <placeName>
                           <country>Korea</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945
                    </death>
                </person>
           <person xml:id="wac">
            <persName>
              <forename>Warren</forename>
              <forename>Akin</forename>
              <surname>Candler</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1857-08-23">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1941-09-25">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </death>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="tsoong">
            <persName>
              <forename>Kia</forename>
              <forename>Tsing</forename>
              <surname>Tsoong</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName>
              <forename>George</forename>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
            </persName>
          </person>
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2008-03-21"><!-- March 21, 2008 --></date>
                <name xml:id="EW"><!-- Erich Wendt --> </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
<change when="2008-04-04" who="#RSV">
        <name xml:id="RSV">Stewart Varner</name> Added Library of
Congress Subject headings and cleaned up the text.
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text><body><div xml:id="yja-18-May-1911" type="letter"><pb  facs="4432.jpg"/>
    <head>[Letter from Mary H. Allen to Mellie]</head>
 <dateline><placeName>Montreal</placeName>:<lb/>  May 18, 1911</dateline>

<salute>Dear <persName>Mollie</persName>,</salute>

	<p>I did not go by San Francisco, to see Ethel -- felt I could not stand the fatigue of the journey.  We have had a very pleasant trip so far, and have met with much kindness from travelling companions.  We have stood the trip very well for us, but Alice had such a severe attack of neuralgia day before yesterday that we were obliged to get off the train at Fort William for her to rest.  We spent a night and a day there  - then came on here.  Do you know Montreal?  It is a lovely old city.  I can't remember if you were ever here.  We shall see Mary Turner and the boys and Harry tomorrow, and will make our first visit there.  Margaret invited us to visit her <pb facs="4433.jpg"/> in June but I do not feel strong enough to go to Florida in Summer.</p>  

<p>Mrs. Cobb invited us to visit her at Montreal in June and July.  I
do not know yet just when we shall go South.  I am sorry not to see big George and little George sooner.  I am <hi rend="underline">so very</hi> tired travelling.  Shall be so glad to get to Mary's and have a rest.</p>

	<p>Ethel will come east with Mary B. in July.  I was <hi rend="underline">very sorry</hi> not to see her, but the extra journey from Vancouver to San Francisco would have been so fatiguing to me.  I do not like the Canadian Pacific Rail Road.  It is extremely rough -- cars do not run smooth.  But the trip on the Monteagle was pleasant.  Neither Alice or I was really seasick though we had a few rough days --  by keeping on deck we escaped seasickness.</p>

	<p>I hope you and the girls will have a pleasant Summer.  Write me at once to Mary Turner's care.  Harry is not going South yet awhile.</p>

<closer><salute>With much love to all,<lb/>
Your devoted Mother,</salute><lb/>
<signed>Mary H. Allen</signed></closer></div></body></text>
</TEI>