<TEI xml:id="yja-1891-12-24.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Tsoong-Kia Tsing to Young John Allen, <date when="1891-12-24">December 24, 1891</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic> Tsoong Kia tsin</sic>
            <reg>Tsoong Kia Tsing</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Tsoong Kia tsing to Young John Allen, <date when="1891-12-24">December 12, 1891</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="thyun">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>T</forename>
                        <forename>H.</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1864">
                        <placeName>
                            <country>Korea</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="tsoong">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Kia</forename>
                        <forename>Tsing</forename>
                        <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>George</forename>
                        <surname>Bell</surname>
                    </persName>
                </person>
                                     </listPerson>
            
            <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    <item>Emory College, Oxford, Ga.</item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2008-03-12">March 12, 2008</date>
            <name xml:id="AH">Alice Hickcox</name> corrected and validated the text.
        </change>
        <change>
            <date when="2008-03-03">March 3, 2008</date>
                <name xml:id="ABV">Ann Vidor, </name>
                transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
<change when="2008-04-04" who="#RSV">
        <name xml:id="RSV">Stewart Varner</name> Added Library of
Congress Subject headings and cleaned up the text.
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body><div type="letter">
								<pb facs="4258.jpg"/>
								<head> [Letter from Tsoong-Kia tsing to Young John Allen, December 24, 1891]</head>
								<opener>
								  <dateline><name type="place">Oxford</name>, <date when="1891-12-24">Dec. 24, 1891</date></dateline>

<salute>Rev. Y. J. Allen D.D.
<lb/>
	My dear Teacher,</salute></opener>

		<p>Since I left San Francisco, I have had a very pleasant 
trip across the Continent and had no trouble at all.  I enjoyed 
the trains so much.  I arrived Atlanta last Saturday and Dr. 
Lewis received me warmly.  I stayed at his home 3 days.  Dr. 
Lewis gave me a suit of clothes.  We both went 
<pb facs="4259.jpg"/>
down to Geo Muse store a bought a suit of clothes.  Last Sunday I dressed 
Chinese dress and went to the Sunday School and Mr. Memphill, who is 
the Supt of the Sunday School, introduced me to the S.S. and 
placed me on the platform and I read few verses in Chinese.  All 
the boys laughed at and their little blue eyes looked at me as 
something was <choice><sic>curios</sic><corr>curious</corr></choice>.  At 11 Bishop Haygood preached us a very  
<pb facs="4260.jpg"/>
nice sermon.</p>

	<p>My railroad ticket costed $57.75 and left me $17.25 for the 
other expenses on the way -- such as lunch basket, wagon hire, 
&#x0026;c.  When I came here I had about ten dollars left.</p>

	<p>I came to Oxford day before yesterday.  Dr. Candler said I 
can board at Marvin Hall.  My room mate is a nice Christian 
youth &#x0026; I shall like him much.  I feel little lonesome today 
<pb facs="4261.jpg"/>

because all the boys have gone home.  Yun has gone to Atlanta.</p>

	<p>I have not seen any professors yet except one.  One of the 
German professors came today and invited me to the Xmas dinner 
tomorrow.  </p>

	<p>All the boys here like me much and are very kind.</p>
	    
	<closer><salute>Will write again when I am somewhat settled.  Meanwhile with kindest regards,

	I am your faithful pupil,</salute><lb/>

								<signed><name type="person" ref="#tsoong">Tsoong Kia tsin </name></signed>
</closer>
 </div>
	</body>
</text>
</TEI>