<TEI xml:id="PAGE_yja_August_1898">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Allen to daughter, <date when="1898-08-24">August 24, 1898</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic>Young John Allen</sic>
                <reg>Young John Allen papers, 1854-1938</reg>
             </choice>
            </name>
               </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Allen to daughter, <date when="1898-08-24">August 24, 1898</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="thyun">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>T.</forename>
                        <forename>H.</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1865">
                        <placeName>
                           <country>Korea</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945
                    </death>
                </person>
           <person xml:id="wac">
            <persName>
              <forename>Warren</forename>
              <forename>Akin</forename>
              <surname>Candler</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1857-08-23">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1941-09-25">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </death>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="tsoong">
            <persName>
              <forename>Kia</forename>
              <forename>Tsing</forename>
              <surname>Tsoong</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName>
              <forename>George</forename>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
            </persName>
          </person>
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2008-03-28">March 28, 2008</date>
                <name xml:id="MP">Michael Page</name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text><body><div type="letter">     
   <pb facs="4382.jpg"/>
<opener><dateline><placename>Animdel Hotel, London</placename>
    <date when="1898-08-24">August 24th, 1898</date></dateline><lb/>
<salute><persName ref=""></persName>My darling daughter,</salute></opener><lb/>
</opener>
            <p>When I wrote Ma'ma last I promised that I would write next to you. So now I avail of this muggy day, no unusual one by the way in London, to fulfill briefly that engagement. You have been very kind to<unclear> noread </unclear>and regularly, but I was sadly dissappoited on my arrival this morning not to find letters from China as some were due when I left the States and orders were left for them to be forwarded direct to London. When I finished Ma'ma's letter we had just arrived at Liverpool. Since then I have visited Glasgow, The Lochs of Scotland, and <choice><orig>Edinboro</orig><reg>Edinburg</reg></choice>
    <pb facs="4383.jpg"/>
and arrived in London all within five days. I spent last Monday- today is Saturday in Liverpool and Chester the latter being in Wales and the oldest city in the British Isles. I have some pictures of its quaint buildings.Tuesday I took the train for Glasgow and reached there about 6 o'clock p.m. and spent the next day Wednesday sightseeing in that city. Have some pictures of that also. Thursday morning left for <choice><orig>Edinboro</orig><reg>Edinburg</reg></choice> via Lochs <unclear>Lomond</unclear>, <unclear>Katherine</unclear><unclear> noread  </unclear>spent Friday in Edinburgh and that night came on here by the mail train 35 or 40 miles per hour. So Pulman's Palace Cars are rather a dear luxury in this country. I had to forgo my accustimed rest and so slept more last night. However I do not feel it now though early this morning I could scarcely hold my eyes open. I have not been able to go out much yet as it has been 
    <pb facs="4384.jpg"/>
                raining ever since I arrived. I forgot to tell you in Ma'ma's letter that Aggie <unclear>noread</unclear> were sending you by me some tatting and ribbons enclosed in a nice little letter which I <unclear>noread</unclear> to hand you with the articles enclosed. I am beginining to feel homesick I want to see you all so band and it is so lonesome travelling alone. The city is full of people but I am alone. It is dreadful to meet so many people everywhere yet not know one of them and in consequence have to play<unclear>noread</unclear>but I do not inted to cut short my travels because of that. I have  entered upon them as a duty and must stick to them till I have completed my tour. When I get home what a nice time we shall have. I shall love you all a deal more and home will be never so cheerful and happy. I am perfectly content to live in Shanghai, only I want you all to be happy and comfortable too. I saw no place in the U.S. that I could prefer to Shanghai and I think Ma'ma's desire to be in the U.S. will be cured by having you with her. Edgar will not need her when he goes to College and I shall be willing to trust him at Oxford. Tell him he must study hard now and be ready soon to go and take his place with others of his age at old Emory. Now my dear daughter do not complain that this is a short letter. I have done the best that I can at present and as it is disposed to quit raining. I will go out and see what London looks like. Many kisses to you and all the dear ones. Kiss Ma'ma for me and <unclear>noread</unclear>your<unclear>noread</unclear>. 
</p>
           <lb/>
            <closer><salute>Yours,</salute> <lb/>
                <signed><unclear><persName ref="#yja">Allen</persName></unclear></signed></closer>        </div></body></text>   
    
</TEI>