<TEI xml:id="yja-1855-09-14.001">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Mary Houston to Young John Allen, <date when="1855-09-14">September 14, 1855</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic>Mary Houston</sic>
            <reg>Allen, Mary Houston</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Mary Houston to Young John Allen, <date when="1855-09-14">September 14, 1855</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="thyun">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>T.</forename>
                        <forename>H.</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1865">
                        <placeName>
                           <country>Korea</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945
                    </death>
                </person>
           <person xml:id="wac">
            <persName>
              <forename>Warren</forename>
              <forename>Akin</forename>
              <surname>Candler</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1857-08-23">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1941-09-25">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </death>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="tsoong">
            <persName>
              <forename>Kia</forename>
              <forename>Tsing</forename>
              <surname>Tsoong</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName>
              <forename>George</forename>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
            </persName>
          </person>-
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2008-03-21">March 21, 2008</date>
                <name xml:id="amg">Anne Graham</name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text><body>
<div xml:id="yja-1855-09-14.002" type="letter">
    <pb facs="4210.jpg"/>
    <head>[Letter from Mary Houston to Young John Allen]</head>
    <dateline><placeName>Grantville Georgia</placeName> <date when="1855-09-14">September 14th 1855</date></dateline><lb />
<persName>Mr. A Y J W Allen</persName>,<lb />
<salute><persName ref="#yja">Dearest Young,</persName></salute><lb />
<p>It were a mockery to conceal the hearts emotions, to keep back its joyous feelings and prevent them from flowing freely when such a profusion of them falls to our share, as were mine after the reception of thy letter last evening; I oftentimes perused it tonight eve.  I seated myself to write and twas then with a consciousness that I could not write a response which would in any wise be worthy of the one just received.  And so Dear Young you are not a castle builder.  You do not sit and dream of the future but think only of the past and present realities.  Would that I too were thus but now that I can tell you so I am going to real studying myself and quit dreaming.  I am going to school in LaGrange at the opening of it which is October 1st and then I shall try to leave off building worthless castles and ‶tracing shadows″ while I will employ my time in thinking of real things.</p>
<pb facs="4211.jpg"/>
 <p>I thought when you left here that I should have visited Siss Mattie in the west <del rend="strikethrough">this</del> <add place="supralinear">in the</add> winter and sure enough would have done so had not Mother consented for me to enter college, which I had much rather do now then visit Mattie after completing my education.  Yes I thought then that I should ere very long have the delightful and inexpressible pleasure of seeing My Dear, Dear Sister whom I have not seen for years.  I thought that I should erelong be in her beautiful land admiring those bright and blooming Prairies, Natures Own beautiful gardens.  Yet I had much rather stay and acquire that which nothing can arrest from me  an education.  I <add place="supralinear">am</add> happy to receive your counsel Dear Young relative to trusting my God and Saviour it does me much good, gives me much confidence, comforts &#x0026; consoles me much, and I would have you to even speak thus with me.  Yes, yes our Saviour is the one to trust in, to confide in, and he will lighten our burdens, having borne far greater ones for our sake he knows how to sympathise with us from experience.</p>
<pb facs="4212.jpg"/>
<p>I do not understand you Young when you ask of me as a favor to take up those lies one by one and give you the substantial truth of the matter  you know that I heard them not, that I heard only what you told me when you were here and you know my replies then.  If you simply mean for me to give you my opinion on Slanderers  I would say tis useless for you have already expressed <del rend="strikethrough">it</del> my sentiments in far better language than I could have done while writing yours.  As you have said so would I say, Oh!  Where can we find words to express the depravity of the heart, its utter baseness its blackness, with which the darkest hour of midnight would be a shining light compared to it, which harbors this viperous fiend, this debasing principle  slander.  Yes in vain might we search our vocabulary and be disappointed still in finding language that would express in proper terms the baseness of this principle, that would describe the polluted heart of him or hear who could thus unfeelingly and without a fear reduce inch by inch an innocent being to the lowest grades of degradation.  
<pb facs="4213.jpg"/>
Strange it is that every one should with eagerness catch each spark generated by the slanderer and fan it each successive time while tis kindled into a great destroying flame consuming in its course all thats bright pure and beautiful belonging to its victim.  Strange that this or her poisonous breath should be receive[d] as a pleasant zephyr by all instead of a cold wintry blast which is withering all the bright hopes of the innocent one tis degrading.  Yes dying their spotless innocence their snowy purity with the darkest hues of ignominy and shame.  But yet its victim may triumph in the end for though thy would gladly degrade it God would receive it  is this not a triumph?  Yes, yes a glorious triumph. </p>  
<p>Hot, scolding bitter tears were mine Dear Young as I perused the 14th page of thy letter and learned that I had been thus meanly misrepresented by my enemies but I cannot permit myself to speak of it now in my present state of mind, tis too excited.  
<pb facs="4214.jpg"/>
How inexpressible the fullness of my heart when I knew that thou wert still my friend amidst it all  I could only exclaim Heaven bless thy pure heart, thy generous soul.</p>
<p>You perhaps had best not send those books as I shall leave soon.</p>
<p>I was very glad to receive so long a letter from you, and ask you to write again soon another such.  Yet I do not feel that I should since I cannot send thee a long one in return, but you must pardon me I do not feel like writing now.
I have no other news to write you now save I tell you that Sisters health is improving some.  Write me very soon Dear Young.</p>
<closer>Believe me thine Forever,<lb />
    <signed><persName>Mary Houston</persName></signed></closer></div>

<back>
<pb facs="4215.jpg"/><dateline><placeName>Grantville GA</placeName><lb />
<date>Sept 14th</date></dateline><lb />
<address><persName>Mr. A Y J W Allen</persName><lb />
<addrLine>Oxford</addrLine><lb />
<addrLine>Georgia</addrLine></address>

<pb facs="4216.jpg"/>
1 <unclear>illegible</unclear>chapel  6 <unclear>illegible</unclear><lb />
2 chapel  Paul <unclear>illegible</unclear></back></body></text>
</TEI>