<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Wiley Hutchins, <date when="1857-10-23"
                        >October 23, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Wiley Hutchins, <date when="1857-10-23"
                        >October 23, 1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and
                    Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Pa">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Wiley</forename>

                            <surname>Hutchins</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Oxford</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region>/><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-06-29">July 6, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff4_024.jpg"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Oxford Geo.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-10-23">Oct. 23d 1857</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Pa,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>As it is perhaps time that I should write home, and as you may be expecting a
                    few lines this evening though there is no news or anything very interesting
                    about here that I can write you. We have 5 weeks more from this evening to
                    attend College this term, and I assure <sic/> I will be glad, glad enough when
                    they expire, and it will not be long, for time flies swiftly with me now
                        sure.</p>
                <p>There has been a great deal of sickness of one kind or other<pb/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff4_025.jpg"/>here since my return, and I have been myself
                    very unwell with severe cold and headache, which I have now, even while I write.
                    I heard from <unclear>Nasworthy?</unclear>, the other day, and he tells me that
                    there has been an unusual amount of sickness down there and a very unusual
                    number of deaths, for he says that he can count up 20 or 30 deaths there at
                        <unclear>Bark</unclear>Camp in about 6 weeks; he informs me also that Kitty,
                    my Negro woman that Adams has hired, is dead. Oh! how uncertain is life, <hi
                        rend="underline">how sure is death</hi>, and surely it comes as the thief,
                    at an uncertain hour of the night, even when we are not expecting it<pb/>and
                    therefore not looking for it. If that be true then, that death is sure to come,
                    and <del rend="strikethrough">comes</del> when it does come is <add
                        place="supralinear">
                        <hi rend="underline">apt to be</hi>
                    </add> perhaps all unlooked for, how does it become <hi rend="underline"
                    >us</hi>, as rational and accountable beings to be prepared for it, whether it
                    come by night or by day, whether it come gradually in slow disease or suddenly
                    and unexpected. Oh! why will man who knows he must surely die, who knows that he
                    has to live forever either in hell amid devils and damned spirits and among men
                    with whom he could not bear to stay or associate with even for a little while
                    here, or live forever in heaven with Christ and dear Sainted Ones he<pb/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff4_026.jpg"/><sic>he</sic>once loved &amp; cherished
                    here; why, oh! why will such a sensible man as that, acknowledging and believing
                    all these things, refuse to make preparation to meet his God, why will he still
                    sit at ease, and seem not to care whether or not he escape hell and the wrath of
                    God, or gain the bliss and rest of heaven forever &amp; ever. Oh! how it
                    makes my very soul quake and tremble within me to see a man just ready as it
                    were to die and yet not prepared to die; and yet there are thousands of them in
                    that situation that are now hastening on to death and destruction forever. Oh!
                    how sad and awful<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff4_027.jpg"/> is such a sight; and
                    why, Oh! why is it so? There is a reason, there is a cause even for this most
                    fatal of all actions- and the same cause even 2500 years ago Isaiah tells us was
                    hurrying its thousands down to hell forever. Here is the cause, here is the
                    reason; Oh! hear what Isaiah says of the people in this day, he declares that
                    "My people doth not consider," he tells us they will not think, they will not
                    reflect, they will not consider. Yes and the same is the cause why so many now
                    do not prepare to go to heaven to live with God, they do not, they will not <hi
                        rend="underline">consider</hi>. Oh! that they would stop and <pb/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff4_028.jpg"/> think before it be finally too late. I do not
                    believe that there is any man who wants to go to hell; I do not believe there is
                    one who is wilfully and blindly <del rend="strikethrough">making</del> expecting
                    to miss heaven. No I cannot believe that man, even the very worst man, could
                    abandon all desire for rest, peace and happiness when he dies. Then why is it
                    that so many live so carelessly, so thoughtlessly; so daringly and
                    presumptuously trample the love and mercy of such a kind and good God <add
                        place="supralinear">as</add> our heavenly Father, under their feet. Oh! is
                    it not because they will not consider, yes, because they <hi rend="underline">do
                        not consider</hi>.</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>Do you not think, do you not believe that there is not a <hi rend="underline"
                        >single</hi>man who has a sound mind, who thinks and acts as an accountable
                    and rational being, who if he will consider what the Lord has done for him and
                    promises to him, but will turn and serve his God and Master if be not already
                    engaged in his service. Now let us look at some of the things which we should
                    consider, and which we believe if any man will rightly consider he will become a
                    good man, a servant of the Lord Our God- a Christian indeed and in thruth.</p>
                <p>1st We hould consider the character and will of our blessed God; He is our Father
                    and bountiful<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff4_029.jpg"/>preserver. We are ever in his
                    hand, ever before his eyes, he everywhere surrounds us. He is great and wise and
                    powerful, and just and holy. And his love and favor are heaven, and his frown
                    and anger are hell. Oh! let us consider that first-- and then we can</p>
                <p>2d Consider what we ourselves are, what our end and destiny are; what the claims
                    of God upon us are; what we <hi rend="underline">should</hi>do in reference to
                    eternity and meeting of our righteous judge.</p>
                <p>3d We should often ask ourselves what our spiritual condition is before God; we
                    should inquire of our own hearts<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff4_030.jpg"/> whether
                    we are accepted of God; whether we love him and have the evidence that he loves
                    us, or whether we are in a state of condemnation and sin, and liable to
                    <sic/>banished from his presence any moment if we should die.</p>
                <p>4th Oh! we should consider how short is life; how important it is, that <hi
                        rend="underline">now</hi>, even in this life is the time "to ensure the
                    great reward", the time to make preparation for eternity and heaven. Oh! let us
                    consider how short,, how uncertain it is and make haste to make peace with our
                    God. Then it will be sweet to live, but better still<pb/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff4_031.jpg"/> to die, because death then will be but the
                    opening of the gates of heaven to our souls and the invitation to come in, and
                    live forever in our Father's kingdom no more to go out.</p>
                <p>5th Having considered the above subjects we should now approach the solemnities
                    of death. We must all surely die; the history of the world is that <hi
                        rend="underline">we die</hi>; Oh! we cannot doubt that; then does it not
                    behoove us to consider seriously its certainty in reference to ourselves? should
                    we not lay it to heart? should we not consider its probable nearness to us, its
                    awful character if we should be unprepared for it, yes should we not<pb/>
                    seriously consider all those things and make haste to prepare against its
                    certain coming.</p>
                <p>But Death is not all, there is something else that remains for us besides to die.
                    Yes we have "to be to judgement brought, and answer in that day" for our lives
                    our acts and all that we have done while God has spared our lives here in this
                    world, but judgement is not <hi rend="underline">all</hi>, we must from
                    judgement depart with the cursed down to hell, or go with the righteous up to
                    heaven, but that is not all yet we have to live in one or the other of those
                    places forever and forever, yes live and burn in hell forever or reign
                        rejoice<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff4_032.jpg"/> in heaven forever.</p>
                <p>Oh, now Dear Pa, does it not seem to you that if a man will sit down and calmly
                    consider these things as they are, that he will get up fully determined in his
                    heart to be a Christian and make ready to leave the world in peace for heaven
                    and immortality with the saints in light. Pardon me that I have written so much
                    on this subject, for I feel much more than I have written and would that I could
                    express to you half the desire and solicitude I have for your salvation; it
                    weighs upon my heart both night and day; I feel I know that I can never
                        repay<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff4_033.jpg"/> you for all the kindnesses and
                    good acts and things you did for me as a parent, as a Father, yes I say I know I
                    cannot in any worldly sense repay you, but because of all those things I do feel
                    doubly, yea a hundred times more desirous to see you secure your salvation and
                    start out for heaven. Oh! how happy it would make my very soul to know that,
                    when I shall be called to leave your and go forth to labor perhaps far from
                    home, that you are <hi rend="underline">almost home</hi>, yes that all of you
                    Mother &amp; Father &amp; the rest were all hastening on to heaven. Oh!
                    that such a happy, joyful news as that<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff4_034.jpg"/> may
                    reach me before I shall have completed my College course and am ready to take my
                    leave of you all perhaps forever till we meet at the judgement seat of Christ.
                    Yes, Oh! that I could know, be assured that you were all determined to meet in
                    heaven an unbroken family band, there are some of the family already there; the
                    Lord has taken them first as it were while young and tender and lovely that he
                    might lead our love and affections up with them to heaven and fasten them there.
                        <add place="supralinear">Yes</add> that thereby he might excite in us
                    permanent desire and <add place="supralinear">a</add> fixed purpose to meet our
                    loved and lost ones there</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>Oh! should we not desire to get to heaven? Yes, yes, I am not ashamed now to say
                    that I want to get there, though I was once ashamed, no blessed be God, I am not
                    ashamed to say that I want to escape hell, that I want to get to a place of
                    rest, to a home of bliss! where there is no more death, no more sorrow no more
                    grief, no more cares, disappointments and pain. Oh! this is a happy, happy
                    thought that <add place="supralinear">we</add> are invited to go to such a
                    place, that we are promised such a home and resting place. May the Lord help us
                    all to make preparation against the final day, that we may be permitted to enter
                    into the joys of our blessed Lord.</p>
                <pb/>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff4_035.jpg"/>
                <p>I have nothing more to write now. You will please write me soon and write me all
                    the news.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Your devoted &amp; affectionate</salute>
                    <signed>Young J Allen</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
