<TEI xml:id="yja-1880-05-01.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to George Gilman Smith, Jr., <date when="1880-05-01">May 1, 1880</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
              <choice>
                <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
              </choice>
            </name>
	</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to George Gilman Smith, Jr., <date when="1880-05-01">May 1, 1880</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="thyun">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>T.</forename>
                        <forename>H.</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                        <surname>Yun</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1865">
                        <placeName>
                           <country>Korea</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945
                    </death>
                </person>
           <person xml:id="wac">
            <persName>
              <forename>Warren</forename>
              <forename>Akin</forename>
              <surname>Candler</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1857-08-23">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1941-09-25">
              <placeName>
                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                <country>United States</country>
              </placeName>
            </death>
          </person>
          <person xml:id="tsoong">
            <persName>
              <forename>Kia</forename>
              <forename>Tsing</forename>
              <surname>Tsoong</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName>
              <forename>George</forename>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
            </persName>
          </person>
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    <item>Smith, George Gilman, 1836-1913.</item>
                    <item>Missionaries -- China.</item>
                    <item>Emory College, Oxford, Ga.</item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2011-06-16">June 8, 2011</date>
                <name xml:id="MJT">Jae Turner </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
  <body>
    <div type="letter" xml:id="yja-1880-05-01.002">
      <pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_010.jpg"/>
      <head>[Letter from Young John Allen to George Gilman Smith, Jr.]</head>
      <lb/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<name type="place">Shanghai China</name>
<date when="1880-05-01">May 1 1880</date></dateline>
<salute>My dear Br. George</salute></opener>
<p>Your letter of Feb. 23rd came to hand on the 20th ult.  Always glad to hear from you.  Indeed your letters are a source of great pleasure, and profit as well.  You are the most literary of all my correspondents and I am glad you give me an occasional insight into your study and its subjects.  You will soon become a <hi rend="underline">bookful</hi> man.  First principles - the groundwork and 
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_011.jpg"/>
basis of all proper study rightly engage your thoughts and I am glad to see that your labors are fundamental in another respect, to wit, that they have respect to the development of the church by <del>s</del>instructing the children, etc.</p>
<p>Well some of these days your little books will bear fruit.  Success is my old friend.  As to your future labors I should say beware of entering into the speculation on Holiness, Sanctification, Perfection <unclear reason="illegible">or</unclear> whatever else it may be called.  God is all things and all for God.  Here is where I <unclear reason="illegible">work</unclear>.  But you must not
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_012.jpg"/>
break yourself down.  I like to read your letters in the <unclear reason="illegible">Advocates</unclear>.  You are an easy fluent writer and withal have a mind to it.</p>
<p>I am sometimes almost overwhelmed -- not with work only -- but with a sense of <hi rend="underline">down castness</hi>.  You cannot appreciate the struggle I have in this country -- almost alone and <hi rend="underline">lonely</hi> in companionship of <hi rend="underline">endeavor</hi>.  I sometimes sigh for the wings of a dove and would flie one away and hide myself from the face of men.  Now is not that bad enough?  It is partly from weariness and exhaustion and partly from being without the
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_012.jpg"/>
shoulder to shoulder influences that make one strong under such tremendous strains.  The small voice within is <unclear reason="illegible">more</unclear> powerful than all circumstances and not to <unclear reason="illegible">do</unclear> still, would be like death to me.  I could not if I would give up, and I will not complain.  How little we know of one another!  Those apparently strongest are to themselves the weakest of the bunch.  Newton's-on-the-strand are we all, if wise.  I am striving to do my whole duty to China and the Church and though I succeed but poorly yet faith is left and that keeps me active.  But enough of this --  Yes Oxford is 
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF14_013.jpg"/>
booming.  Emory College has signalized itself.  Well there's some hope after all for the China Mission.</p>
<p>Stand up fairly and squarely for us my dear brother.  The Methodist Church South can do wonders if properly aroused.  We want to get a fair start here -- organize a Conference and for once get all the machinery of a life church into operation.  My work is prospering -- 20 names on <unclear reason="illegible">probationers</unclear> list.  Other persons almost <unclear reason="illegible">persuaded</unclear> to forsake paganism.</p>
<closer><salute>Remember us still &#x0026; always.  Love to the dear ones -- and believe me ever yours--</salute><signed>Young J. Allen</signed></closer>
    </div>
  </body>
</text>
</TEI>