<TEI xml:id="yja-1856-11-01.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1856-11-01">November 1, 1856</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
              <choice>
                <sic>Young Allen</sic>
                  <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
              </choice>
            </name>
	</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston<date when="1856-11-01"></date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                
           
             <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
		    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-05-05">May 5, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="ST">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

   <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_038.jpg"/>

            <div type="letter">

             <head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, November 1, 1856]</head>

               <note> NB <lb/>
                Pardon this torn sheet at the first <hi rend="underline">it occurred through carelessness</hi></note>
                <opener><dateline><name type="place">E.C. Oxford Ga.</name><date when="1856-11-01">Nov. 1, 1856 </date></dateline><lb/><salute>My Beloved One<lb/></salute></opener>
                <p>I do not deem it necessary, this evening, to vindicate the long silence and delay which I have indulged, by any lengthened apologies or excuses, since I know the <hi rend="underline">one</hi> who has so long exercised her generous heart and forgiving spirit towards me in all such cases of non-punctuality and seeming negligence, besides in many other errors and ways, will in this case also, not only look upon what has been done, what really is the case now, <add place="supralinear">my having delayed,</add> but will also regard the causes which have combined and conspired to produce such results.  1st My "indisposition"; having been 

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_039.jpg"/>

                tormented with a severe cold, cough and headache, either of which is bad enough, but when all are leagued and besieging at once such a poor weak frame and brain as mine you know it is far from pleasant, very incapacitating for any duty and distracting as to any concern; and want of a <hi rend="underline">suitable</hi> time is the 2d and last reason why I've delayed&#x2014; and I emphasize <hi rend="underline">suitable</hi> because it is not <hi rend="underline">at any time </hi> and under <hi rend="underline">any </hi>circumstances that I fan write a letter to <hi rend="underline">you</hi>&#x2014; My Dearest <hi rend="underline">"Mary."</hi>  This then will briefly account for all the anxiety and suspense which, I surely have caused you, for I know you expected a quick response from me, since

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_040.jpg"/>

                you know, <hi rend="underline">to be punctual,</hi> is my motto in all things, the principle, the life-habit whose influence is to modify and control my actions, and which I trust is even now almost indispensable.  But if thy spirits are depressed, or like some injured dove you sigh and droop alone, because thy "<hi rend="underline">spirit mate</hi>" is far away and no cheerful tidings from his retreat greet thine ears. Oh! revive now and let <hi rend="underline">this</hi> prove the balm for injured innocence, the sweet restoration of that cheerful smile, and happy spirit <hi rend="underline">again.</hi></p>
                <p>I do not design, as you said, to write much this evening, and Oh!  My Dear, do pardon me for such disconnections and such aberrations of mind and sentiments <add place="supralinear">as are</add> in this.

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_041.jpg"/>

                    <add place="supralinear">But</add> since "brevity" has proven itself so beautifully the "soul" and "consciseness" the strength and beauty of <hi rend="underline">your </hi>letter, I desire to follow your example <hi rend="underline">now</hi>and emulate the virtues of your happy and perspicuous style; therefore I shall be<hi rend="underline">very</hi> and<hi rend="underline">very</hi> brief, for I have no news to write, no revelations to make, no discoveries, no adventures, no wonderful exploits, no party excursions, no&#x2014;&#x2014; Shah; what is it that I do have that I can relate&#x2014;ah! woful echo answers, what!&#x2014; What, shall I write then Dearest Mollie?  Were I to retrospect the past, it would all be sadness to 

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_041.jpg"/>

                thee, we would have to gaze upon a <hi rend="underline">dark back ground</hi> indeed&#x2014;its scenes are all embittered to thee, the cheerful smile once so eloquently playing upon the cheek and <add place="supralinear">in the </add>sparkling eyes of Loved ones has ceased to cheer thee; that bright, sunny garden whose verdure and violets once bloomed in fragrance and sweetness, has been rudely invaded and its flowers been stolen from us, leaving, <del rend="strikethrough"><unclear>only</unclear> what th</del> upon our minds <add rend="supralinear">only </add>more strongly confirmed the sweet sentiments of the Poet, "You may crush the vase if you <add rend="supralinear">will </add> The scent of the rose will linger round it still", That forest and grove in which so <unclear>???</unclear> we have retreated, when all around us was sunshine and 

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_042.jpg"/>

                song, bird and flower has almost ceased to invite our rambling footsteps thither, and soon- perhaps, (don't be sad Dearest) now we'll have to leave it, to see it, nor enter it any more forever.  Are not then these retrospections sad ones to thee, My Mollie Dearest.  But if we contemplate the present, how is it then?&#x2014; Oh! <hi rend="underline">I</hi> cannot tell.  If we turn to the future and <hi rend="underline"> calculate</hi>; what shall meet us then?  Shall we see hope and fear in doubtful conflict poised, shall we see misgivings, forebodings of ill throng in our pathway, shall clouds obscure and foes enlist and wrath

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_043.jpg"/>

               thus "help each other on each other's crosses bear."  I have not time, Dear One, to say much on it, but I know you agree with me and I know you are willing, yea even desirous to do all you can for our Blessed Savior and his Cause and will make almost any Sacrifice in order to glorify "Our Father which art in Heaven."  Then, Dear one, as the Lord has so mercifully heard and answered your prayers in the conversion of your Dear Sisters, and thus given you assurance that he loves you and will still hear you if faithful and fervent in your supplications

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_044.jpg"/>

                    asking what you need&#x2014;and then converting them too (he has now) given you great encouragement to pray and great strength and help through them to help you on to Heaven.  Since he has done all these things Dear One, and ma<add place="supralinear">n</add>y others "whereof you are glad," are you not (now) willing to set up and consecrate an altar of prayer (aided by your Sisters) <hi rend="underline">among</hi> them, and there morning and evening, and evening in particular, pay your vows and consecrate your life, time, talents, soul and body all, all to God.  Yes Dear One I know you are.  And Mollie 

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_044.jpg"/>

pardon me if I do wrong in thus suggesting such a thing to you&#x2014;but let me suggest that it would be of more than infinite worth to you, both individually and to your Sisters who compose the family thus to take up your cross as a meek, and humble follower of our Lord and lead the way to usefulness and <add place="supralinear">to </add>God by a pious, devoted and influential example in the social circle at home&#x2014;around the Sacred hearth stone of the holy and consecrated spot hallowed by so many tearful recollections and memories of past days when the <hi rend="underline">circle </hi>was indeed complete

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_045.jpg"/>

                    and our joys  were full.  Take up the cross then Dear One, and follow Jesus "through <hi rend="underline">evil </hi>as well as good repast" fearing no danger nor harm&#x2014; for when God is on our side who can prevail against us.  Say as the Psalmist "As for me and <hi rend="underline">my </hi>house <hi rend="underline">we </hi>will serve the Lord," let others say what they may, let them "Stretch their arms like seas And grasp in all the <unclear>shore</unclear>"
                </p>
                <p>But as for you Dear One, Say "Lord grant me the visits of thy face&#x2014;<lb/>And I desire no more" and thus determined, <del rend="strikethrough">and</del> <add place="supralinear">let </add>your purpose be settled and fixed and your Soul

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_046.jpg"/>

 engage to drive us from our purpose- shall "some unknown dread, some indescribable apprehension" drive us back and force us to retreat, or shall <add place="supralinear">we </add>see <del rend="strikethrough"><unclear>abov</unclear></del> hope, the sheet anchor of the soul, fast anchored by the throne of God, our pathway radiant with smiles and the presence of <hi rend="underline">Immanuel,</hi> our sky bight with the meridian glories of the Sun of righteousness? if so&#x2014; we shall&#x2014; then, let foes, and hell their denunciations and wrath disgorge&#x2014; we shall fear no evil&#x2014; for we have a refuge near, a secure hiding place from every ill.  May <hi rend="underline">God </hi>grant that, <hi rend="underline">so </hi>it may be, to our poor trembling Souls</p>

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_047.jpg"/>

                   <p> My Dear Mollie, I thank God that I yet can praise <hi rend="underline">Him</hi> "who is the health of my countenance my exceeding great reward." I love to feel just as I feel now while penning these lines to thee; my bless God, He is always dear to my poor soul in comforts in peace and consolations. I <hi rend="underline">do</hi> want to be entirely His. And praise the Lord, that such desires such inclinations do live in my bosom.
                </p>
                <p>My Dearest, God loves to bless us when we pray, and I tell you He often comforts my heart and ministers to me in secret prayer&#x2014; 'tis then I love to pray for the <hi rend="underline">one,</hi> that lives

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_047.jpg"/>

 in my heart, that has given my poor soul so much encouragement, and who to day I know <del rend="strikethrough"><unclear>p</unclear></del><hi rend="underline">is on her way to heaven with me</hi>, and whose soul daily ascends for me in prayer. Bless, God oh!  My Soul for such a friend.  Yes eternal praises be to His name forever, that He has given me such a sweet Comforter, such a sweet companion here.</p>
                <p>My Dearest "Mary" I have many many things which I would like to write you but I cannot now, for I must conclude.</p>
                <p>Your Paper I have ordered to be changed, and perhaps you have received it for this week.</p>

                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_048.jpg"/>

                <p>You may prepare, Mollie, to visit the Conference with me this winter as I shall expect you to go with me&#x2014; please go, now Dearest, do not disappoint me. I promise that it shall prove a happy as well as interesting time with us.</p><p>Please now, <hi rend="underline">do</hi> forgive the imperfections of this harem scarem letter and write me back immediately, on the very day you get this, if possible for I will be <hi rend="underline">over</hi> anxious to hear from <hi rend="underline">you</hi>.  Give my love to Mellie and Bexa</p> <closer><salute>and still believe me thine only and thine faithfully</salute><signed><name rend="underline">Young Allen</name></signed></closer><lb/><postscript><p>Give me all the news with <hi rend="underline">you</hi> both temporal and spirtiual, please</p></postscript>
            </div>
	  </body>
	  <back>
	    <div type="envelope">

	      <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_036.jpg"/>
		<note place="inline">Nov. 1 '56</note>

		  <p>
		    <address><persName>Miss Mollie Houston</persName>
		    <lb/>
		    <addrLine>Grantville</addrLine>
		    <lb/>
		    <addrLine>Georgia</addrLine>
		    </address>
		  </p>
	      <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_037.jpg"/>
	    </div>
	  </back>
	</text>
      </TEI>