<TEI xml:id="yja-1856-08-02.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1856-08-02">August 2nd 1856</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
              <choice>
                <sic>Young John Allen</sic>
                  <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
              </choice>
            </name>
	</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston<date when="1856-08-02">August 2 1856</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                   <person xml:id="mh">
		     <persName>
		   <forename>Mollie</forename>
		   <surname>Houston</surname>
		   </persName>
		   </person>
                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  <!-- or 1900-1999 -->
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    <item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-04-01">April 1, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="ST">Sue Trowbridge</name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
    <body>
    <div type="letter">
<pb facs="Allen-11-FF1-003.jpg"/>
        <opener>
            <dateline>Grantville, <date when="1856-08-02">Saturday evening, August 2nd 1856</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>My Dearest One,</salute>
        </opener>
        
        <p>I need offer no apology for what I am now performing, for I am sure more will be required suffice this there as it is.  I am once more 
            in town and have a slight opportunity of sending you a short communication which I will in <hi rend="underline">this</hi> briefly do.  
            I want to <hi rend="underline">see you</hi> very bad, I want to <hi rend="underline">be with</hi> you, but fearing lest I should
            act <add place="supralinear">by going</add> imprudently, I will send you this note requesting that you send me as soon as is convenient a reply.</p> 
        
        <p>Dearest Mollie, I have been all the week engaged in our meeting at prospect which is still gloriously progressing, I have been endeavouring to 
            prove faithful to my promise and my soul to my Savior and work for his cause, I have been conducting a prayer meeting held by the young <add place="supralinear">men</add> 
            in the grove of an evening before preaching for 3 evenings now, and on last night we had a gracious visitation in our midst out there I was 
            exceedingly happy Dear One, and was  enabled to renew my strengths and my efforts struggling with penitents and <unclear></unclear> at the altar. Oh! It was a 
            glorious time to my soul last night.</p>

<pb facs="Allen-11-ff1-004.jpg"/>
        
        <p>Oh I am exceedingly anxious to see you that I may talk with and tell you of my hopes and my prospects.  My heart has often been enabled 
            to go up to God in prayer for you Dear Beloved one since I saw you, that he may be your comfort and exceeding great reward in all your 
            affliction and sorrow.  I never did in all my life feel so entirely cut loose from the world as I do now.  God Bless you now my <hi rend="underline">Only One</hi>, 
            and may he establish you at all times and everywhere and make you a whole-hearted-devoted, useful active working Christian is the sincere 
            daily prayer from your Faithful and devoted forever unchanging Y.A.</p>
        
        <postscript><p>I will come at whatever time you may see fit to appoint be sure and tell me Mollie if it be in your power you know that although I want to be
            with you so anxiously yet I would not in my over anxiousness act improperly or unwisely nor unadvisedly, so Mollie now you must advise me. 
            I have written this in great haste for I have to leave now to get back to our prayer meeting to night.  God Bless and keep you forever.  Farewell
            for a few days</p></postscript>
    </div>
    </body>
    <back>
        <div type="envelope">
            <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_005.jpg"/>
           <dateline>
               <placeName>Grantville GA</placeName>
           <date when="1856-08-02">Aug 2 '56</date>
           </dateline>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                <address><persName>Miss Mollie Houston</persName>
                <lb/>
                <addrLine>Grantville</addrLine>
                <lb/>
                <addrLine>Georgia</addrLine>
                </address>
            </p>
        </div>
        </back>
  </text>
</TEI>