<TEI xml:id="yja-1856-08-21.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1856-08-21">August 21, 1856</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
              <choice>
                <sic>Young</sic>
                  <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
              </choice>
            </name>
	</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1856-08-21">August 21, 1856</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                    </person>
                
    <person><persName><forename>Mollie</forename><surname>Houston</surname></persName></person>                     </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date>  
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    <item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-03-23">March 23, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="sat">Sue Trowbridge</name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_007.jpg"/>
<opener><dateline><placeName>E. C. Oxford, Geo.,</placeName> Aug. 21st 1856</dateline></opener>
                    

<salute>My dearest Mollie,</salute>

<p>After another happy meeting, and sweet-month of communion, and an other painful, yet resigned and dutiful separation, I find myself seated
at this window of my study to perform again that most pleasureful task, and delightful duty, of corresponding with thee.  I will not enter into 
the preliminaries common on such occasions as this, <hi rend="underline">the first</hi> communication, as I do not intend a yet to write you a regular letter, but only
to acquaint you that I had a pleasant trip and most cordial greetng on my arrival, and and was most pleasantly located at my former place. 
    <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_008.jpg"/>
    I need
not detail all the incidents and feelings that transpired and excited me during the <hi rend="underline">run</hi> from Grantville to Oxford, for I deem it all unnecessary 
and will pass them all over in silence therefore.</p>

<p>I found on arriving that I did not surprise any of them at least of <hi rend="underline">my <add place="supralinear">our</add> family</hi> as they had been expecting me ever since Friday night.  The
    Old Lady (Mrs. Talley) and the girls told me they were about going down to the depot <hi rend="underline">a foot</hi>, about a mile, to meet me and <hi rend="underline">gallant</hi> 
me home, but feared lest I should not come and they would be alone at the depot rather <hi rend="underline">too</hi> late at night by themselves and give it out.  But I assure you
    <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_008.jpg"/>
Mollie they greeted me with many smiles, kind words, and assurances that they were glad to see me; and before I entered the door all
anxiously enquired <hi rend="underline">where I saw Mollie and how she was</hi> <unclear>etc</unclear> all of which I gladly responded to.  Be assured My Dear that I am happily situated
now, I feel very cheerful hopeful and encouraged, and knowing, feeling that I have thy love to cheer, thy chaste and constant heart of virtue to
repose confiding trust and hope in, and thy fervent prayers in my behalf to <unclear>string</unclear> there and sustain me, how otherwise than be cheerful and hopeful could 
I be, be happy and cheerful there too my 
    <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_009.jpg"/>
dear, fervent, dilligent and punctual in the discharge of all your duties particularly your private and 
Christian devotions, and though we meet not for a few months, let's join our prayer and supplications jointly and unitedly morning and evening
at a throne of grace, in behalf of each other and <hi rend="underline">our very dear friends</hi> whom we so much desire to see partaking with us of the divine 
character and blessings that are ever ready to be bestowed upon the meek and lowly and faithful Christian.</p>  <p>My soul swells with rapturous joy 
at times when I contemplate the Christian's hopes, his prospects and his exceeding precious reward.  May we ever live in God's presence.</p>
                
                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_010.jpg"/>

<p>Now back again Mollie to the news after a little deviation which (deviation) I will leave for you to trace on further for yourself as I have not
    the time.</p><p>Not many old students have returned as yet, but a quantity <hi rend="underline">of new ones</hi>. 29 new ones were admitted yesterday and most of them for <hi rend="underline">our</hi> 
class which will swell it to about <hi rend="underline">60</hi> there are several new ones that have arrived since and still they come.  There are 6 returned <hi rend="underline">here</hi> and 6 more 
    are expected, then we will have 10 boarders all fine gentlemen.</p>

<p>Miss Lizzie Tally left us this morning to spend awhile  
    <pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_011.jpg"/>
    in Green. I sent <hi rend="underline">our</hi> love jointly to the Madison Ladies with whom I enjoyed myself so
    much at <unclear><hi rend="underline">C---?</hi></unclear></p>

                <p>I have an idea of going over to Covington on tomorrow to call on <hi rend="underline">my old <unclear>bride?</unclear></hi> Miss <hi rend="underline">Emma Oliphant</hi>, our <hi rend="underline">old</hi> boarder (<hi rend="underline">she has left us</hi>).</p>

<p>Now Dear, I believe I have told you the most that has happened or that's in any way entertaining to you and I must close.  I heard from <hi rend="underline">your 
    dearest Tish</hi> yesterday, as Mr. Arnold, a student, got on the train with us there, <hi rend="underline">just right</hi> from Charlie Arnold's where she now is, may God bless 
you both, and keep you both and 
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_011.jpg"/>
    save you both in the Heaven of his love forever.</p>

<p>Give my love Dearest Mollie to your Dear sisters, Mellie <unclear>Becar</unclear>, Mintie, Sweetie and Sallie, and accept the fulness of a devoted heart as thine 
own constantly and purely forever.</p>
<closer>
<signed><name>Young Allen</name></signed>

<address><name><hi rend="underline">Miss</hi>Mollie Houston</name>
<placeName>Grantville
    Georgia</placeName></address>
</closer>
<postscript><p>Mr. Peabody of Columbus, of my class who left here sick on the night of the 5th of July, is dead.</p>

                <p>Are you acquainted with a Mr. Honeycut of Coweta, now a student here?</p>
<p>"Thine own"</p>
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF1_012.jpg"/>
<p>Mollie Dearest please answer this as soon as you can and I will try and write you a letter after a while, and talk <hi rend="underline">lots</hi> with you.</p>
    <p>Good bye</p>

      <p><name>Young</name></p></postscript>
            </div>
         </body>   
    </text>
</TEI>
