<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/Beck%20Projects/yjallen-svn/xml/yja-tei4.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="yja-1858-00-00.001">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter to Mary (Mollie), future wife of Young John Allen <date when="1858">1858</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                    
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent></extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                        Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                        contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA 30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><date> </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person>
                        <persName>
                            
                        </persName>
                        
                    </person>
                    
                    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
                
                <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement></settlement>
                            <region></region>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                    of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                    Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                    images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                    captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                    an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                    have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                    the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                    For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                    Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                    http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                    dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                    in the original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date> 
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                        <item>Missionaries -- China.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2010-07-07">July 21, 2010</date>
                <name xml:id="sat">LeEllen Hannan </name>
                transcribed and encoded the text.
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF5_023.jpg"/>
                
                <p>That ringlet of thy hair I still preserve in sweet remembrance.</p>
                <p>It's raining in torrents; I am alone: my <sic>my</sic> mind and whole heart is with thee.  A little <unclear>grillums</unclear> on the hearth is the only companion I have of this late hour, to cheer the solitude of my little abode; Nay I am not alone, they presence haunts me; thy type dispels the gloom of solitude, and transports me to other days when I was so happy by thy side and in thy presence.   Tell me Mollie what they have asked you about us being engaged and what they have said about us, be sure in your next, I know they have said Something some of them. What is it ? Mollie.</p>
                <p> I will ever remember thee Dear Mollie.  There are 5 <sic>us</sic> boarding here, and at <hi rend="underline">"9"</hi> oclock we all meet in one of our rooms and hold <hi rend="underline"> "prayers"</hi>. I think Dear it is a great blessing, r that is, many blessings are attendant on it.  I will never cease to remember thee at that hour now in private.   and Oh!  may's then soon obtain the blessing of Religion, the pardon of all thy sins, and may'st then be a 'burning &#x0026; shining sight' and may <sic>may</sic> be brought home to God by thy example and influences.  Read the Bible much Mollie Dear, and Meditate on it, and you'll be strenghtened every time.  Remember me, and may we together<pb facs="Allen_11_FF5_024.jpg"/>
                    in sweet counsel gladly wander up and down in this world of sorrows and finally we enter through our Lord the portals of the New Jerusalem to the ever lasting eace and rest of God's dear children, let us Dearest, take counsel with each other concerning our spiritual welfare and etenal destiny; I have none other in whom I have a greater interest; should we live to go forth together Dear Mollie, I do not know where our lot my be cast in this world but let us rest our hopes upon some sure peace of rest and reward in the world above, yes Mollie, let us ever strive to live for God and the advancement of his cause, and let our faces and progress ever be <unclear>Zimward</unclear>and let our conversation be  not of a common place character, but ever the pure and ennobling not stooping to worthless things, to force a smile or to entertain our <unclear>gr'daz</unclear> friends who <unclear>sport</unclear> at the profession we have made, no Mollie, let us guard well one thoughts for they also heard in heaven; Read the 5th &amp;6th chapters of Ephesians for instruction on this.  Yes dearest Mollie, let us never give sanction in any manner to a sinful act of any kind to our friends, but let us discuontenance it, and live above such - for verily it will not be without its reward.  Go on then Mollie, persevering in the path of duty regardless of the censure and scoff of thy worldly friends, I once was like the and decided the Christian follower.  But thanks God, Dear Mary, I can say I have been awakened, and know there is reality in it, then heed them.  Dearest is the counsel of thy truest Dearest Friend.</p>
                
                    <signed><persName>Y. J. Allen</persName></signed>
                       

                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
