<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/Beck%20Projects/yjallen-svn/xml/yja-tei4.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="yja-1858-00-00.002">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston <date when="1858">1858</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>A. Y. J. W. Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                    
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent></extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                        Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                        contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA 30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><date> </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person>
                        <persName>
                            
                        </persName>
                        
                    </person>
                    
                    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
                
                <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement></settlement>
                            <region></region>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                    of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                    Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                    images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                    captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                    an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                    have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                    the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                    For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                    Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                    http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                    dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                    in the original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date> 
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                        <item>Missionaries -- China.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2010-07-07">July 21, 2010</date>
                <name xml:id="sat">LeEllen Hannan </name>
                transcribed and encoded the text.
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF5_022.jpg"/>
		<head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston]</head>
		<lb/>
                <opener>
                    <salute> Mary Dear;</salute>
                </opener>
                <p> I have nothing more to write thee now save I tell thee my health is still increasing which is te most glorious news to <hi rend="underline">"me"</hi>.  You will be surprised when you see me again; I was but a skeletor while I was at home, I've recovered so fast since I've been here some of the boys say I'm <hi rend="underline">"bloated"</hi>, but they mistake it is but nature assuming her throne, and health blooming again on my cheeks.  Expect not to see too <unclear>peat</unclear>a change lest you be disappointed, there is more change of feeling than appearance.</p>
                <p>Mollie You may choose the next subject of Discussion, - we'll not, if you say so, say anything more on the other.  Write very soon in answer to this, Give my Love to Miss <unclear>Stow</unclear>again, if she'll accept it; Give the General news there Mollie, tell em al aout the girls; Who's going to see Miss Virginia now and who Miss <unclear>Kansas</unclear>the other.  tell me all aout them it will be very interesting to me, and I know you.  I must now close.  Then farewell, Mollie, the dearest friend I ever knew; Remember me, Mollie. </p>

                <p>Be sure and write soon.  Forever thine - <unclear>ad etererrasso</unclear>.   Some of my Friends are going out home with me at vacations perhaps, to see you, they have seen you <del rend="strikethrough">Ty</del>fro, but rather see the <unclear>"rejende</unclear>, they are taking in Mollie.</p>
                
                
                <closer><salute>Your truest Best Friend I love</salute>
                    <signed><persName>Allen</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Y. J. Allen</persName></signed>
                    <name type="place">Emory College Geo.</name></closer>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>