<TEI xml:id="yja-1858-06-12.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Mellie Houston and Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1858-06-12">June 12, 1858</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                    
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent></extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                        Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                        contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA 30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><date> </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person>
                        <persName>
                            
                        </persName>
                        
                    </person>
                    
                    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
                
                <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement></settlement>
                            <region></region>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                    of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                    Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                    images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                    captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                    an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                    have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                    the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                    For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                    Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                    http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                    dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                    in the original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date> 
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                        <item>Missionaries -- China.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2010-07-07">July 14, 2010</date>
                <name xml:id="sat">LeEllen Hannan </name>
                transcribed and encoded the text.
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
<head>[Letter from Mellie Houston and Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, June 12, 1858]</head>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_FF5_013.jpg"/><lb/>
                <opener><dateline><name type="place">Grantville Geo</name><date when="1858-06-12">June 12th 1858</date></dateline>
                    <salute>My Darling Sister; <lb/>
                    My Precious Dear Mollie;</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>As soon as Mellie received your Sweet letter this morning she came (immediately) to see me and brought it.  She has just left with the request that I should write you immediately <hi rend="underline">"for her" </hi> as she did not have time owing to circumstances.</p>
                <p>So My Dear One, I am writing now in a double capacity, foryou know I could <add place="supralinear">not</add>write <hi rend="underline">"to you" </hi>for another and not some for myself.</p>
                <p>And in the first place then let us both, for Mellie desires it, return you our many gracious feelings of gratitude and pleasure and <hi rend="underline">"happiness for we are truly happy"</hi>- that you have so kindly <pb facs="Allen_11_FF5_014.jpg"/> (decided and) consented to have our <del rend="strikethrough">engagement</del> <add place="supralinear">marriage</add>consummated before coming home - for this may the <hi rend="underline">"Lord Bless You - My own Mollie Dearest"</hi>. I am not careful  <add place="supralinear">or solicitious</add>as <hi rend="underline">"to the place,"</hi> the most that I desired was that <hi rend="underline">"it"</hi> be done.  Yes My Dearest, <hi rend="underline">"we can agree - we will agree, we never shall disagree."</hi> Shall we <hi rend="underline">"My Mollie"</hi>?</p>
                <p>My Dearest, <hi rend="underline">"we were not mad"</hi>.  how could we be.  You had not given any offers - Oh! <hi rend="underline">"no. no. no.  we were not, could not be offended"</hi> by our <hi rend="underline">"precious absent one"</hi> - don't let it trouble you then, Dearest, any more. You are <hi rend="underline">"dearer to me every day - every hour."</hi> Yes <hi rend="underline">"every time I think of you"</hi> and that is <hi rend="underline">"very, very often"</hi>, now that I am at home.  I <hi rend="underline">"know"</hi>I spend the <hi rend="underline">"most"</hi>of my <hi rend="underline">"time with you"</hi>by far.  I can't help it; You and subjects intimately connected with you and our future destiny are all that engage <hi rend="underline">"my mind, my Soul"</hi>,my affections and thoughts now, except it be only for a very short time.<del rend="strikethrough">at</del></p>
                <p>My Dearest, I know not what to write you, or how to write you - I feel just <add place="supralinear">like</add>I could pour out my whole soul to you - not <unclear>by</unclear> this way - but were I sitting with you, as <add place="supralinear">in</add>other days we sat together in <hi rend="underline">"sweet-sweet"</hi> communion in this <hi rend="underline">"old Piazza"</hi>- Dear Mollie, as you remember them!  But bless the Lord My Dearest - I anticipate, the next time we sit together here, a far sweeter, holier mingling of Soul and communion of Spirit than ever characterized our past intercourse.  Yes.  Yes - Mollie, <hi rend="underline">"do please pardon me"</hi> for visiting you in this style, and indulging your name and its <hi rend="underline">"dear Synonyms"</hi> so often - they are the overflowings of a once <hi rend="underline">"full-full"</hi> <pb facs="Allen_11_FF5_015.jpg"/>of pure and precious love for thee and <hi rend="underline">"only"</hi>thee - and therefore are intended for My Mollie's eyes alone.  Dearest, <hi rend="underline">"I love you so"</hi> that I told Mellie this morning, that I knew <hi rend="underline">"any place would be pleasant and we be happy there"</hi>, "at <hi rend="underline">"home"</hi>or <hi rend="underline">"abroad, on the land"</hi>or <hi rend="underline">"on the sea""</hi>.  Yes, Yes <hi rend="underline">"anywhere, especially"</hi>, of <hi rend="underline">"Jesus"</hi>dwell with us there, and I know he will, for he promised to be with us and <hi rend="underline">""he is faithful that promised, who also will as it." Glory be to his"</hi>name for that.  do you think, yes, <hi rend="underline">"I know"</hi>you do, - that you <hi rend="underline">"love me"</hi>better and better every day too, My own Mollie and that you are still willing to share the hardest fate of your own devoted Young, should it come!</p>
                <p>Then God bless <add place="supralinear">you</add> abundantly, more and more with grace and strength for the sacrifice.  My own soul <hi rend="underline">"blesses you all the time"</hi>.  Oh!  we shall be very, very <hi rend="underline">"happy together"</hi> will we not Dearest One!</p><pb facs="Allen_11_FF5_016.jpg"/>
                <p>As to what remarks would be made, I merely meant, Mollie, that if we come home and remained as we are now, that many would take advantage or rather seek advantage or opportunity to <hi rend="underline">"make remarks"</hi>, for that as you know had long been their character and that they loved to talk especially about you &#x0026;c - there have not been any made as yet - <del rend="strikethrough">only</del> <add place="supralinear">except</add>a few in regard our <unclear>consummation</unclear> - they seemed to think that we would <hi rend="underline">"never marry"</hi>, that it would all prove a magnificent four years of failure.   Many have prophesied that we would never wed - but My Dearest, such a thought nevr burdened my mind for an <hi rend="underline">"instant"</hi>, and I am truly <hi rend="underline">"glad"</hi>, yes I do <hi rend="underline">"sincerely rejoice"</hi>that the time is so near when all those <hi rend="underline">"ban"</hi>, unfounded, uninspired <sic>propesies</sic> shall fail and <pb facs="Allen_11_FF5_017.jpg"/>we be <hi rend="underline">"happily associated together for life"</hi>.</p>
                <p>I believe I have taken up nearly all the letter for myself - nevertheless, <unclear>Miss</unclear> Mellie joins me in reference to the greater part of it, as I have heard her express similar feelings &#x0026;c to you.</p>    
                <p>She is quite well and so are all y(our)<hi rend="underline">"little sister"</hi>; Dearest, I do love <hi rend="underline">"them so much"</hi>, whether because I love you so or not, I can't tell, but they are very dear to me. </p>
                <p>I shall<add place="supralinear">come</add> down to Macon, I reckon, on the day before your commencement and be there only that day.  I don't want to be there long after I get with you - <unclear>you</unclear> had better begin in time to pack up and prepare for leaving for you will find it quite inconvenient to do so if you wait til near the end in getting ready Dearest, let me suggest now in time, that you had better pack up all your things,  <hi rend="underline">"especially your books"</hi>, and have them ready to send on home before the last days.  Select what articles you wish to carry with you to Oxford, and carry but one trunk with you there, and we'll send the others from Atlanta down home; I think that will be the best arrangement for our convenience and pleasure &#x0026;c.  </p>
                <p>Now My own Mollie - I will close by requesting you to tell me, in answer to this,<del rend="strikethrough">to Mellie,</del>how must I do when I come down. Shall I call for you and see you Tuesday evening if I get there in time or at any other time atall, before you are through, and all's done, or what shall I do - <hi rend="underline">"just have it your own way"</hi>- I will do as you say. <hi rend="underline">"My Darling One"</hi>, My precious Mollie, <hi rend="underline">"Oh! that I could embrace you and say it"</hi>  -   </p>
                  
           
                <closer><salute>believe <hi rend="underline">"us"</hi>ever </salute><lb/>
                    <signed><persName>Your Loving Sister Mellie <unclear>Simms</unclear> and devoted One forever Young J Allen</persName></signed></closer>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>