<TEI xml:id="yja-22-march-1857.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to his foster parents, <date when="1857-03-22"
                        >March 22, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen </sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to his foster parents, <date when="1857-03-22"
                        >March 22, 1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and
                    Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <person>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Nancy</forename>
                            <surname>Hutchins</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person><person>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Wiley</forename>
                            <surname>Hutchins</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person></listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement/>
                            <region/>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
			<item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-04-07">April 7, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="ypw">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_032.jpg"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Oxford Geo.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-03-22">March 22/57</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Father &amp; Mother;</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>On the above date I commenced to write this letter but thinking I
                    <sic>a</sic>might be gone to Tenn. and from some other considerations I
                    postponed it until now.</p>
                <p>The object of this letter is to speak of a subject which has long borne heavily
                    on my mind, and which I have often thought I ought to communicate; but to do it,
                    I have always been wanting in courgae or have been "halting between two
                    opinions." This morning, cool and dispassionate as I ever was in my life, I am
                    fully persuaded, as I have long been, that my heavenly master has called me to
                    proclaim his gospel to a dying world. I have not until within a few weeks past,
                        got<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_033.jpg"/>my consent to obey this summon and
                    even now I am sometimes <sic>vacilating</sic>. But this morning, confidently relying upon
                    the promise of our Savior, when he said "lo, I am with you always even into the
                    end of the world."</p>
                <p>I feel like obeying his call. I cannot enjoy religion unless I give my consent to
                    perform this responsible work. I feel my own inadequacy and unfitness for the
                    great work that lies before me. Our heavenly Father, by the influences of his
                    holy Spirit can make the feeble strong. This is my only hope. Otherwise I could
                    not engae in so important a work. I have chosen today to write because I am calm
                    and dispassionate. My thoughts flow from the dictates of judgement and not from
                    the impulses of excitement.</p>
                <p>However much I may some-<pb/>times be led off the almost irresistible influences
                    of another description, my impressions have become of the nature of fixed
                    principles. They are, however, sometimes powerfully attacked by the filthy lure
                    of this world's pleasures and distinctions.</p>
                <p>I hope however in the end to be enabled to overcome every temptation which the
                    great enemy of God and man is constantly throwing in my pathway.</p>
                <p>I hope firmly to withstand every inducement which this world's gawdy allurements
                    can present or its fretful ambition offer. It is true this requires no ordinary
                    supply of grace. My heavenly father is richly able and abundantly willing to
                    grant the supply. If I but trust to him I shall be able to come off conqueror in
                    the end. </p>
            </div>
	</body>
                <back>
                 <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_034.jpg"/>
		 <div>
                    <list>
                        <item>Take heed lest there be in any of you an evil heart of
                            unbelief--Martin</item>
                        <item>Blessed are they which do hunger &amp; thirst &amp;c <hi
                                rend="underline">Lovejoy</hi></item>
                        <item>4th Esther--Martin</item>
                        <item>1st ch. Proverbs--Patillo</item>
                        <item>I know in whom I have believed &amp;c Lovejoy</item>
                    </list>
		 </div>
                </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
