<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-03-24">March
                        24, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x0026;#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory
                        University makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by
                        the Young John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim
                        of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download,
                        transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions
                        to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational
                        purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further
                        inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie, <date when="1857-04-13">April 13,
                        1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book
                    Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName></birth>
                        <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName></death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->
                </listPerson>
                <listPlace>
                    <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement/>
                            <region/>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
                <!-- or 1900-1999 -->

            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh"> ***<list>
                        <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                        <item>Emory College, Oxford, Ga.</item>
                        <item>Allen, Mary Houston</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change><date when="2009-04-02">April 2, 2009</date><name xml:id="sej">Yvette
                    Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Oxford Geo.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-03-24">March 24th 1857</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My Dearest "Mary"--</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I fondly anticipated a letter from you this morning, but as none came, I have
                    thought, perhaps, that you were expecting one from me too, in reply to your
                    last, before you would write.-- I do not Dearest, write you these lines because
                    of any anxiety or impatience but to assure you that I have not times to reply to
                    your last, but will anxiously await the answer to my last, when if I have <hi
                        rend="underlin">not</hi>time I will <hi rend="underline">take</hi>time to
                    reply.--<pb/></p>
                <p>I have some fun items of suggestion and observation, had I time to sum up and
                    write them which might be of some interest, now, but I forebear in this brief
                    communication and hold in reserve for the next--.</p>
                <p>I have written two letters to Mellie and on last week received one from her.</p>
                <p>Mollie, I was <hi rend="underline">very glad</hi>when I recieved it, it <add
                        place="supralinear">has</add>done me good; I intend answering it soon,
                    perhaps this evening. You must write and encourage her often My Dearest, her
                    heart and soul seemed fired up, too, for still higher attainments in a
                        <unclear>dim</unclear>life. Oh! may the Lord comfort his children and speed
                    on the happy day of the fulness of his love and the joy of his perfection<pb/>in
                    the hearts, (thy heart and soul and hers, my Dearest). Mellie stated that she
                    had not heard from you in two weeks and that she was very uneasy &amp;c.</p>
                <p>I must now close this letter by asking you<lb/>Do you know Miss Kendall?<lb/>" "
                    " F. Williamson?<lb/>" " " Mollie <unclear>Gonder</unclear>?<lb/>Has Miss
                    Rylander yet returned?<lb/>&amp;TC</p>
                <p>Now <hi rend="underline">My</hi>Dearest, I shall expect a letter, a <hi
                        rend="underline">long</hi>letter from you soon.-- I am <sic>affraid</sic>I
                    write too long, too much in my letters, not too much <hi rend="underline">of
                        ideas</hi>I do not mean but <del rend="strikethrough">of</del>that I
                    scribble down too<del rend="strikethrough">much</del>little in much- instead of
                    the other better plan of "<hi rend="underline">Multum in parvo</hi>"
                    &amp;C.--</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>My Dearest, Yours Affectionately &amp; Yours Only</salute>
                    <signed>Young J Allen</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
