<TEI xml:id="yja-19-feb-1857.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-02-19">Feb.
                        19 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-02-19">Feb.
                        19, 1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare
                    Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
		    </person>
		    <person>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region>/><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-06-08">June 8, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="ypw">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_073.jpg"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>E. C. Oxford Ga.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-02-19">Feb. 19 1857</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My Dear Mollie,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I take this opportunity, as I have not time to write a regular letter, to address
                    you a few lines.</p>
                <p>I should long ago, have written again, but tantalizing <hi rend="underline"
                        >hope</hi>, kept suggesting that I should get a letter from you, "<hi
                        rend="underline">on the next morning</hi>," and so I've been delaying, in
                    great anxiety, to hear a second time from you, for several reasons,-- But as
                        <unclear>Matt.</unclear> wrote me the other day that you had written to her
                    and she to you, but had not re'cd any response, I concluded that you intend
                    letting us hear from you soon. And with the exception of <hi rend="underline"
                        >this manifestation</hi> otherwise, I quietly and patiently await your
                    opportunity and pleasure to write, knowing that you will not delay under
                    favorable or even ordinary circumstances.</p>
                <pb/>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_074.jpg"/>
                <p>As we were disappointed in the <hi rend="underline">anticipated</hi> celebration
                    of my birth day, suppose we celebrate yours as we intended for mine.</p>
                <p>Please, Dearest, write me how you intend celebrating it, and I will, though some
                    distance from you, try to participate in spirit with you; Let's set it apart as
                    a <hi rend="underline">holy day</hi>, of fasting and prayer, of renewed
                    consecration and devotion to God-- and thereby begin the new <hi
                        rend="underline">year of life</hi> with a closer walk, and sweeter
                    communion, a holier, more confiding trust in the Lord.</p>
                <p>Please, Mollie, write me on Friday evening or night so that your letter may
                        <unclear>?</unclear> there on Saturday evening and be sure to reach me on
                        <hi rend="underline">Monday</hi>, which is your <hi rend="underline">birth
                        day</hi>. I am more than anxious to hear from you and do please write me a
                    long<pb/> letter, just such a one as you would like yourself under the
                    circumstances, and thus carry out the Precept of our Savior-- "do unto others as
                    you would they should do unto you."--</p>
                <p>I hope you will get this on tomorrow and respond at night immediately.</p>
                <p>When I write you <hi rend="underline">a letter</hi>
                    <del rend="strikethrough">and</del><add place="supralinear">in</add> reponse to
                    the <hi rend="underline">one</hi> I shall anticipate on Monday, or perhaps the
                    one I am <hi rend="underline">now</hi> anticipating may come tomorrow morning,
                    if so when I respond to one or either <hi rend="underline">this or that</hi>, I
                    will give you a more lengthy detail of matters both at home (here) and abroad,
                    (at Gran). You must please write me very soon.--</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Happily, I remain Ever Your own Devoted</salute> <signed>Young J. Allen</signed>
                    <address>
		      <persName>Miss Mollie Houston</persName><lb/>
		      <placeName>Macon<lb/>Ga</placeName>
		    </address>
		</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
