<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:id="yja-14-feb-1857.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-02-14"
                        >Febrary 14, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x0026;#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory
                        University makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by
                        the Young John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim
                        of copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download,
                        transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions
                        to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational
                        purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further
                        inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie, <date when="1857-02-14">February 14, 1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book
                    Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName></birth>
                        <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName></death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>


            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh"> 
		  <list>
                        <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                        <item>Emory College, Oxford, Ga.</item>
                        <item>Allen, Mary Houston</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change><date when="2009-05-07">May 7, 2009</date><name xml:id="sej">Yvette
                    Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_049.jpg" n="1st"/>
                <opener><epigraph><quote>"Don't view this with critic's eye<lb/>But pass its imperfections by."</quote></epigraph>
                    <dateline>Night<lb/>Emory College. Oxford Geo. <date when="1857-02-14">Feb. 14
                        1857</date></dateline>
                    <salute>My Dearest Mollie,</salute></opener>
                <p>Not <hi rend="underline">more joyfully</hi>did <del rend="strikethrough"
                        >Ahab</del>the words of the Old Prophet fall upon the ears of Ahab,
                    announcing "a sound of abundance of rain", after the long drought of three
                    years, than <del rend="strikethrough">those</del><add place="supralinear"
                        >did</add><hi rend="underline">those</hi>which announced for me thy letter
                    this morning.  With "hope" as my <hi rend="underline">Prophet</hi> and
                    "patience" for my servant, I had long been tarrying on Mt Carmel gazing far down
                    upon the Mediterranean. Often, yea more than <hi rend="underline"
                    >seven</hi>times had "patience" clambered to the heights of the Mt. and returned
                    with sad countenance; but the Old Prophet, <hi rend="underline">"hope"&#x2014;eternal
                        hope"</hi>, <del rend="strikethrough">still</del> once more arousing himself
                    as for a desperate effort, pierced the veil by faith, and saw the cloud,<pb/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff2_050.jpg"/> the timid cloud arise; and bidding "patience"
                    again retrace her steps to the <del rend="strikethrough">height</del><add
                        place="supralinear">summit</add> of the torturous peak, on tiptoe with eager
                    gaze, <hi rend="underline">too</hi>, she something spied, -which while she
                    hurried down in joyful haste to tell, fast and faster grew till all the sky was
                    darkened with the <hi rend="underline">truth</hi> and King and Prophet and
                    servant all rejoiced that indeed "a sound of abundance of rain" had come, and
                    that not only they, but the scanty herds, the perishing flocks, <hi
                        rend="underline">and</hi>exhausted, languid nature herself had heard the
                    sound thereof and had arisen from her sepulchre of death and had come forth with
                    bounding life currents and heart of health<del rend="strikethrough">ful</del>
                    and full pulse to meet the God of <del rend="strikethrough">showers</del><add
                        place="supralinear">rain</add> as he descended in blessings upon her head.
                    Yes, Dearest, you have but to read the account of Elijah and his servant upon
                    Mt. Carmel, <del rend="strikethrough">and you</del>
                    <add place="supralinear">to</add> have a true picture of <hi rend="underline"
                        >me</hi> (old wretched Ahab)<pb/> as <hi rend="underline">I passed the last
                        two weeks&#x2014;1st Kings 18th Chap.</hi></p>
                <p>But I must not tarry longer on this subject, for I fear I have already wearied
                    your patience; Suffice it however in this place to state, that you are perfectly
                    pardonable; for your excuse is certainly a most acceptable as well as valid one,
                    &#x2014;but on the other hand let me beg of you to pardon my great impatience of spirit
                    and anxiety of mind, which you <hi rend="underline">see</hi> I had, (though only
                    partially manifested,) if the above <hi rend="underline">illustration</hi> is
                    not too incredible for your faith.</p>
                <p>Your correspondence, Dearest, is one of the happiest privileges I enjoy; it is
                    the source <add place="supralinear">to me</add> of many a blessing; <del
                        rend="strikethrough">to me,</del> It comforts, cheers, animates the drooping
                    spirit, revives the heart wearied with tasks and burdened with cares, shines
                    upon the pathway of duty with an encouraging and tranquil radiance, that seems
                    to say, Ho! Pilgrim, courage, onward press, this is not thy goal, not thy rest.<pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_051.jpg"/>
                    <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_052.jpg" n="4th"/>then, how soon I remember the words, "That in
                    the Catalogue which fate reserves for a generous manhood, there <hi
                        rend="underline">is no such word as fail</hi>," and old energies arouse, new
                    efforts spring into being, and the spirit <add place="supralinear">thus</add>
                    fired and energized leaps forth from its lethargy into active life and with zeal
                    rejoices again to enter the race of joy and usefulness&#x2014; those are some of the
                    happy results which thy letters effect for me; and far greater than these might
                    I mention. I <hi rend="underline">will add</hi>, though, that, I find nothing
                    else so indispensable to my cheerfulness, my enjoyments, my very life as the
                    assurance <del rend="strikethrough">which</del> and encouragements which are
                    granted me through thy correspondence.&#x2014; Surely I <hi rend="underline">must</hi>
                    be, <hi rend="underline">ought</hi> to be, <hi rend="underline">am</hi> happy,
                    as some have ventured to say, blessed with such a <hi rend="underline">Dear</hi>, <hi rend="underline">congenial</hi>, <hi rend="underline">faithful</hi>, <hi rend="underline">"spirit-mate"</hi>, as Mrs Amelia
                    would have it.</p>
            </div>
	    <div>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_053.jpg"/>
                <dateline>Noon <date when="1857-02-18">Feb. 18th <hi rend="underline">57</hi>
                    </date></dateline>
                <p>With the preceding preliminary and rather excursory, if not at times, extravagant
                    remarks, I will now proceed, or at least so endeavor, to answer your letter, so
                    full of tenderness and affection, of sweet simplicity and generous confidence;
                    But as you see, I can not write <hi rend="underline">it</hi> all at once. I will
                    as I have leisure at noon and night, employ it all with thee and write <hi
                        rend="underline">then</hi> a little and <hi rend="underline">now</hi> a
                    little, and thus after awhile perhaps I can fulfill a responsive sheet; I merely
                    make the above statement that you may be the better prepared to pardon the
                    disconnected and limping sentences that I may be able under such circumstances
                    to throw together.</p>
                <p>I am happy to hear, Dear Mollie, that you are so well pleased with your <hi
                        rend="underline">comparatively</hi> new situation; that you have formed so
                    high an opinion and<pb/> estimate of your instructors; <del><gap reason="overwritten" extent="6" unit="letters"/></del> and that
                    among your new acquaintances, the students, you have found some choice, valuable
                    and sweet girls, in whom <del><gap reason="strikethrough" extent="6" unit="letters"/></del> you can confide, and with whom you can
                    now and then spend a "happy moment's time." Many intimate friendships, I
                    always thought were not desirable, or if desirable at least not advisable, and
                    so following <add place="supralinear">as well</add> my own inclination as the
                    desire to act "<hi rend="underline">prudently</hi>," wherever I have been, I
                    never would seek, nor form but few, and the same I would recommend to you
                    Dearest,&#x2014;although my experience reaches only to one side of the question, <add
                        place="supralinear">yet</add> observation will testify that it is the safest
                    and happiest in its results. Then Dear Mollie, though you find but few among the
                    many, in whom you can trust as bosom friends, prize, cherish and love them for
                    they will make you happy when the friendships and professions<pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_054.jpg"/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff2_055.jpg" n="7th"/> of the "many" shall have waxed cold and their
                    disguises have fallen off.</p>
                <p>I am sorry however to hear that the <hi rend="underline">very</hi> ones who ought
                    to be your most intimate and devoted friends are among the "many" whose
                   <sic>tratorous</sic> lips and false pretensions are so much to be shunned and despised; yet
                    Dearest, like the thorn which annoyed and vexed Paul, these things amy be
                    intended by a designing Providence to work out happy and glorious results for
                    us. We ought <del rend="strikethrough">always</del> to remember that the "<hi
                        rend="underline">thorn</hi>is always linked with the sweets fo the rose"&#x2014;
                    but by no means are <hi rend="underline">they</hi>justifiable to continue in sin
                    that <hi rend="underline">grace</hi> may the much more <hi rend="underline">abound</hi> in your behalf. God forbid, says the great Apostle in Romans
                    6thC. 1st-2nd.</p>
                <p>Well, Dearest, I have had some experience also in a situation very similar to
                    what your present one is,<pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_056.jpg"/>I have had all
                    sorts and dispositions of <unclear>chums</unclear>, <add place="supralinear"
                        >from</add> the mild, inoffensive, good natured, peaceable, quiet,
                    charitable religious and happy, to the wild, reckless, wretched, inconsiderate,
                    passionate and irreligious hard heart, stubborn and flinty and abandoned to
                    wretchedness and sin, and therefore, though I am <add place="supralinear"
                        >not</add> the better off by it having been so, yet I am the better prepared
                    to appreciate your very unenviable position and to sympathize with you in your
                        <hi rend="underline">seeming</hi> misfortune, in having been thus placed&#x2014;
                    but would you have a <hi rend="underline">sovereign antidote</hi> against all
                    such influences and dispositions and tempers which might be sinful in their
                    tendency, unholy and uncharitable in their character, growing out of your
                    present circumstances, then would I recommend to you a sure and prevailing
                    remedy, which will<pb/> not only prevent the <hi rend="underline">risings</hi>
                    of such <hi rend="underline">things</hi> in the future, but will even eradicate
                    all that has, (if any,) sprung up heretofore. It is a <hi rend="underline"
                        >medicine</hi> which I find to be pleasant in every respect.</p>
                <p><del rend="strikethrough">I found</del>It is designed to affect the heart more
                    particularly, and in nearly all its diseases proves a healing balm. Will you
                    try it, My Dearest Mollie? Yes I know you will, and incorporate it as I have
                    done in the list of Antidotes which are so much needed at times by the student
                    to counteract the poisonous influences and unwholesome prejudices which are so
                    apt to insinuate themselves into our <unclear>pain</unclear> and our lives. Then
                    here it is, in a few and simple words. "That I may be kept from speaking or
                    thinking amiss of my Christian friends, associates, or even my foes" those who
                    may be my secret oppressers, enemies, despisers or persecutors, "<hi
                        rend="underline">I will daily</hi> <hi rend="underline">for them</hi>."</p>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff_057.jpg"/>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_058.jpg"/>
                <p>Adopt that, Dearest, as one of your principal rules in the governing your heart
                    and regulating the sometimes "unruly member," and let what come then will, you
                    can still be cheerful and delight yourself in the holy will of God, do your duty
                    and be happy. Let not your present embarrassments deter you in the least from
                    your duties, Dearest, but patiently and perseveringly endure all for the cause
                    of your Dear Savior, and it will not be long before your meekness, and humble
                    reliance upon Providence, your reverence for his word and your trust and hope
                    therein, exemplified and enforced by your actions, will awe them into silence
                    and ultimately perhaps bring them to "consider." I have said thus much about
                    this and <hi rend="underline">them</hi> here, anticipating the obstacle of which
                    you spoke to<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_059.jpg"/> be one not so <del
                        rend="strikethrough">much</del> prejudiced to your common worldly or sensual
                    pleasures and enjoyments as to those of a more spiritual and holy character;
                    therefore you must pardon me if I have been rather <hi rend="underline">over
                        tedious</hi>, which doubtless you can justly say.</p>
                <p>Tis now &#x2014;"Night"&#x2014; again, and I have a few more minutes to employ in communion
                    with thee, and as it is usual to put off the <hi rend="underline">best</hi> for
                    the last, I now propose to close this rather lengthy communication with <hi
                        rend="underline">what</hi> I may say, in reply to your request, on that most
                    important subject, which I am <hi rend="underline">so</hi> glad to hear you say,
                    has not been neglected nor forgotten by you, but on the other hand, is eliciting
                    more &#x0026; more serious investigation every day, more earnestness, <del
                        rend="strikethrough">a</del> more "hungering and thirsting after entire
                    holiness of heart, <add place="supralinear">after</add> righteousness, after
                    Perfection&#x2014;Sanctification.</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>Now Dearest, you wish to know how to proceed; And by that I understand, if you
                    will allow me to draw inferences, -though I am satisfied in this instance
                    perfectly- that you "believe," as we sometimes ask a penitent, that there is
                    such a thing as a "holiness of heart," "Christian Perfection," Entire
                    Sanctification <del rend="strikethrough">(to be attained to, and realized in
                        this present life)</del> that you <hi rend="underline">believe</hi> such a
                    state is attainable and can be obtained even by you according to the blessed
                        promise<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> of our Dear Savior. "Blessed are
                    those which do hunger and thirst after righteousness for <hi rend="underline"
                        >they shall be filled</hi>;" that you, after having satisfied yourself that
                    there is such a blessing, and that it can be attained and enjoyed in this
                    present life, are now willing and ready to use <hi rend="underline">any means,
                        make any sacrifices, to be<del rend="strikethrough">come</del></hi> an
                    humble follower of our Lord all your days, "through evil as well as through good
                        report,"<pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_060.jpg"/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_061.jpg" n="13th"/> that you are willing to be
                    number'd with the outcasts, abandoned and persecuted, for his <hi
                        rend="underline">name's</hi> sake; to have your name even <del
                        rend="strikethrough">a</del> become a byword and reproach among <add
                        place="supralinear">
                        <hi rend="underline">in</hi>
                    </add> the world; that you are willing, yea desirous to become crucified unto
                    the world and have it crucified unto you; to leave <hi rend="underline">all,
                        home, friends, Sisters, dearest Ones</hi>, kindred, associates, companions
                    even <hi rend="underline">Country</hi> itself to spend your life, even a
                    voluntary exile, amid the depravity of Pagan Superstitionists or Heathen
                    Idolatries; Yes, Dearest Mollie, I understand from your "request" that you are
                    willing, yes anxious to "do", or "suffer", or "become" any of the above
                    humiliations if the Glory of the Lord can only be promoted and his blessed
                    kingdom advanced by you in any manner. Well now, Dearest, if you are willing to
                    "do" and "suffer" the above,<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_062.jpg"/> which I know
                    you are, because your words and your actions, which have never deceived me, both
                    testify to the earnestness and truthfulness of your inquiries into the way of
                    Holiness, there <add place="supralinear">are</add> a few conditions, which <del
                        rend="strikethrough">yours</del> in accordance to your <hi rend="underline"
                        >belief</hi>, "that there is such a state, and that <hi rend="underline"
                        >that state</hi> is attainable &#x0026;c here," that you must comply with
                    and fulfill, in order that you may begin to employ the means which are in your
                    power &#x0026;c, these conditions, some of them at least, are that you manifest
                    your desires after Perfection and the earnestness of your intentions, and more
                    than all <del rend="strikethrough">by</del> your willingness to have the
                    blessing bestowed upon you, by your actions and the earnest groanings of your
                    heart, unto God continually, besieging the throne of his Mercy by day and night
                    in continued supplication, prayers and tears, &#x0026;c. These are some of the
                    conditions that<pb/><sic>that</sic> you must comply with in order to prove your
                        <hi rend="underline">willingness</hi><add place="supralinear">to receive
                        it</add>; but, Dearest, there are others, also, which are equally important,
                    that you may prove (also) your <hi rend="underline">willingness</hi> to make <hi
                        rend="underline">any sacrifice</hi>, which might be necessary on your part
                    to secure that inestimable blessing&#x2014;which (blessing can be defined no <hi
                        rend="underline">more truly</hi> than in the brief words of our Dear
                        Savior<del rend="strikethrough">'s</del> when he said "<hi rend="underline"
                        >Father thy will be done not mine</hi>," that is the <hi rend="underline"
                        >true</hi> definition of <hi rend="underline">true "Christian
                        Perfection"</hi> and when Dear Mollie, you arrive at that place or point in
                    your experience when under any circumstances of adversity or prosperity, joy or
                    sorrow, griefs, trials, misfortunes or peace, happiness, of <del
                        rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="strikethrough" extent="1" unit="word"/></del> &#x0026;c when you can <hi rend="underline"
                        >say from the very bottom</hi> of <hi rend="underline">your heart</hi>,
                    "Lord thy <hi rend="underline">will</hi>, not <hi rend="underline">mine</hi> be
                        <hi rend="underline">done</hi>", then you have gained the <hi
                        rend="underline">triumph</hi> and the <hi rend="underline">joy</hi> is
                    yours,&#x2014; <hi rend="underline">that</hi> is, the "all in all" of <hi
                        rend="underline">Sanctification</hi>, believe<pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_063.jpg"/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff2_064.jpg"/>me, My Dearest, because it is the very essence
                    of the Spirit of Christ, himself, who hath left us <hi rend="underline"
                        >that</hi> model of <del rend="strikethrough">His</del> Perfection, that
                    high and holy standard of holiness unto which, through his own amazing
                    condescension, Love and Mercy, he hath opened up a way for our approach, and
                    thereby made what would otherwise have been forever inimitable and inaccessible
                    by us, plain and easy.</p>
                <p>But to return,&#x2014;now Mollie, after a considerable digression, which I trust
                    however will prove beneficial to us both&#x2014;we will (again) notice the second
                    condition with which you must comply, "<hi rend="underline">that</hi> of making
                        <hi rend="underline">any</hi> sacrifice necessary;&#x2014;</p>
                <p>Now, Dearest, you must examine your heart <hi rend="underline">thoroughly</hi>,
                    spare not; &#x0026; though it be painful to probe its secret depths, search it,
                    and try it, view it in the light of the Holy Spirit; try the strength of its <hi
                        rend="underline">attachment</hi> to the <hi rend="underline">cause</hi> of
                        <hi rend="underline">God</hi>, test its <hi rend="underline">sincerity</hi>,
                    and <pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_065.jpg"/> prove it, whether it be willing to
                    make a full and entire surrender of <hi rend="underline">itself</hi>; to make a
                        <hi rend="underline">life and eternity</hi> consecration, of all it holds
                    dear, <del rend="strikethrough">values</del>
                    <add place="supralinear">or estimates</add> or is in disguise connected with it
                    in time or eternity.  Whether (<hi rend="underline">it</hi>is) <add
                        place="supralinear">
                        <hi rend="underline">or you are</hi>
                    </add> willing to consecrate for once and always unto the Lord.</p>
                <p>"Your <hi rend="underline">soul</hi> and <hi rend="underline">body's</hi>
                    powers,<lb/>Your <hi rend="underline">memory</hi>, <hi rend="underline"
                        >mind</hi> and <hi rend="underline">will,</hi><lb/>All you <hi
                        rend="underline">know</hi> and all you <hi rend="underline"
                    >feel</hi>,<lb/>All you <hi rend="underline">think</hi> or <hi rend="underline"
                        >speak</hi> or <hi rend="underline">do</hi>;"<lb/> All your <hi
                        rend="underline">freedom</hi>, <hi rend="underline">friends</hi> and <hi
                        rend="underline">fame</hi>,<lb/> Your <hi rend="underline">loved
                        Sisters</hi>, health and <hi rend="underline">name</hi>,<lb/>And can adopt
                        <del rend="strikethrough">now</del> the language of the Pious <hi
                        rend="underline">Chas</hi> Wesley and say&#x2014; "From <hi rend="underline">this
                        moment</hi>, Lord, live or die,<lb/>I came, to serve my God alone."</p>
                <p>And if it can answer an affirmative to <hi rend="underline">all</hi> these, then
                    Dearest, <hi rend="underline">all is right</hi>.</p>
                <p>Now Mollie, we have examined all the conditions except one I believe, and
                    that<pb/> too has partially, if not wholy been incorporated in the last, &#x2014;<del
                        rend="strikethrough">and all of them</del> though perhaps they are all so
                    confused that it will prove quite a task to (decipher) <add place="supralinear"
                        >unravel</add> their tanglements and trace out their true meaning. Since
                    there may be some difficulty in understanding them I will try to place them in a
                    more tangible and plainer &#x2014;form&#x2014;<list><item>The 1st condition is&#x2014;That you manifest an
                    earnest desire and willingness on your part to receive the blessing.</item><item> 2d
                    That you be willing to make any sacrifice or consecration which the Lord may see
                    best in his wisdom to require.</item><item>3d- Which is to a great extent contained in
                    the second, that you be willing to resign yourself entirely into the hands of
                    the Lord and give up to his directions and his will altogether.</item></list></p>
                <p>The above are the conditions, Dearest, of which I have been in somewhat a
                    bungling <sic>maner</sic> speaking, and with<pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_066.jpg"/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_067.jpg"
                    />which you are required to comply.</p>
                <p>Now Dear Mollie, just proceed in that way and see what <del rend="strikethrough"
                        >ever</del> is <hi rend="underline">in</hi> the way&#x2014;and remove it
                    immediately. Test your <hi rend="underline">willingness</hi> first, and see if
                    you desire <hi rend="underline">it</hi> above <hi rend="underline">all
                        things</hi> else, and if you find you <hi rend="underline">do</hi>, why then
                    do not delay as to the other conditions; but since you desire it above all else;
                    ask yourself how it must be obtained; and when you learn that it must be by a
                    thorough, entire and unreserved consecration of <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
                    you have and <hi rend="underline">are</hi> to <hi rend="underline">God</hi>,
                    your tempers, dispositions thoughts &#x0026;c, and that you cannot fully comply
                    with the <hi rend="underline">second</hi> without <del rend="strikethrough"
                        >the</del> performing the 3d, why then comply with <hi rend="underline">it
                        too</hi> in all haste, delay not, but resign <hi rend="underline"
                    >all</hi>life, time, talents &#x0026;c, to him and lay yourself humbly at the
                    feet of Jesus and there wait the words of Your Blessed Jesus&#x2014;Your Friend
                    &#x0026; Savior.<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_068.jpg"/>But now, Mollie don't
                    forget that there is no <hi rend="underline">merit</hi> whatsoever in any thing
                    of <hi rend="underline">works</hi> that you can devise or use, and that this
                    blessing comes just like justification by <hi rend="underline">faith alone</hi>
                    in the Lord Jesus Christ, who is able to cleanse and purify and make holy. <hi
                        rend="underline">Faith</hi> is what you must use, Dearest, <hi
                        rend="underline">all the time</hi>. Place all you are and have upon the
                    Altar of <hi rend="underline">entire consecration</hi> and <hi rend="underline"
                        >there abide by faith, in prayer</hi>, till you receive the answer to your
                    petitions, yes an assurance that your consecration has been accepted and your
                    soul admitted into the sunshine of perfect love&#x2014;never, never retrace your
                    steps, but having vowed, like good old Jephtha pay your vows.
                    I am so glad that you are fully determined in the matter that you will seek
                    until the "promised blessing" is secured.</p>
                <pb/>
                <p>Oh! that the Lord may set your soul free, even before this <sic>come</sic> to
                    you.</p>
                <p>My Prayer is every day that we may both be <hi rend="underline">entirely
                        sanctified</hi> and made holy and acceptable, that the spirit of the Lord
                    may take up its abiding place in our hearts and rule there alone. Dearest
                    Mollie, I <hi rend="underline">do desire that</hi> above everything else, and I
                    do bless and praise the Lord that he has permitted me to enjoy such a rich
                    abundance of his mercies, such a depth of his love, such an unceasing flow of
                        joy<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> and peace as has been mine very nearly
                    every day since the 10th day of November. I want us to rejoice and praise God
                    together in our hearts and in the labor of our hands, be steadfast, persevering
                    and bold to claim the promises which <hi rend="underline">are</hi> ours <unclear>this</unclear>
                    Dearest, and we shall be permitted to live and serve our God "<hi
                        rend="underline">with joyful hearts &#x0026; free</hi>."</p>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_069.jpg"/>
	    </div><div>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_070.jpg"/>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1857-02-19">Morning 19th</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>Your letter, Dearest, did not reach me until Tuesday morning. I however
                        <unclear>according</unclear> as it requested, had kept your <hi
                        rend="underline">birth day</hi>, as a day of fasting and prayer, prayer,
                    especially, that you might realize the triumph of faith, and the fulness of the
                    joy which ever fills the Soul of a Christian at rest in Christ and abounding in
                    the Love of <hi rend="underline">Perfection</hi>.</p>
                <p>It proved, Mollie, a happy day indeed to my soul, and one long to be remembered
                    for its blessings, and benefits. I hope, Dearest, for I prayed for it, that you
                    too enjoyed much of the presence and joy of the Lord in your Soul, and that you
                    were much strenghened and confirmed and encouraged to&#x2014;<quote><l>"Set out anew, your
                    journey to pursue,</l><l>And after Glory run</l>."</quote></p>
                <pb/>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_071.jpg"/>
                <p>That you are now better prepared, by examination and prayer to devote yourself to
                    the service of the Lord, (And) that whether you live or whether you die you may
                    be entirely the Lord's. Be encouraged, My Dearest Mollie, the promise is yours,
                    claim it, the <hi rend="underline">blessings</hi> are yours too, appropriate
                    them and be happy.</p>
                <p>There are many other things Mollie about which I thought I would speak a few
                    words, but I must I reckon pass over them now, and reserve <hi rend="underline"
                        >them</hi> for the next times. I wish I did have time sufficient to allow me
                    to mention them, but I will <add place="supralinear">have</add> not now, &#x2014;but
                    enjoin it upon <hi rend="underline">you particularly</hi> to <hi
                        rend="underline">immediately reply to this</hi> and then I will give them to
                    you <hi rend="underline">at length</hi>. Remember now, Dearest, I shall take it
                    as a test of your anxiety and willingness<pb/> to hear from (&#x2014;), whether you
                    write soon or delay. I heard from Matt., the other day, but I
                    suppose you have heard since I have. She began her school on your <hi
                        rend="underline">birth day</hi>&#x0026;c.</p>
                <p>I wrote to Mellie as I told you I was going to. I could not comply Mollie
                    Dearest, with all your requests particularly the <unclear>Val</unclear>.Please
                    write me what kind of books you would prefer, and what kind of a Society is
                    yours&#x2014;I mean Secret or Literary.</p>
                <p>Are you acquainted with Misses Lundy, Mollie Rylander, Mollie Butts, a small
                    girl,? there are several others I thought I would ask you about but I have
                    forgotten their names.</p>
                <p>Be sure now, <hi rend="underline">My Dearest</hi>, and do not delay if you have
                    to do as I have done in order to write this, for I will be more than <hi
                        rend="underline">anxious</hi> to hear from you before I do, any way, even if
                    you write immediately.</p>
                
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_072.jpg"/>
                <p>Mollie, what do <sic/> think about taking music lessons, do you think <sic/>would
                    be a valuable appropriation of your time? that is the time spent at it?</p>
                <p>I believe if I were you I would take lessons during your <add place="supralinear"
                        >my</add> course there, it is true it would not do <hi rend="underline"
                        >you</hi> much good in the extensive sense that it might others, who would
                    wish to add a new charm to their beauties, or greater fascination to their
                    loveliness, by such flourishes and flashes in Society, but it would sweeten life
                    to some extent; for music hath its charms, and they soften down our coarser
                    natures &#x0026;c &#x0026;c&#x2014; but I have not time now to descant on that. You
                    must learn to sing Dearest, if you have to take lessons only for that. I am
                    going to learn too, we have two splendid teachers here now and I have entered as
                    a subscriber, <hi rend="underline">vocal music only</hi>. I am going to make an
                    effort to learn, please cooperate with me.</p>
                <closer>Write now very soon Mollie, please. <salute>Thine and thine only
                        forever.</salute><signed>Young J. Allen</signed></closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
