<TEI xml:id="yja-28-jan-1857.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-01-28"
                        >January 28, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-01-28"
                        >January 28, 1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and
                    Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item>Houston, Mollie.</item>
			<item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-06-08">June 9, 2009</date>
                <name>Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_076.jpg"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>E. C. Oxford Ga.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-01-28">Jan. 28th 1857</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My Dearest Mollie,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>With many thanks to a kind and obliging <hi rend="underline">Guardian</hi>, and
                    doubly many to your worthy, indulgent and generous President, for the honor
                    conferred and the fond privileges granted us, --which I trust shall be improved
                    happily and appreciated highly and well by us,-- I will endeavor, though hastily
                    and briefly, to respond <add place="supralinear">to</add> yours and
                    yester-morning-at-hand. To be brief then and concise I will try the plan of
                    Richard Watson, when writing to his daughter and "be systematic", for I like
                    system, order and adjustment in all things when convenient, and in writing a
                    letter, perhaps nothing is more desirable, <del rend="strikethrough">than</del>
                    to a proper distribution of facts or <add place="supralinear">a</add> relation
                    of items of news or information, than system, by which I mean a separate and
                    distinct disposition of each heterogeneous variety of news.<pb/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff2_077.jpg"/>But I must proceed to my "<hi
                        rend="supralinear">task</hi>," which lies more immediately before me, as I
                    did not set out with the intention of writing an essay on the <hi
                        rend="underline">necessity</hi>of<hi rend="underline">System</hi> or the <hi
                        rend="underline">advantages</hi> of <hi rend="underline">System</hi> in what
                    we do, besides that of writing a letter is by far the more preferable as well as
                    the more pleasing task --if thus you will allow me to call, its -- Oxford-- my
                    return &#x0026;c &#x0026;c.</p>
                <p>You are perhaps aware, from your knowledge of my past history in Oxford and of my
                        <hi rend="underline">returns</hi> hither, that on arriving here I found some
                    warm and generous friends both old and young, gentlemen and ladies to welcome me
                    back, and shall I be "presumptuous" enough to tell you the flattering <hi
                        rend="underline">truth</hi> that both by student and citizen I had a hearty
                    welcome to my "<hi rend="underline">Home Again</hi>," -- well be it so-- here I
                    am.</p>
                <p>Leisurely and lazily <hi rend="underline">in room</hi>, I spent the greater part
                    of my first week, it being<pb/>rather forbidding out-doors. I shall not enter
                    into minute detail of each several day, but suffice it on this head to say, that
                    a right respectable band of new students at the end of the week had gathered in,
                    to fill the places of the <hi rend="underline">departed</hi>, but in some
                    instances, not very tearfully lamented. There are perhaps now in of new and old
                    80 or 90-- On sabbath we had quite a treat from our Pastor, who formerly was
                    stationed there, (at Macon) he preached us two beautiful and sweet sermons. I
                    think him an amiable and zealous man; I became acquainted with him at Conference
                    and I tell <hi rend="underline">you</hi> I feel like giving him my hand in the
                    glorious work in which he is engaged and heartily cooperating with him. May God
                    bless and abound his good words and works in this place and build <add
                        place="supralinear">up</add> for himself an <del rend="strikethrough"
                        >great</del> exceeding great name her in the conversion<pb/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff2_078.jpg"/> and reclamation of all these sinners and
                    back-sliders, that a great cloud indeed (of witnessess) may arise from here and
                    spread itself with showers of blessings and benefits to communities and states
                    far and near.--</p>
                <p>Monday, regular exercises in College began and to day under full canvases I think
                    we have cleared our moorings with prospect of a prosperous and happy voyage. I
                        <hi rend="underline">know</hi> we have a faithful and tried Pilot, a Crew
                    whom other days have inured to perils and dangers, quicksands and wrecks, and
                    passengers some, of whom, at least, I can affirm, they will be landed safely at
                    our next Post-- Commencement -- but enough -- enough!!--</p>
                <pb/>
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_079.jpg"/>
                <p>Religious -- By the grace of God, my Dearest One, I intend to make the days of
                    this year severally and separately the holiest and happiest of my life. I have
                    done laid <hi rend="underline">all</hi> upon the Altar, made an entire, full and
                    consecrate surrender of life, time and talents-- soul, body and mind-- of all I
                    am or have-- substance, prospective, things temporal and things spiritual and do
                    again this night redetermine and vow to follow the Lord with whithersoever his
                    providence may guide or direct. The power of his grace supporting and the
                    strength of his Spirit sustaining me. I want to be a holy, sanctified and
                    zealous Christian servant, entirely devoted to the will and service of my most
                    holy Master. I want to be usefull in my day and generation -- and spend <hi
                        rend="underline">the day</hi> alloted me here in the vineyard of the Lord.
                    Do you not agree with <pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_080.jpg"/>me, Dearest, in what
                    I have said? Yes I know you do, for our intentions are one and the same our
                    purposes and our aims in life -- that is, the glory of God and the salvation of
                    our own souls and those of our fellow mortals. May the Lord help us so to devote
                    ourselves, in our intercourse with the world, in our conduct and deportment, to
                    his cause as shall successfully <del rend="strikethrough">as shall</del> "land
                    and magnify <del rend="strikethrough">"</del> his name."</p>
                <p>I have last night and to day just made my first entries in my journal. I began by
                    totally resigning myself to God and consecrating <hi rend="underline">my
                        all</hi> to him, and (have been) <add place="supralinear">
                        <hi rend="underline">continued by</hi>
                    </add> framing and selecting such rules as I thought would best assist me in
                    carrying out <hi rend="underline">Our plans</hi>, regulating my life and
                    governing my conduct.</p>
                <p>My Dear Mollie, though far we be from each other I know you will <pb/>zealously
                    and fervently write with me in carrying out our general and I trust
                    Providence-approved plans of future life. Let us devote ourselves then, Dearest,
                    more entirely more thoroughly to God, become more alive to God and good works
                    and more dead to the world and the things of the world.</p>
                <p>"<hi rend="underline">Blessed</hi> are <hi rend="underline">all</hi> they that
                    put their trust in the Lord". Is not our trust Mollie, in the Lord only? then
                    let's hold fast; <hi rend="underline">there's</hi> the promise and "<hi
                        rend="underline">He</hi> is faithful that promised." Let us not forget the
                    "ways of pleasantness and paths of peace" which are of the Lord-- nor stray from
                    God's flock that cheerfully feeds in the "green pastures and beside the still
                    waters," "to walk in the counsel of the ungodly, nor stand in the way of sinners
                    nor sit in the seat of the scornful-- but rather let us delight in the law of
                    the Lord and <pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_081.jpg"/><sic>and</sic> in his law
                    meditate day and night, that we too, like <hi rend="underline">that man</hi>
                    described in the 1st Psalm, may be like a tree <hi rend="underline">planted</hi>
                    (not a wild tree) but <hi rend="underline">a tree planted</hi> by the <hi
                        rend="underline">rivers</hi> of <hi rend="underline">water</hi> not <hi
                        rend="underline">by a little branch</hi> that the summer droughts exhaust
                    and dry away, not by a little wet-weather streamlet, but by the <hi
                        rend="underline">rivers</hi>of water, that bringeth forth his fruit in his
                    season; whose leaf shall not wither, but whatsoever he doeth shall be watered
                    and nourished of God and therefore shall prosper.-- God Bless you My Dearest
                        One.--I must now close. Pardon this very hasty and imperfect reply
                        to yours. I would have selected a better time, but I knew not when it would
                        come, so rather than hold you in further suspense I submit this. There are
                        several items I shall have to neglect now Dr N. for instance &#x0026; his
                        care. I am going to write to Mellie soon as I can. <hi rend="underline">Must
                            I</hi>? Mollie I know you will write me soon therefore I will not ask
                        you, for I know you will and I expect it-- anxiously await a "lengthy"
                        reply.</p><closer><salute>Thine Own &#x0026; Forever</salute><signed>Yound J.
                            Allen</signed>
                    </closer>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
