<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-03-31">March
                        31, 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen </sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie, <date when="1857-03-31">March 31,
                        1857</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book
                    Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="thyun">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->
                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>
                    <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement/>
                            <region/>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-03-25">March 25, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <note resp="#yja" place="inline">N. B.<p>I will have to send this contrary to your
                        request.-- So you must pardon it and write back on Saturday or just as soon
                        as you can.-- I'll be patient.--<signed>Young</signed></p></note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>E. C. Oxford Geo.</placeName>
                        <date when="1857-03-31">March 31st 1857</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My Dearest Mollie--</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I would gladly avail myself of any opportunity that presents itself of writing to
                    you even though it be but a few lines at a time-- therefore as I have a few
                    leisure moments now, I trust that to spend them in sweet communion with <hi
                        rend="underline">my Dearest Mollie</hi>, will not be altogether unacceptable
                    to thee-- I have not time to enter into a full and comprehensive answer to your
                    letter so full of affection and confidence <hi rend="underline">in him
                    who</hi>hopes at no <hi rend="underline">very distant</hi>day to share with <hi
                        rend="underline">thee the</hi>/burdens and crosses of life of which you
                    spoke in such simple and pathetic language.-- <hi rend="underline">Mollie</hi>,
                    I have read your letter over and over again; it is sad, yet that sadness is
                    sweet when I see it united with such tenderness of spirit such abasement of
                    self-- it is a strain of sadness such as is calculated to work profitablness to
                    the soul; it is a sadness such as the wise man contemplates when he said it is
                    better to go to the house of mourning than to the place of mirth.-- Yes, Mollie,
                    it did, though, unanticipated by you, give me more pleasure than pain. And how
                    can that be, does not My Dear One ask? Well, Mollie, I'll tell you how it is.--
                    I have had the same experiences myself, I had to suffer mortification,
                    disappointment and anguish from the very same causes. I had to be abased,
                    humbled and taught my own weakness, and depravity, my utter helplessness and
                    insufficiency of myself to accomplish any good, just as you have stated in
                    reference to yourself, your own heart; now Dearest, in all these things our
                    experience does not diverge at all, but mutually coincide throughout.--</p>
                <p>You have now arrived at a most important crisis, <del ren="strikethrough"
                        >where</del>in the history of your religious experience where you can just
                    begin to see the glory of being a <hi rend="underline">thorough devoted,
                        entirely converted Christian</hi>, you are now my <hi rend="underline"
                        >precious Mollie</hi>occupying a high stand point from which God permits you
                    to look <del rend="strikethrough">below</del><add place="supralinear"
                    >down</add>upon the <hi rend="underline">world as it is</hi>--upon <hi
                        rend="underline">your heart as it is</hi>, now Dearest that is a <hi
                        rend="underline">precious</hi>privilege and one which you should value very
                    highly because now that you have seen the deceitfulness, the corrupt blindness
                    of your heart, you can turn away more successfully from its suggestions and
                    dictates and flee to the Closet for Communion with God, with him who knoweth the
                    secret intents and purposes of your heart.-- I might say a great deal on this
                    interesting and fruitful subject but it is all needless, but suffice it to say-
                    My Dearest, that you are <del rend="strikethrough">now</del><hi rend="underline"
                        >almost</hi>right, if not <hi rend="underline">quite right</hi>, and I
                        <unclear>believe</unclear>Dearest from your experience that you have shared
                    some of the fulness of the promised blessings of God-- that you have had great
                    encouragement to be vigilant and vigorous still in the struggle; the fiercest of
                    the conflict perhaps is over now, for the powers of darkness are beginning to
                    yield and fall back when the horrid deceit and crimes of the soul when the <add
                        place="supralinear">its</add>secret aults and weaknesses are beginning to
                    show themselves you have overcome the greatest and strongest of <add
                        place="supralinear">his</add>powers- that is-<del rend="strikethrough"
                        >the</del>to see yourself as you are, that is what Satan would have us blind
                    to always, and as long as he can have that he knows the case is a sure one, but
                    thanks to God, <hi rend="underline">My Mollie</hi>, that the secret path, like
                    that around Thermopylae of old has been found out by you, and that you have been
                    enabled to defeat the purposes of your great arch-enemy by getting <del
                        rend="strikethrough">a proper</del>so to speak <hi rend="underline"
                        >into</hi>yourself and beholding for yourself the hidden works which he was
                    carrying on there.-- Raise the shout now, My Dearest for the Victory is surely
                    yours, you will Triumph, though the devil with all his legions oppose you, you
                    may expect a desperate encounter- you perhaps have had one, <del
                        rend="strikethrough">for</del>Leonidas and his brave companions did not give
                    back when they stood in that narrow pass, you recollect, but met the enemy and
                    fell on the field-- so these daring presumptuous sins these legions <del
                        rend="strikethrough">from</del> commissioned from below to torment and worry
                    your soul will bravely contest it with you till the very last moment, but just
                    as sure <del rend="strikethrough">as the</del>as the Spartans fell at
                    Thermopylae will they fall before the armed power of God; trust <hi
                        rend="underline">in God</hi> then my dearest, My Beloved;-- I can rejoice
                    over the account you gave me of your experience because I think all will <hi
                        rend="underline">soon</hi>be right, God grant it may be.</p>
                <p>Sad account! why Mollie you could have told me nothing <hi rend="underline">(that
                        seems)</hi> so auspicious as that; that is the sure sign of your progress.--
                    Oh! be encouraged; I am <hi rend="underline">almost</hi>led to say that you have
                    obtained that for which you seek.-- Another one of my friends has been enabled
                    to obtain and rejoice in <del rend="strikethrough">the</del><hi rend="underline"
                        >perfect assurance</hi> of acceptance,- of perfect Love, and we have
                    frequently talked it over; (it occured since I wrote you last,) and I find that
                    our experiences very much resemble and both greatley, particularly as to doubts
                    and fears, coincide with yours.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">thank God</hi>, any how My Dearest, yes I do <hi
                        rend="underline">right now</hi>, that you have been brought this far in his
                    knowledge and <sic>and</sic> in the light of his countenance.--</p>
                <p>You lack nothing at all My Dearest now, according to your experience, that I
                    know, that keeps you from that perfect Love. I believe you have obtained it. I
                    will venture to say so <hi rend="underline">any how</hi>- for how is it that you
                    were not so blessed before when you asked? You said then that you could not
                    believe God would give it to you right <hi rend="underline">then</hi>.-- Well
                    now, how was it when you said you <hi rend="underline">would</hi> believe, did
                    not the blessing come, did you not feel happy, did you not rejoice? Oh! My
                    Dearest, that was the obstacle all the while, and that <hi rend="underline"
                        >surely</hi> was the blessing which you received as soon as it was removed-
                        <sic>wasn't</sic> Dearest? Yes, Glory be to God-- don't you say so too from
                    your very heart-- Mollie?</p>
                <p>But you feared, and indeed you said, that you could not believe you had received
                    such a blessing, judging from your life the next day-- now Mollie I don't think
                    there was anything in <hi rend="underline">that</hi> which could authorize you
                    to disbelieve it; I don't doubt but taht you felt some bitter regrets and that
                    your conscience smote you some for having neglected what you purposed doing--
                    but my Dearest, I cannot see that that was a particular violation of any (very
                    impervious) <hi rend="underline">duty</hi> or that the neglect of once or twice
                    reading the Scriptures under such circumstances should cause you to doubt your
                    acceptance, to doubt what the Lord had done for you-- no My Beloved I don't
                    think that can be any evidence at all that you were not blessed with a full
                    salvation.-- Your resolutions were firm and your intentions were bright towards
                    God, then let not your heart be discouraged for says Thomas A. Kempis, "it is
                        <hi rend="underline">no illusion</hi> that thou art sometimes wrapt in an
                    ecstacy but presently returnest to the accustomed weaknesses of thy heart", by
                    no means,but it was not even weakness in thy heart nor the absence of a better
                    purpoe that caused you to neglect that which you so much regretted, not but
                    rather the pressure of circumstances.-- Oh1 My Beloved, arise and rejoice in the
                    Lord, burst the fetters of darkness and give glory to the Lord, Gof of our
                    Salvation.-- My Beloved I cannot write any more now on these very interesting
                    themes, nor have I time to notice all your letter, but I do believe-- and I must
                    say presson-- that you are <hi rend="underline">almost</hi>home, My Dearest
                    Mollie. I never fail to remember you, and the Lord <hi rend="underline"
                        >will</hi> answer your petitions, and I can't help but believe, it is his
                    work that's now being accomplished in your experience-- don't then get
                    discouraged but when you sin go to God and confess it and he will pardon and
                    accept you for Christ's sake.-- You know how I <sic>done</sic><add
                        place="supralinear">had to do</add>, what expedient I had to resort to when
                    I was convicted and awaken'd to a sense of my duty in reference to this
                    blessing. I tried my rellious, wicked, <hi rend="underline">deceitful heart</hi>
                    till I could not trust it in a single instance so I took my little (vade mecum)
                        <del rend="strikethrough"/>illegible word</del> commonplace book and set down every sin, every
                    thing which I thought or felt to be in my way, and that is <hi rend="underline"
                        >all</hi> the way I would overcome myself.-- I would always </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>


</TEI>
