<TEI xml:id="yja-13-april-1857.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston, <date when="1857-04-12">April 13,
      1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
    <author>
     <name type="person">
      <choice>
       <sic>Young</sic>
       <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
      </choice>
     </name>
    </author>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent/>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
    <date>2008</date>
    <availability>
     <p>&#x0026;#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University makes a
      claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young John Allen Project
      participants. Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text. Permission is
      granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the
      contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
      provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries about this text's
      availability, please contact:
      <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
    <respStmt>
     <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
     <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
     <name>Stewart Varner</name>
     <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
    </respStmt>
   </seriesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie, <date when="1857-04-13">April 13, 1857</date>;
     Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
    <listPerson>
     <person xml:id="yja">
      <persName>
       <forename>Young</forename>
       <forename>John</forename>
       <surname>Allen</surname>
      </persName>
      <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
        <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
        <region type="state">Georgia</region>
        <country>United States</country>
       </placeName></birth>
      <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
        <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
        <country>China</country>
       </placeName></death>
     </person>
     <person xml:id="Mollie">
      <persName>
       <forename>Mary</forename>
       <forename>Houston</forename>
       <surname>Allen</surname>
      </persName>
     </person>

     <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->
    </listPerson>
    <listPlace>
     <!-- add any list places you want to -->
     <place>
      <placeName>
       <settlement/>
       <region/>
      </placeName>
     </place>
    </listPlace>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John Allen Letters
     Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by
     this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical
     purposes.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <samplingDecl>
    <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may be provided
     as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
   </samplingDecl>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page using either
     a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi. These digital images were
     converted to an electronic text file by transcription. The text files produced have been
     proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of the original. This proofread text
     file has then been encoded using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
     Guidelines. For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for
     Best Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently replaced em
     dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles displayed in brackets have
     been added by the encoder and do not appear in the original text.</p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
     <bibl>
      <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
     </bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
    <rs type="language">English</rs>
    <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
    <date>1800-1899</date>
    <!-- or 1900-1999 -->

   </creation>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="lcsh">
     <list>
      <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
      <item>Emory College, Oxford, Ga.</item>
      <item>Allen, Mary Houston</item>
     </list>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change><date when="2009-03-23">March 23, 2009</date><name xml:id="libypw">Yvette Wright</name>
    transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div type="letter">
    <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_003.jpg"/>
    <opener>
     <dateline>E.C. Oxford Geo. <date when="1857-04-13">Apr. 13 1857</date></dateline>

     <salute><hi rend="underline">My own Dearest Mollie</hi>,</salute>
    </opener>
    <p><hi rend="underline">I do thank God, and praise God</hi>, that he hath dealt so kindly, so
     mercifully, and so graciously <add place="supralinear">with</add> our souls. Yes, <hi
      rend="underline">My Own Mollie, I do bless God</hi> that in his Providence I ever knew <hi
      rend="underline">you</hi>. Tis the work of the Lord, <del rend="strikethrough">and</del> that
     brought us together and <hi rend="underline">Glory be to God</hi>, I know tis his Spirit that
     is leading us on.-- My Dear Mollie, your letter overcame me I was <hi rend="underline">so
      glad</hi>.-- I went away, <hi rend="underline">far away</hi>into a <hi rend="underline">thick
      wood</hi> and there praised and blessed God and thanked him that he had heard our prayers and
     blessed our souls with the <hi rend="underline">fulness</hi> of his love and with the joy
      and<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_004.jpg"/> of a <hi rend="underline">full Salvation</hi>, of an
     entire and accepted consecration, yes of an entire Sanctification of soul and all its powers,
     of body, time, talents and <add place="supralinear">all our</add> substance and all our
     interests in the world.-- And just about the time I got your letter, I believe on the very same
     day, I found out that another one of my friends here had gained the triumph.-- And oh! Glory be
     to God, Mollie, I have been <hi rend="underline">full</hi> all the week, I could <hi
      rend="underline">scarcely talk</hi>, tears of joy would rush and fill my eyes all the times,
     and choke my utterance. I had to stay in my room and rejoice and my happy, dear friends would
     visit me once and awhile and such <del rend="strikethrough">a</del>glorious times this earth
     never affords to poor sinners-- And my Mollie</p>
    <pb/>
    <p>At class meeting on Friday night the good Spirit and all its sweet and heavenly influences
     were there.-- Our leader called on me to close by prayer after the exercises were over-- and in
     the act of praying the power of the Spirit seemed to rest upon my soul and almost overcome me,
     (this poor soul)-- so that I went away rejoicing and from that time till now I have been
     scarcely able to do anything, my mind would be so abstracted.--</p>
    <p>I set down on Saturday evening to answer your letter, but before I wrote half a page, my soul
     became so full and overwhelmed that I had to stop,-- I <hi rend="underline">could not</hi>
     write.-- I feel the same good Spirit this morning and would delight to write you a full answer
     to your letter but I cannot<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_005.jpg"/> as I have but a very few
     minutes this morning and I know not when I ever will have time again-- as I Just hastily drop
     you these lines to tell you My <hi rend="underline">Dearest, precious Mollie</hi>, that I know
     not when I can write you a full answer, for I have so much to do now I can scarcely turn
     round.-- I want you to write me a <hi rend="underline">long letter</hi> in answer to <hi
      rend="underline">this</hi> if it is <hi rend="underline">but a note</hi>, and tell me some
     more of your experience and how you have enjoyed yourself since that happy triumphing hour when
     "faith lent its realizing light."-- Don't be ashamed, nor <sic>affraid</sic> to confess what
     the Lord has done for you My Beloved Mollie no, no, that is, to those who ought to know.</p>
    <p>Be sure and read the <hi rend="underline">Riches</hi> of <hi rend="underline">Grace</hi> as I
     asked you Mollie, in connection with your present experience it will confirm and establish your
     heart in its present height of joy and love.-- We sent on for 5 more copies of it here, all the
     boys are so anxious to read it.</p>
    <pb/>
    <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_006.jpg"/>
    <p>Speak to Miss Nellie on the subject, if you think it will be prudent, or any other of your
     friends that are anxious for a growth in grace and get them enlisted with you and endeavor, My
     Dearest, to awaken a deep concern on the subject there as there is now with us.-- Oh! the good,
     the glory which may thus be accomplished.--</p>
    <p>Be sure <sic>an</sic> answer all my questions concerning Miss Nellie. I<del
      rend="strikethrough">'ll</del><hi rend="underline">will</hi> tell My <hi rend="underline"
      >Dearest</hi>, who it is that is inquiring, tis <hi rend="underline">John Norris</hi>, of
     Columbus-- one of my best friends, the <hi rend="underline">first</hi> one that raised the
     shout of <hi rend="underline">triumph</hi> this term in Oxford-- he is a happy soul, will join
     the Conference next winter.--</p>
    <p>My case (concerning which I asked your advice) is before the preacher &amp; leaders. I
     have not heard yet the result of my petition but will in a few days and let you know.-- I went
      no<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_007.jpg"/> farther down the road than Atlanta.-- But according
     to <unclear>friends</unclear> I shall have to go down on some business to Grantville about the
     first of May.-- If there should be anything at that time you want from there, or that I can do
     for you please write me Mollie and you know how happy I will be to do it for you. I can get
     anything for you and send it down from Atlanta to you on my return.-- You can write home and
     have arrangements made for sending you whatever you want and I will attend to it as I
     return.--</p>
    <closer>
     <p><hi rend="underline">My Dearest Mollie</hi>, pray much for your own unworthy Young, that he
      may hold out, be faithful and do the will of God in all things.--</p>
     <p>Pardon this as it is only a few lines to warn you that I know not when I can write.-- Write
      immediately please My Mollie.-- God bless you and keep you in the prayer of <hi
       rend="underline">your own faithful</hi> Young <hi rend="underline">forever</hi>.--</p>
    </closer>
   </div>
  </body>
  <back>
   <div type="envelope">
    <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_001.jpg"/>
    <dateline>
     <date when="1857-04-13">13 Apr '57</date>
    </dateline>
    <p>
     <address><persName>Miss Mollie Houston</persName><lb/><addrLine>W. F. college</addrLine><lb/><addrLine>Macon</addrLine><lb/><addrLine>Georgia</addrLine></address>
    </p>
    <p>Care of<lb/>Prest. Smith</p>
    <pb facs="Allen_11_ff2_002.jpg"/>
   </div>
  </back>
 </text>
</TEI>
