<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to his mother, Nancy Hutchins, <date
                        when="1867-10-07">October 7, 1867</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to his mother, Nancy Hutchins, <date
                        when="1867-10-07">Octover 7, 1867</date>; Young John Allen Papers,
                    Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region>/><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-07-20">July 20, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_001.jpg"/>
                <opener>
                    <note>This letter should reach you the 1st or 2d week in Jan. 1868 at
                        farthest--perhaps before Christmas.</note>
                    <note place="margin">I hope you will get some one to read this for you. I fear
                        you can't read it.</note>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Shanghai China</placeName>
                        <date when="1867-10-07">Oct. 7th 1867</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My own dear mother,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>My own dear Mollie is far away in Japan with our little darlings, and I am left
                    here alone; During the day I am busy but at night I feel solitary and sometimes
                    not a litte <hi rend="underline">homesick</hi>. I miss my Mary very much and
                    little Mellie, Charlie and Edgar, and as I often think of you too I have thought
                    to write you a few lines by this mail. I often wonder how you are looking. We
                    have been separated a long time and I know time and trouble have not left you
                    without traces of their cares. Your face I know must reflect the shadows of the
                        <unclear>pain?</unclear>, and your gray hairs tell the tale of age and
                    sorrow. I always think of you as last I saw you when we parted. Your <hi
                        rend="underline">ambrotype</hi> stills keeps good, and as I gaze on it my
                    heart is with you then again. Through Wright and Uncle Carter I have heard from
                    you since the war, but have not had a word from any of you yet.</p>
                <p>I do so much wish to know how you all are and how you are getting along in your
                    old age, and as I suppose you would like to have a few details of my family I
                    will tell you in this letter. We have had some trials and embarrassments here,
                    but chiefly on account of the war in which you suffered so much -- far more than
                    we have.</p>
                <p>We have a pleasant home here in Shanghai<pb/>
                    <pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_002.jpg"/> and my health and Mary's too has been
                    exceedingly good all the time. I have not been sick scarcely a day since I saw
                    you eight years ago. Our little family has been steadily increasing. Oh what a
                    happy thing it is to have children around us, in our own house in this far off
                    heathen land. We have had <hi rend="underline">six</hi>, three are now in heaven
                    and three are with their darling mother in Japan, where they have gone for a
                    short trip. Our first you have seen. Mellie is now a large girl and can spell
                    and read and sing, and makes us very happy. Our second was a fine large boy,
                    weighing (12) twelve pounds when born; he was the very image of his mother, with
                    heavy black hair curling all over his head. We named him Yound John after his
                        <hi rend="underline">papa</hi>. He only lived to be 11 months and 14 days
                    old. we think of him now as our Angel boy in that bright abode with Jesus, who
                    said suffer little children to come unto me and forbid them not for of such is
                    the kingdom of heaven. Our third little one still lives and is now nearly five
                    years old. His name is Charles Arthur, and a cheerful little fellow he is. He
                    loves for his papa to tell him little stories about <del rend="strikethrough"
                        >about</del> the children in America. He has some nice little books, but has
                    not learned to read yet. Our <del rend="strikethrough">fifth</del><add
                        place="supralinear">4th fourth</add> was named <hi rend="underline">Herbert
                        Maury</hi>. He lived to be 19 months old, and he too was taken away. We felt it<pb/>
                    <pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_004.jpg"/>hard to give him up. He was such a precious
                    little pet- was just beginning to talk and run about the house. He had just cut
                    his last tooth when inflamation of the bowels set in and soon he was taken from
                    us, but we mourn not now our little lamb-- we know he is safely in the fold and
                    Jesus is his Shepherd. Oh! <add place="supralinear">how</add> strong the ties
                    that bind us to heaven. Here are wo little verses I wrote soon after he
                    died.</p>
                <p>1st Here storms will still obscure<lb/>Tempests still be driven<lb/>Earth's ties
                    ne'er endure<lb/>All will soon be riven<lb/> 2d But beyond this dark
                    scene<lb/>This sad vale of tears<lb/>Herbert shall be ours again<lb/>Through
                    eternal years.</p>
                <p>Yes that is our great consolation that if we are faithful we shall meet these
                    dead little ones again in heaven and never, never leave <hi rend="underline"
                        >them</hi>, nor they us again <hi rend="underline">forever</hi>. Is not that
                    consolation enough? Our fifth is another bright boy just like his <hi
                        rend="underline">Ma Ma</hi>, with long black curly hair. He is one of
                    nature's finest mold and a dear little one he is. He is not quite two years old
                    yet, but such a sprightly little romper jolly and full of fun. He is just
                    learning to talk. His name is <hi rend="underline">Edgar Pierce</hi>. Our sixth,
                    the little <hi rend="underline">Nameless one</hi> was born at seven months and
                    only lived ten hours. She was a girl with jet black hair. My dear Mollie was
                    suffering intense agony from neuralgia or face ache which brought on a premature
                    confinement last July (1867). Mollie never suffers during confinement<pb/><pb
                        facs="Allen_11_ff8_003.jpg"/>more than two or three hours. The Doctor hardly
                    has time to reach her, and she soon recovers. If you were to see her now you
                    would not believe she is the mother of six children. She looks almost as young
                    and beautiful as when you saw her last. She has made me one of the best of
                    wives. If I had sought the whole world over, I could not have found a more
                    devoted and better one. Everybody loves her in Shanghai that knows her and she
                    has many kind friends. I have loved Mollie ever since <hi rend="underline"
                        >1854</hi>, thirteen years and more, and every year I love her better. I
                    sometimes fear I love her too much. We are along ways separated from you and
                    from all our dear relatives and friends, but we love each other so much and have
                    such a cheerful little family of children that we are quite happy here. As for
                    myself I am <hi rend="underline">Young</hi>yet, both in name and in age. Mollie
                    is 28 and I am 31 years old. I don't think I have changed much. I will enclose
                    you our <hi rend="underline">photographs</hi> (pictures) and you can judge for
                    yourself. You will see that I wear a heavy beard. I have not shaved since the
                    war began in America and don't know when I shall. The Chinese look at my beard
                    and wonder at my age. They say I am about <hi rend="underline">80</hi> eighty
                    years old. The Chinese do not begin to have whiskers till they are about 40
                    forty and never large then.<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_005.jpg"/><note
                        place="margin">Mollie and the children will be back I hope this month-- have
                        been gone one month</note>Well now I suppose you would like to know what I
                    am doing. I came here as a Missionary to preach to the heathen, who are
                    idolaters; they worship all kinds of <hi rend="underline">gods</hi> made out of
                    wood and stone, mud &amp;c and know nothing about God that created heaven
                    and earth. They are very wretched and miserable and our work is a work of
                    charity and love. Jesus said "Go into all the world and preach my gospel to
                    every creature, all nations, and we have obeyed his call and command. We feel
                    that God hath called us to this work and we have no fears but that he will care
                    for us and bless us. When I was leaving home I sold out all my negroes
                    &amp;c and put the money in the Atlanta &amp; Westpoint and Central
                    R.Roads which has proved to be a safe investment so far, myself and my dearest
                    wife &amp; child I committed to the guidance of my heavenly Father and thus
                    far he hath kept <hi rend="underline">us</hi>. When the war began the Missionary
                    Society of our Church could not send us any money and for nearly five years we
                    did not get a cent from home. Yet we never suffered want. The oil in <add
                        place="supralinear">the</add>cruze, <del rend="strikethrough">nor</del><add
                        place="supralinear">and</add>the flour in the barrel never failed; like
                    Elijah in the wilderness, we were fed as it were by the ravens, which found us
                    even this far off wilderness of China. At present we have not received
                    sufficient funds from the Society to enable us to do much missionary work,
                        but<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_006.jpg"/>I manage to support myself and <del
                        rend="strikethrough">work</del><add place="supralinear">preach</add>
                    besides. I have a large Chinese School in the city of Shanghai and teach in it
                    40 young men three hours a day. The School belongs to the Chinese Government and
                    the young men are preparing to be officers. The highest officer in Shanghai is
                    the Superintendent of the School. He pays me about 200 two hundred <hi
                        rend="underline">green backs</hi> (dollars) <del rend="strikethrough"
                        >pa</del><add place="supralinear">a</add> month to teach it (3) three hours
                    a day. I teach from 9 to 12 o'clock each day except Sunday.</p>
                <p>In the afternoons and on the Sabbath I preach to the people in our chapels here
                    in the city and also in <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> some large towns out
                    in the country. How large do you suppose Shanghai is? Well suppose you put
                    Savannah, Augusta, Atlanta, Macon, Columbus, Rome &amp; Charleston <del
                        rend="strikethrough">and</del> together and then add on New Orleans besides,
                    then you would not have a city as large as Shanghai. Savannah in China would be
                    a little town. One third of all the people in the world live here in China. You
                    never saw such crowds. There are Chinamen everywhere. You <sic>cant</sic>get out
                    of sight. There are no trees in the country here like there are at home-- every
                        <del rend="strikethrough">thing</del>
                    <add place="supralinear">place</add> is a field or graveyard. There are <hi
                        rend="underline">millions</hi> of <hi rend="underline">graves</hi> in this
                    old country. And just think of it. All these people worship the <hi
                        rend="underline">devil</hi> instead of God. They know what is right but they
                    will not do it. They are all going to hell. There is no Savior in China. Some of
                    them believe after they die they will <pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_007.jpg"/>
                    turn into a bird or some beast, if they are bad but if they are good will come
                    back, that is be born again into the world, and be richer men or officers of
                    Government. They know nothing about heaven. The Bible, God, Jesus, Heaven and
                    Salvation they never heard of before, it is all news to them, and you know the
                        <hi rend="underline">Gospel</hi> means, good news or glad tidings. Oh! if
                    you were shut up among these poor heathen and could never see your Bible again,
                    never hear any more preaching, how indescribably miserable you would feel. You
                    would long to see the Bible and to hear preaching again, yet how many <del
                        rend="strikethrough">poor</del> people in our country have that Book of
                    Books and will not love it; how many go to church just because it is the
                    fashion, and will not join it, nor love the God of the Bible and prepare to live
                    in Heaven. Oh! it is a sad thought. These who have the opportunity to be
                    Christians and <sic>wont</sic> be good and prepare to go to heaven now, must go
                    where these wicked heathen go-- but alas! it will be too late to repent then.
                    Oh! what gnashing of teeth wailing and lamentation there will be among these who
                    go to hell from America where the Bible is known and the Gospel preached. My
                    constant prayer is that Mother and Pa may make haste and delay not to believe in
                    Jesus and turn unto the Lord. It would be a joy to me greater than the
                    conversion of a hundred heathen to hear that you had joined the Church and were
                    striving to meet me in Heaven. I<pb/><pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_008.jpg"/>never
                    expect to see you again in this world, we have parted forever, unless you are
                    preparing to meet me again in Heaven. Let no consideration keep you from making
                    that preparation. If heaven be lost all is <sic>is</sic> lost. You have lived as
                    it were in vain and Eternity will be too short to repent-- indeed after death is
                    the judgement and there is no more room for repentance. I am at the least, in a
                    straight line, not less than (12,000) twelve thousand miles from you now, and it
                    would take me sixty days and nights on the fastest steamer to reach you, but if
                    we be separated in Eternity-- the distance will be so great that Eternity would
                    be too short a time to cross the gulf that separates between us. It is as near
                        <add place="supralinear">to</add> heaven from China as from America and all
                    I do here I do in view of living there when done with this life of sorrow, for
                    if in this world only we have sorrow and affliction we shall be blessed indeed
                    and happy forever when these light afflictions have wrought out for us that
                    exceeding and eternal <sic>wright</sic> of glory which is reserved for the
                    faithful in Christ. May you my own Dear Mother and Pa and all of you lay up
                    henceforth your treasures in heaven. Shall I meet you there? "'Twould be an
                    assurance most dear to know" that you are expecting to see your absent <hi
                        rend="underline">Young</hi> again in heaven where partings are unknown
                        forever.<closer>Love, much Love to you Mother and Pa and all of you.
                            <salute>Affectionately Your Son-</salute><signed>Young J
                        Allen</signed></closer></p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
