<TEI xml:id="yja-undated2.001" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to Dr Lehon, <date when="1868">1868?</date>, an
                    electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email: beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Dr Lehon, <date when="1868">1868?</date>;
                    Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory
                    University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
		      <item>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-09-01">September 01, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="ypw">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                
<pb facs="Allen_11_FF8_012.jpg"/>

                <head>Letter 3d</head>
                <opener>
                    <salute>My dear Dr. Lehon,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>Having in previous letters nos 1 &#x0026; 2 urged the necessity of qualifying
                    and thrusting out a greater number of vigorous native agents to meet the wants
                    of our work and extend the area of our operations, I will now venture to call
                    your attention to the <hi rend="underline">field</hi> which seems most open and
                        <unclear>assaible</unclear> for the full development of our church system. Our
                    church in spirit and cast is essentially missionary in its organization, based
                    on the great principle that redemption by Christ is general, and that
                    consequently, christianity is a universal remedy for the <hi
                        rend="strikethrough">wants</hi><add place="supralinear">sin</add> and woe of
                    the world, and true to that principle and spirit, it has set to work, accepted
                    the world as its parish, and adopted a system, at once characteristic and
                    competent as a means to the end, of reaching and meeting <unclear>tho</unclear>
                    its wants.</p>
                <p>The success which our church has had in the West during the past century has been
                    unparalleled and marvelous and while we may not claim all the honor of its
                    efficiency as attaching to and belonging to the <unclear>illiteracy</unclear>, yet we
                        <unclear>conceive</unclear> this greater share of its trimphs is due to the
                    ubiquitous and vigorous <unclear>enterprises</unclear> of that system.</p>
                <p>While therefore, we are anxious to see our church established here, and that
                    characteristic and efficient feature of it in large and extensive exercise among
                    this people, (yet we cannot

<pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_013.jpg"/>

                    to discern
                    great embarrassments, and hence great and just reasons for careful consideration
                    of the field that we should broach and occupy in view of the largest measure of
                    success and protracted usefulness.)</p>
                <p>We think it becoming in us, in view of the vastness of this Empire, and the great
                    diversity of its dialects, as well as the utter impossibility <add
                        place="supralinear">inability</add> under which the church suffers <add
                        place="supralinear">labors</add> to meet the demands made upon it to use
                    every caution to make a selection from the numberless dialects and sections of
                    this great country, which shall give us the widest range of efficiency and
                    usefulness.</p>
                <p>As you are aware, and as I have stated above, the country while it is nominally
                    one, governed by the same Emperor and laws, and having the same written and
                    printed characters, is really divided into as many sections or tribes, with
                    altogether different spoken dialects, quite as dissimilar and unintelligible to
                    each other, except by means of the written character as the nations of Europe,
                    who use the roman letters but have an idiom and dialect peculiarly their own. So
                    extensive are these differences that scarcely any two of the ports now open to
                    foreign commerce in China, have the same dialect or are intelligible to each
                    other. These difficulties not only occur on the coast they are
                    more <unclear>numerous</unclear> still in the Interior where each large

<pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_013.jpg"/> 

                    city
                    becomes the center of a different dialect which is gradually shaded down and
                    lost as you proceed still farther beyond. Besides, none of these dialects, admit
                    of being written, no <hi rend="strikethrough">works</hi>
                    <add place="supralinear">books</add> are attempted to be printed in them by the
                    natives. If they read at all, which is exceedingly rare, perhaps about one in a
                    hundred, may have some idea of what a few of the simplest
                        <corr><unclear>char</unclear>[Characters]</corr> are called- they must read the
                        <unclear>terse</unclear>literary style, or the Mandarin which is a simpler
                    style, consequently they have to use what to them is a dead language.</p>
                <p>These remarks apply more particularly to that Section of Country to the South of
                    the great river Yang Tze, where the tribes and dialects are as numerous
                    apparently as their large cities. <hi rend="strikethrough">Having learned one of
                        their dialects, you are</hi> The acquisition of one of them does not qualify
                    you for access to or work among the others, for the natives
                    themselves find it impossible to acquire anything like a proficiency to enable
                    them to communicate very readily. North of the great river however while there
                    exists slight changes in dialect yet the idiom, and expression is the same and
                    apparently had a common origin, in one distinct tribe. Their language is what is
                    
<pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_014.jpg"/>

                    <sic>is</sic>
                    <unclear>usually</unclear> known as the <hi rend="underline">Mandarin</hi>
                    which is both written and <unclear>printed</unclear>. It is the language of the
                        <unclear>Consul</unclear> and has always been, both where the Capital was
                    at Nankin and in Pekin. All <add place="supralinear">
                        <unclear>the</unclear>
                    </add> teachers and tradesmen are supposed to speak and understand more or less
                    of it. It is estimated that 3/4 of the Provinces of the Empire can read it
                    understandingly and that it is the spoken dialect of nearly one half the whole
                    Empire. Through this vast section from Nankin its most southern city you may
                    travel north to Pekin and be readily understood &#x0026; vice versa or from the
                    Shantung province on the eastern coast to the <unclear>far</unclear> interior
                    provinces of Szechuan and Shensi and be also intelligible.</p>
                <p>While in the Southern regions a native preacher would be almost useless away from
                    his own immediate city and dialect, in the north he may travel and preach
                    &#x0026; <add place="supralinear">be</add> understood throughout the whole
                    region.</p>
                <p>These are facts which I think it worth while to notice, in view of our future
                    operations here, for although it is our desire to give all this
                    people, whatever be their dialect, the opportunity of having the gospel
                    &#x0026;c- yet I think it far more compatible with common sense, and the system
                    of </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
