<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Young John Allen to an editor, <date when="1868-01-28">January
                        28, 1868</date>, an electronic edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Young J. Allen</sic>
                            <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
                <date>2008</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University. Emory University
                        makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions made by the Young
                        John Allen Project participants. Emory University makes no claim of
                        copyright to the original text. Permission is granted to download, transmit,
                        or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this
                        work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes,
                        provided that this header is included in its entirety. For further inquiries
                        about this text's availability, please contact:
                        <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                    <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                    <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                    <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to an editor, <date when="1868-01-28">January
                        28, 1868</date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare
                    Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="yja">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Young</forename>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1907-05-30">May 30, 1907 <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                                <country>China</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Mollie">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Mary</forename>
                            <forename>Houston</forename>
                            <surname>Allen</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Ch'i-ho</forename>
                            <surname>Yun</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1865">
                            <placeName>
                                <country>Korea</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1945-12-06">December 6, 1945 </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="wac">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Warren</forename>
                            <forename>Akin</forename>
                            <surname>Candler</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <birth when="1857-08-23">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="county">Carroll County</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </birth>
                        <death when="1941-09-25">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Atlanta</settlement>
                                <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>
                        </death>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="tsoong">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Kia</forename>
                            <forename>Tsing</forename>
                            <surname>Tsoong</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName>
                            <forename>George</forename>
                            <surname>Bell</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>

                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>

                    <place>
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Madison</settlement>/> <region type="state"
                                >Georgia</region>/><country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </place>
                </listPlace>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part of the Young John
                    Allen Letters Project. Project participants intend for this encoded text, as
                    well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for
                    educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded. Paratextual elements may
                    be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF images of each page
                    using either a flatbed scanner. Text pages were captured in color at 400dpi.
                    These digital images were converted to an electronic text file by transcription.
                    The text files produced have been proofread against the original document or a
                    JPEG image of the original. This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                    the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines. For the
                    details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI Guidelines for Best
                    Encoding practices at http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/. Encoders silently
                    replaced em dashes with two dashes. Page numbers and other text such as titles
                    displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear in the
                    original text.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
                <rs type="language">English</rs>
                <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
                <date>1800-1899</date>
            </creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date when="2009-08-03">August 3, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="">Yvette Wright</name> transcribed and encoded the text. </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_015.jpg"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Shanghai, China,</placeName>
                        <date when="1868-01-28">Jan. 28, 1868</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <head>Letter No. 2.</head>
                </opener>
                <p>In a previous letter I informed you, if I mistake not, that the late Tai-ping
                    rebellion was of a two-fold, politico-religious character, and that while they
                    sought the overthrow of the present Tartar dynasty, their chief object both at
                    its beginning and during its progress was the extermination of idolatry. Their
                    iconoclastic fury far surpassed all their other characteristics, and was
                    unabated even to the day of their downfall. Hence, they laid waste in capital,
                    city and country, on islet, lake, river, and mountain, every temple and
                    habitation appropriated to idolatry. I have travelled through a large extent of
                    the country once in their hands and in no place did I find one of ten thousand
                    temples whose idols had not fallen before them. Indeed, so complete an erasure
                    both of images and priests did they effect that idolatry seemed almost, if not
                    entirely and hopelessly, doomed to extinction.</p>
                <p>After the overthrow of the Rebellion and the restoration of the country to Tartar
                    rule, the missionaries were very anxious to follow the returning refugees to
                    their desolated homes and carry with them an effectual antidote against a
                    relapse into the fatal errors and superstitions which formerly duped and
                    beggared them.</p>
                <p>The desire to follow up the openings thus made by the Rebels was the greater, and
                    the entrance more certain and hopeful, from the fact that among those returning
                    were many Christians who desired to carry with them and establish in their midst
                    the Christian Church and its doctrines. Many of us did all we could to enter in,<pb/>
                    <pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_017.jpg"/>but for lack of laborers, both native and
                    foreign, the country seemed destined once more to be given up to idolatry. Judge
                    then of our surprise and joy when we learned at Su Chow, the other day, that the
                    evil day is still put off and the Church has yet another opportunity of entering
                    the field, a large field, amongst a people who are refused the privilege of
                    rebuilding their temples or resorting to idolatry.</p>
                <p>The facts are about these: A large number of Mandarins holding office in the
                    recently desolated region, convinced apparently of the folly of idolatry, its
                    deceptive and impoverishing character, have in the interests of the country
                    petitioned or memorialized the Government to forbid the rebuilding or even the
                    repairing of any of the temples, except the Confucian, which even the Rebels
                    respected. The Emperor had responded favorably, and I was told that a
                    proclamation had been issued accordingly in the region above mentioned. Again,
                    in the city of Su Chow, where I had least <sic>expevted</sic> such a turn in the
                    matter, I was shown a proclamation which was issued about the 25th of December
                    last, by the On toah-sz, or Criminal Judge of this Province, and placarded in
                    the largest thoroughfares and public places, absolutely forbidding women to
                    enter the temples, while idolatry and the priesthood are denounced, the one as
                    vile (encouraging lewdness), and the other as the deceivers of the people, and
                    heavy penalties are threatened against all who dare violate the proclamation by
                    appearing at the temples for purposes of worship. The priests are threatened
                    with the <hi rend="underline">cangue</hi>, or heavy wooden collar, and to be
                    chained at the entrance of their<pb/>
                    <pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_019.jpg"/> temples. The husband of any woman violating is
                    to be held responsible and punished with the bamboo, and the smaller mandarins
                    having jurisdiction are made responsible for the conduct of their several
                    districts, and are threatened with degradation, and other punishment, if they
                    attempt to evade the requirements of the proclamation. </p>
                <p>The people were thunder-struck at the announcement and read the <hi
                        rend="underline">writing on the wall</hi> with awe. I heard the following
                    comment only, "the proclamation savors of the Jesus doctrines; the Judge must
                    belong to the Church."</p>
                <p>On Monday the 20th, we left Su-chow, and in a day and a half reached Kia-Shin-fu
                    in the Che-kiang provinces, about sixty miles to the south of Su-chow. There we
                    found that the highest Mandarin of the place had but a few weeks previously
                    issued a proclamation in obedience to the Governor General who had several
                    months before issued one at Hang-Chow, removing every obstruction out of the way
                    of freely preaching Christianity, and also guaranteeing to the people the utmost
                    religious liberty.</p>
                <p>Mr. Editor, we missionaries at Shanghai are almost overwhelmed by the signs of
                    the times. What do they mean? We are astonished at the revelations that are now
                    apparent. Are not all things working together here to accomplish the purposes of
                    Jehovah? It is not by might nor by power, but by the Spirit of the Lord that
                    Christianity is noiselessly effecting her revolutions in this ancient pagan
                    land. The word of the Lord shall not return unto him void. Oh! how our faith, or
                    rather want of faith, is being rebuked.<pb/>
                    <pb facs="Allen_11_ff8_021.jpg"/></p>
                <p>If there was ever a time for the Church to awake, arise and put her armor on and
                    advance to victory, that time, that opportunity is the present. The Mandarins
                    themselves, though it may be all unconsciously, have arrayed themselves on our
                    side and have set to their powerful arm to arrest the tide of returning
                    superstition, idolatry and death. While, therefore, the Emperor on his throne,
                    and the Madarins in the provinces are proscribing idolatry and inviting
                    Christianity by removing its disabilities, shall the Church cease to pray for
                    the China Mission, withhold its support and deny in future -- at an early day,
                    to send one, five or ten of the score and more missionaries that are now an
                    absolute necessity to secure a tithing of the harvest spread out to the
                    sickle?</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Yours truly,</salute>
                    <signed>Young J. Allen.</signed>
                </closer>
                <p/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
