<TEI>
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title> <date when="1857-05-07">May 7th 1857</date>, an electronic edition</title>
            <author>
            <name type="person">
            <choice>
            <sic>Young</sic>
                <reg>Allen, Young John, 1836-1907.</reg>
            </choice>
            </name>
            </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent></extent>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Emory University, Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Atlanta, Georgia</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <availability>
                <p>&#x00A9; 2008, Lewis H. Beck Center, Emory University.
                    Emory University makes a claim of copyright only to original
                    contributions made by the Young John Allen Project participants.  Emory University makes no claim of copyright to the original text.  Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute, or display the contributions to this work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is included in its entirety.  For further inquiries about this text's availability, please contact:
                    <address><addrLine>Lewis H. Beck Center</addrLine><addrLine>Emory University</addrLine><addrLine>Robert W. Woodruff Library</addrLine><addrLine>Atlanta, GA  30322-0053</addrLine><addrLine>United States of America</addrLine><addrLine>Email:  beckctr@emory.edu</addrLine><addrLine>Website: <ptr target="http://beck.library.emory.edu"/></addrLine></address></p>
            </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Young John Allen Papers</title>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Naomi Nelson</name>
                <name>Alice Hickcox</name>
                <name>Stewart Varner</name>
                <resp>Principal Investigators</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston<date when="1857-05-07">May 7th 1857 </date>; Young John Allen Papers, Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University.</bibl>
            <listPerson>
                <person xml:id="yja">
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Young</forename>
                        <forename>John</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1836-01-03">January 3, 1836
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="county">Burke County</settlement>
                            <region type="state">Georgia</region>
                            <country>United States</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </birth>
                    <death when="1907-03-30">May 30, 1907
                        <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Shanghai</settlement>
                            <country>China</country>
                        </placeName>
                    </death>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <persName>
                        
                    </persName>
                    
                </person>
           
    <!-- you may add other people based on occurrences in your letter, see the Warren Candler letter for more examples -->                         </listPerson>
 
             <listPlace> <!-- add any list places you want to -->
                <place>
                    <placeName>
                        <settlement></settlement>
                        <region></region>
                    </placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This text was created by the Lewis H. Beck Center as a part
                of the Young John Allen Letters Project.  Project participants intend for this encoded text, as well as all texts produced by this project, to be made available on the web for educational, scholarly and pedagogical purposes.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <p>The archival material has been transcribed and encoded.
                Paratextual elements may be provided as digital images only, with some exceptions.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <p>Processing this electronic text file began by creating TIFF
                images of each page using either a flatbed scanner.  Text pages were
                captured in color at 400dpi.  These digital images were converted to
                an electronic text file by transcription.  The text files produced
                have been proofread against the original document or a JPEG image of
                the original.  This proofread text file has then been encoded using
                the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.
                For the details of Level 3 encoding, please see the webpage for TEI
                Guidelines for Best Encoding practices at
                http://www.indiana.edu/~letrs/tei/.  Encoders silently replaced em
                dashes with two dashes.  Page numbers and other text such as titles
                displayed in brackets have been added by the encoder and do not appear
                in the original text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="lcsh">
                <bibl>
                    <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
                </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
        </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <creation>
            <rs type="collection">Young John Allen Papers</rs>
            <rs type="language">English</rs>
            <rs type="geography">United States</rs>
            <date>1800-1899</date> 
        </creation>
        <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="lcsh">
                <list>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                    <item></item>
                </list>
            </keywords>
        </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change>
            <date when="2009-07-15">July 7, 2009</date>
                <name xml:id="">Sue Trowbridge </name>
            transcribed and encoded the text.
        </change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="letter">
    <pb facs="Allen-11-ff3-031.jpg"/>
    <head>[Letter from Young John Allen to Mollie Houston]</head>
    <opener><dateline><name type="place">E. C. Oxford Geo.</name><date when="1857-05-07">May 7th 1857</date></dateline><lb/>
        <salute>My <hi rend="underline">own </hi>Dear <hi rend="underline">"Mary,"</hi> </salute></opener>
    <p>I have a few minutes of leisure to night that I desire to spend in communion with <add place="supralinear">my</add> the absent <hi rend="underline">beloved one</hi>.-  I have been unusually cheerful this evening and to night I have (in private meditation and prayer) enjoyed much of the presence and sweet influence of the Holy Spirit-  My Dear Mollie, I do love God, and I feel it <hi rend="underline">now</hi>, and I love to praise his name- I love to think of heaven, and of Christ and to give myself to his service-  Bless God with one my <hi rend="underline">own Mollie</hi>, and help me to magnify his grace and his glory-  Oh!  Can't you say with me this happy night, Mollie
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff3-032.jpg"/>
        "Jesus I <hi rend="underline">my cross</hi> have taken <hi rend="underline">All to leave and follow Thee</hi>," don't you feel willing to <hi rend="underline">leave all</hi> and count the treasures, the riches, the honors and glories of this world as but loss and worse than nought that you may <unclear>?</unclear>, that you may <hi rend="underline">live</hi> for Christ, tha you may be a useful and happy Christian, a faithful Servant in the vineyard of the Lord?  Yes, thank the Lord, My <hi rend="underline">Dear One</hi>, I know you are willing and  that you are striving thus to glorify God with me your very unworthy but devoted One-  Yes I do bless the Lord with my <hi rend="underline">whole Soul</hi> when I think of it, that you are so devoted and attached to the Cause of ourBlessed Savior, that it is always first in your thoughts, the first in your private <hi rend="underline">soul</hi>-communings, the first and chiefest of all your writings, in your correspondence not only to him who now writes, but <del rend="strikethrough">to </del>those who love you  so dearly and who look so much and so fonfidently to you as a counselor and example, as a pattern for piety and <unclear>???</unclear> trust and submissive to the will and way of the Lord-  Oh!  <hi rend="underline">my Dear</hi>, if you knew my heart this moment, which now <hi rend="underline">it</hi> writes, you wuld understand perhaps how it is that I so much rejoic-  But as it is, I <hi rend="underline">know</hi> it's so.  Bless God, and that's all I can tell you now--  I got some of your old Letters this evening, Mollie, and read them, some that you wrote while in La Grange, some that you wrote me in reference to your soul's interest, about religion, about joining the church, about devoting yourself entirely to God,
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff3-033.jpg"/>
        and oh! how quick my mind run back and traced up the history of the fast-  I love at times to recur to those happy days, to live over again, as it were, the scenes and days that memory alone can recall-  But Oh! how different now is every thing, how changed the scene that presents itself, how different the circumstances that surround us-  Oh! how different <hi rend="underline">we ourselves</hi> are-
    </p>
    <p>All Glory be to God- for he it is that has changed our poor souls, our hearts, our lives, and given us the:<hi rend="underline">new song</hi>,""established our goings," and planted our feet upon "the Rock Christ Jesus"-  Yes all Glory be to god, that where as once we were blind now we see, that through we were
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff3-034.jpg"/>
        lost and guilty wretches now we are found and pardoned and permitted to rejoice in hope of heaven- <hi rend="underline">Yes Glory be to God</hi>, ca't you say it <hi rend="underline">too</hi> My Dear Mollie?  Christ has forgiven all our sins, washed our souls and cleased them in the fountain of his own blood-  Can't you rejoice this night, and say thank God!  <hi rend="underline">Thank God</hi>!  I am on my journey home, yes <hi rend="underline">home</hi>, to Canaan, to heaven, my happy home, my long <hi rend="underline">sought home</hi>, yes that you are bound <hi rend="underline">to die in the army</hi>, in the service of you <hi rend="underline">dear Jesus</hi>-  Oh! my soul! farewell vain delusive world, I know you often say, and your soul mounted on faith and winged by prayer, sums up the <hi rend="underline">shining way</hi> to see and praise your God, the spring of <hi rend="underline">all</hi> your joys and life of <hi rend="underline">all</hi> your delight.
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff3-035.jpg"/>
        Oh! does not each day bring some fresh memorial of his grace, make some precious promise still more sweet, some sacred word still more dear- do you not each day have much to praise and <unclear>magnify?</unclear> the Lord for, do you not find his word still more and more interesting and full of life more precious- and Oh! do you not feel daily a hungering and thirsting after righteousness, after a <hi rend="underline">greater <choice><sic>fulness</sic><corr>fullness</corr></choice></hi> of God, after a more pervect image and likeness and conformity of your Savior and to his will?  do you not grow in grace, in the knowledge of God, in acquaintance with your own deceitful and wicked heart?  do you not see your prospects brightening for the upper and better Kingdom even though the world is darking all around,are not your hopes renewed, those glorious hopes of the Christian that cheer our pilgrimages while here on earth we stay?  Yes, yes, My Dear One, I do bless God for the triumphs of his grace and the strength of his spirit which has been vouchsafed you so recently-  I know the Lord is with you and he will all the time sustain and comfort you, Mollie, if you will put your trus in him-  Strive to live, Dear One, by faith, by <hi rend="underlined">naked faith</hi> in the word, in the promises and the willingness of Christ to do <hi rend="underline">anything </hi>for us, to grant us <hi rend="underline">anything</hi> whatsoever that we ask for, that will be for our good and his glory- lean upon his strong arm, my Dear, when you are weak, he will support and strengthen you for all the trials, conflicts and temptations with which this world shall harrass and <unclear>?</unclear>
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff3-036.jpg"/>
        My Dear Mollie I am so glad that you so cheerfully give me your experiences, it does me great good, it cheers me much; and Bless God my <hi rend="underline">own</hi> Mollie, I feel that it draws out my soul with yours and bears it up toward heaven, I feel that it causes me, (and does it not you, too) to "delight more and more in the law of the Lord," and to "meditate in it day and night;" It points us both to the path of the <hi rend="underline">just man</hi>, to his upward and holy flight, which "shineth more and more, says Psalmist, unto the perfect day."-
    </p>
    <p>Let us put our trust entirely in the Lord, Dear Mollie, and then we shall fear no harm and no danger shall befall us (that is, <hi rend="underline">our souls</hi>, whatever may attach this body but we shall be always praising God and looking frward to that happy day the day of deliverance when
        <pb facs="Allen-11-ff3-037.jpg"/>
        from earth set free, "we shall go marching home together," yes home to that happy place where Jesus reigns and saints and angels dwell-        
    </p>
    <p>I will close now for this time to resume the next leisure opportunity, by committing you to the Lord with the sincere prayer, my beloved, for his spirit and presence to always attend, and give you great peace and joy, great strength <add place="supralinear">of</add> faith in approaching his presence, and for the realization and appropriation of all those precious promises which Christ holds out to us-  Oh! that you may always exercise that meek, simple, childlike faith and confidence in coming to God that we see the little child exercise towards the earthly parents-  May God bless, and keep <h rend="underline">my Dear Beloved One</h> this night for Christ's sake-  Thine <hi rend="underline">own</hi> and thine alone
        <lb/>
        <signed><persname>Young</persname></signed>
        
    </p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
    </TEI>